<div type="episode" n="01">
<p rend="inset"><lb n="010000"/>I</p>
<p><lb n="010001"/>Stately, plump Buck Mulligan came from the stairhead, bearing a
<lb n="010002"/>bowl of lather on which a mirror and a razor lay crossed. A yellow
<lb n="010003"/>dressinggown, ungirdled, was sustained gently behind him on the mild
<lb n="010004"/>morning air. He held the bowl aloft and intoned:
<lb n="010005"/><said who="bm">―<quote xml:lang="la">Introibo ad altare Dei.</quote></said></p>
<p><lb n="010006"/>Halted, he peered down the dark winding stairs and called out
<lb n="010007"/>coarsely:
<lb n="010008"/><said who="bm">―Come up, Kinch! Come up, you fearful jesuit!</said></p>
<p><lb n="010009"/>Solemnly he came forward and mounted the round gunrest. He faced
<lb n="010010"/>about and blessed gravely thrice the tower, the surrounding land and the
<lb n="010011"/>awaking mountains. Then, catching sight of Stephen Dedalus, he bent
<lb n="010012"/>towards him and made rapid crosses in the air, gurgling in his throat and
<lb n="010013"/>shaking his head. Stephen Dedalus, displeased and sleepy, leaned his arms
<lb n="010014"/>on the top of the staircase and looked coldly at the shaking gurgling face
<lb n="010015"/>that blessed him, equine in its length, and at the light untonsured hair,
<lb n="010016"/>grained and hued like pale oak.</p>
<p><lb n="010017"/>Buck Mulligan peeped an instant under the mirror and then covered
<lb n="010018"/>the bowl smartly.
<lb n="010019"/><said who="bm">―Back to barracks!</said> he said sternly.</p>
<p><lb n="010020"/>He added in a preacher's tone:
<lb n="010021"/><said who="bm">―For this, O dearly beloved, is the genuine christine: body and soul and
<lb n="010022"/>blood and ouns. Slow music, please. Shut your eyes, gents. One moment. A
<lb n="010023"/>little trouble about those white corpuscles. Silence, all.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010024"/>He peered sideways up and gave a long slow whistle of call, then
<lb n="010025"/>paused awhile in rapt attention, his even white teeth glistening here and
  <lb n="010026"/>there with gold points. <said who="bm" aloud="false">Chrysostomos.</said> Two strong shrill whistles answered
<lb n="010027"/>through the calm.
<lb n="010028"/><said who="bm">―Thanks, old chap,</said> he cried briskly. <said who="bm">That will do nicely. Switch off the
<lb n="010029"/>current, will you?</said></p>
<p><lb n="010030"/>He skipped off the gunrest and looked gravely at his watcher,
<lb n="010031"/>gathering about his legs the loose folds of his gown. The plump shadowed
<lb n="010032"/>face and sullen oval jowl recalled a prelate, patron of arts in the middle
<lb n="010033"/>ages. A pleasant smile broke quietly over his lips.
<lb n="010034"/><said who="bm">―The mockery of it!</said> he said gaily. <said who="bm">Your absurd name, an ancient Greek!</said></p>
<p><lb n="010035"/>He pointed his finger in friendly jest and went over to the parapet,
<lb n="010036"/>laughing to himself. Stephen Dedalus stepped up, followed him wearily
<lb n="010037"/>halfway and sat down on the edge of the gunrest, watching him still as he
<lb n="010038"/>propped his mirror on the parapet, dipped the brush in the bowl and
<lb n="010039"/>lathered cheeks and neck.</p>
<p><lb n="010040"/>Buck Mulligan's gay voice went on.
<lb n="010041"/><said who="bm">―My name is absurd too: Malachi Mulligan, two dactyls. But it has a
<lb n="010042"/>Hellenic ring, hasn't it? Tripping and sunny like the buck himself. We must
<lb n="010043"/>go to Athens. Will you come if I can get the aunt to fork out twenty quid?</said></p>
<p><lb n="010044"/>He laid the brush aside and, laughing with delight, cried:
<lb n="010045"/><said who="bm">―Will he come? The jejune jesuit!</said></p>
<p><lb n="010046"/>Ceasing, he began to shave with care.
<lb n="010047"/><said who="sd">―Tell me, Mulligan,</said> Stephen said quietly.
<lb n="010048"/><said who="bm">―Yes, my love?</said>
<lb n="010049"/><said who="sd">―How long is Haines going to stay in this tower?</said></p>
<p><lb n="010050"/>Buck Mulligan showed a shaven cheek over his right shoulder.
<lb n="010051"/><said who="bm">―God, isn't he dreadful?</said> he said frankly. <said who="bm">A ponderous Saxon. He thinks
<lb n="010052"/>you're not a gentleman. God, these bloody English! Bursting with money
<lb n="010053"/>and indigestion. Because he comes from Oxford. You know, Dedalus, you
<lb n="010054"/>have the real Oxford manner. He can't make you out. O, my name for you
<lb n="010055"/>is the best: Kinch, the knifeblade.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010056"/>He shaved warily over his chin.
<lb n="010057"/><said who="sd">―He was raving all night about a black panther,</said> Stephen said. <said who="sd">Where is his
<lb n="010058"/>guncase?</said>
<lb n="010059"/><said who="bm">―A woful lunatic!</said> Mulligan said. <said who="bm">Were you in a funk?</said>
<lb n="010060"/><said who="sd">―I was,</said> Stephen said with energy and growing fear. <said who="sd">Out here in the dark
<lb n="010061"/>with a man I don't know raving and moaning to himself about shooting a
<lb n="010062"/>black panther. You saved men from drowning. I'm not a hero, however. If
<lb n="010063"/>he stays on here I am off.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010064"/>Buck Mulligan frowned at the lather on his razorblade. He hopped
<lb n="010065"/>down from his perch and began to search his trouser pockets hastily.
<lb n="010066"/><said who="bm">―Scutter!</said> he cried thickly.</p>
<p><lb n="010067"/>He came over to the gunrest and, thrusting a hand into Stephen's
<lb n="010068"/>upper pocket, said:
<lb n="010069"/><said who="bm">―Lend us a loan of your noserag to wipe my razor.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010070"/>Stephen suffered him to pull out and hold up on show by its corner a
<lb n="010071"/>dirty crumpled handkerchief. Buck Mulligan wiped the razorblade neatly.
<lb n="010072"/>Then, gazing over the handkerchief, he said:
<lb n="010073"/><said who="bm">―The bard's noserag! A new art colour for our Irish poets: snotgreen. You
<lb n="010074"/>can almost taste it, can't you?</said></p>
<p><lb n="010075"/>He mounted to the parapet again and gazed out over Dublin bay, his
<lb n="010076"/>fair oakpale hair stirring slightly.
<lb n="010077"/><said who="bm">―God!</said> he said quietly. <said who="bm">Isn't the sea what Algy calls it: <quote rend="none">a great sweet
<lb n="010078"/>mother?</quote> The snotgreen sea. The scrotumtightening sea. <quote xml:lang="grc-Latn">Epi oinopa ponton.</quote>
<lb n="010079"/>Ah, Dedalus, the Greeks! I must teach you. You must read them in the
<lb n="010080"/>original. <quote xml:lang="grc-Latin">Thalatta! Thalatta!</quote> She is our great sweet mother. Come and
<lb n="010081"/>look.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010082"/>Stephen stood up and went over to the parapet. Leaning on it he
<lb n="010083"/>looked down on the water and on the mailboat clearing the harbourmouth
<lb n="010084"/>of Kingstown.
<lb n="010085"/><said who="bm">―Our mighty mother!</said> Buck Mulligan said.</p>
<p><lb n="010086"/>He turned abruptly his grey searching eyes from the sea to Stephen's
<lb n="010087"/>face.
<lb n="010088"/><said who="bm">―The aunt thinks you killed your mother,</said> he said. <said who="bm">That's why she won't let
<lb n="010089"/>me have anything to do with you.</said>
<lb n="010090"/><said who="sd">―Someone killed her,</said> Stephen said gloomily.
<lb n="010091"/><said who="bm">―You could have knelt down, damn it, Kinch, when your dying mother
<lb n="010092"/>asked you,</said> Buck Mulligan said. <said who="bm">I'm hyperborean as much as you. But to
<lb n="010093"/>think of your mother begging you with her last breath to kneel down and
<lb n="010094"/>pray for her. And you refused. There is something sinister in you ....</said></p>
<p><lb n="010095"/>He broke off and lathered again lightly his farther cheek. A tolerant
<lb n="010096"/>smile curled his lips.
<lb n="010097"/><said who="bm">―But a lovely mummer!</said> he murmured to himself. <said who="bm">Kinch, the loveliest
<lb n="010098"/>mummer of them all!</said></p>
<p><lb n="010099"/>He shaved evenly and with care, in silence, seriously.</p>
<p><lb n="010100"/>Stephen, an elbow rested on the jagged granite, leaned his palm
<lb n="010101"/>against his brow and gazed at the fraying edge of his shiny black coatsleeve.
<lb n="010102"/>Pain, that was not yet the pain of love, fretted his heart. Silently, in a dream
<lb n="010103"/>she had come to him after her death, her wasted body within its loose
<lb n="010104"/>brown graveclothes giving off an odour of wax and rosewood, her breath,
<lb n="010105"/>that had bent upon him, mute, reproachful, a faint odour of wetted ashes.
<lb n="010106"/>Across the threadbare cuffedge he saw the sea hailed as a great sweet
<lb n="010107"/>mother by the wellfed voice beside him. The ring of bay and skyline held a
<lb n="010108"/>dull green mass of liquid. A bowl of white china had stood beside her
<lb n="010109"/>deathbed holding the green sluggish bile which she had torn up from her
<lb n="010110"/>rotting liver by fits of loud groaning vomiting.</p>
<p><lb n="010111"/>Buck Mulligan wiped again his razorblade.
<lb n="010112"/><said who="bm">―Ah, poor dogsbody!</said> he said in a kind voice. <said who="bm">I must give you a shirt and a
<lb n="010113"/>few noserags. How are the secondhand breeks?</said>
<lb n="010114"/><said who="sd">―They fit well enough,</said> Stephen answered.</p>
<p><lb n="010115"/>Buck Mulligan attacked the hollow beneath his underlip.
<lb n="010116"/><said who="bm">―The mockery of it,</said> he said contentedly. <said who="bm">Secondleg they should be. God
<lb n="010117"/>knows what poxy bowsy left them off. I have a lovely pair with a hair stripe,
<lb n="010118"/>grey. You'll look spiffing in them. I'm not joking, Kinch. You look damn
<lb n="010119"/>well when you're dressed.</said>
<lb n="010120"/><said who="sd">―Thanks,</said> Stephen said. <said who="sd">I can't wear them if they are grey.</said>
<lb n="010121"/><said who="bm">―He can't wear them,</said> Buck Mulligan told his face in the mirror. <said who="bm">Etiquette
<lb n="010122"/>is etiquette. He kills his mother but he can't wear grey trousers.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010123"/>He folded his razor neatly and with stroking palps of fingers felt the
<lb n="010124"/>smooth skin.</p>
<p><lb n="010125"/>Stephen turned his gaze from the sea and to the plump face with its
<lb n="010126"/>smokeblue mobile eyes.
<lb n="010127"/><said who="bm">―That fellow I was with in the Ship last night,</said> said Buck Mulligan, <said who="bm">says
<lb n="010128"/>you have g. p. i. He's up in Dottyville with Connolly Norman. General
<lb n="010129"/>paralysis of the insane!</said></p>
<p><lb n="010130"/>He swept the mirror a half circle in the air to flash the tidings abroad
<lb n="010131"/>in sunlight now radiant on the sea. His curling shaven lips laughed and the
<lb n="010132"/>edges of his white glittering teeth. Laughter seized all his strong wellknit
<lb n="010133"/>trunk.
<lb n="010134"/><said who="bm">―Look at yourself,</said> he said, <said who="bm">you dreadful bard!</said></p>
<p><lb n="010135"/>Stephen bent forward and peered at the mirror held out to him, cleft
<lb n="010136"/>by a crooked crack. <said who="sd" aloud="false">Hair on end. As he and others see me. Who chose this
<lb n="010137"/>face for me? This dogsbody to rid of vermin. It asks me too.</said>
<lb n="010138"/><said who="bm">―I pinched it out of the skivvy's room,</said> Buck Mulligan said. <said who="bm">It does her all
<lb n="010139"/>right. The aunt always keeps plainlooking servants for Malachi. Lead him
<lb n="010140"/>not into temptation. And her name is Ursula.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010141"/>Laughing again, he brought the mirror away from Stephen's peering
<lb n="010142"/>eyes.
<lb n="010143"/><said who="bm">―The rage of Caliban at not seeing his face in a mirror,</said> he said. <said who="bm">If Wilde
<lb n="010144"/>were only alive to see you!</said></p>
<p><lb n="010145"/>Drawing back and pointing, Stephen said with bitterness:
<lb n="010146"/><said who="sd">―It is a symbol of Irish art. The cracked lookingglass of a servant.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010147"/>Buck Mulligan suddenly linked his arm in Stephen's and walked with
<lb n="010148"/>him round the tower, his razor and mirror clacking in the pocket where he
<lb n="010149"/>had thrust them.
<lb n="010150"/><said who="bm">―It's not fair to tease you like that, Kinch, is it?</said> he said kindly. <said who="bm">God knows
<lb n="010151"/>you have more spirit than any of them.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010152"/><said who="sd" aloud="false">Parried again. He fears the lancet of my art as I fear that of his. The
<lb n="010153"/>cold steel pen.</said>
<lb n="010154"/><said who="bm">―Cracked lookingglass of a servant! Tell that to the oxy chap downstairs
<lb n="010155"/>and touch him for a guinea. He's stinking with money and thinks you're
<lb n="010156"/>not a gentleman. His old fellow made his tin by selling jalap to Zulus or
<lb n="010157"/>some bloody swindle or other. God, Kinch, if you and I could only work
<lb n="010158"/>together we might do something for the island. Hellenise it.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010159"/>Cranly's arm. His arm.
<lb n="010160"/><said who="bm">―And to think of your having to beg from these swine. I'm the only one
<lb n="010161"/>that knows what you are. Why don't you trust me more? What have you up
<lb n="010162"/>your nose against me? Is it Haines? If he makes any noise here I'll bring
<lb n="010163"/>down Seymour and we'll give him a ragging worse than they gave Clive
<lb n="010164"/>Kempthorpe.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010165"/>Young shouts of moneyed voices in Clive Kempthorpe's rooms.
<lb n="010166"/>Palefaces: they hold their ribs with laughter, one clasping another. O, I
<lb n="010167"/>shall expire! Break the news to her gently, Aubrey! I shall die! With slit
<lb n="010168"/>ribbons of his shirt whipping the air he hops and hobbles round the table,
<lb n="010169"/>with trousers down at heels, chased by Ades of Magdalen with the tailor's
<lb n="010170"/>shears. A scared calf's face gilded with marmalade. I don't want to be
<lb n="010171"/>debagged! Don't you play the giddy ox with me!</p>
<p><lb n="010172"/>Shouts from the open window startling evening in the quadrangle. A
<lb n="010173"/>deaf gardener, aproned, masked with Matthew Arnold's face, pushes his
<lb n="010174"/>mower on the sombre lawn watching narrowly the dancing motes of
<lb n="010175"/>grasshalms.</p>
<p><lb n="010176"/>To ourselves .... new paganism .... <foreign xml:lang="grc-Latin">omphalos</foreign>.
<lb n="010177"/><said who="sd">―Let him stay,</said> Stephen said. <said who="sd">There's nothing wrong with him except at
<lb n="010178"/>night.</said>
<lb n="010179"/><said who="bm">―Then what is it?</said> Buck Mulligan asked impatiently. <said who="bm">Cough it up. I'm quite
<lb n="010180"/>frank with you. What have you against me now?</said></p>
<p><lb n="010181"/>They halted, looking towards the blunt cape of Bray Head that lay on
<lb n="010182"/>the water like the snout of a sleeping whale. Stephen freed his arm quietly.
<lb n="010183"/><said who="sd">―Do you wish me to tell you?</said> he asked.
<lb n="010184"/><said who="bm">―Yes, what is it?</said> Buck Mulligan answered. <said who="bm">I don't remember anything.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010185"/>He looked in Stephen's face as he spoke. A light wind passed his
<lb n="010186"/>brow, fanning softly his fair uncombed hair and stirring silver points of
<lb n="010187"/>anxiety in his eyes.</p>
<p><lb n="010188"/>Stephen, depressed by his own voice, said:
<lb n="010189"/><said who="sd">―Do you remember the first day I went to your house after my mother's
<lb n="010190"/>death?</said></p>
<p><lb n="010191"/>Buck Mulligan frowned quickly and said:
<lb n="010192"/><said who="bm">―What? Where? I can't remember anything. I remember only ideas and
<lb n="010193"/>sensations. Why? What happened in the name of God?</said>
<lb n="010194"/><said who="sd">―You were making tea,</said> Stephen said, <said who="sd">and went across the landing to get
<lb n="010195"/>more hot water. Your mother and some visitor came out of the
<lb n="010196"/>drawingroom. She asked you who was in your room.</said>
<lb n="010197"/><said who="bm">―Yes?</said> Buck Mulligan said. <said who="bm">What did I say? I forget.</said>
<lb n="010198"/><said who="sd">―You said,</said> Stephen answered, <said who="sd"><said who="bm" direct="false" rend="italics">O, it's only Dedalus whose mother is beastly
<lb n="010199"/>dead</said>.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010200"/>A flush which made him seem younger and more engaging rose to
<lb n="010201"/>Buck Mulligan's cheek.
<lb n="010202"/><said who="bm">―Did I say that?</said> he asked. <said who="bm">Well? What harm is that?</said></p>
<p><lb n="010203"/>He shook his constraint from him nervously.
<lb n="010204"/><said who="bm">―And what is death,</said> he asked, <said who="bm">your mother's or yours or my own? You
<lb n="010205"/>saw only your mother die. I see them pop off every day in the Mater and
<lb n="010206"/>Richmond and cut up into tripes in the dissectingroom. It's a beastly thing
<lb n="010207"/>and nothing else. It simply doesn't matter. You wouldn't kneel down to
<lb n="010208"/>pray for your mother on her deathbed when she asked you. Why? Because
<lb n="010209"/>you have the cursed jesuit strain in you, only it's injected the wrong way.
<lb n="010210"/>To me it's all a mockery and beastly. Her cerebral lobes are not
<lb n="010211"/>functioning. She calls the doctor sir Peter Teazle and picks buttercups off
<lb n="010212"/>the quilt. Humour her till it's over. You crossed her last wish in death and
<lb n="010213"/>yet you sulk with me because I don't whinge like some hired mute from
<lb n="010214"/>Lalouette's. Absurd! I suppose I did say it. I didn't mean to offend the
<lb n="010215"/>memory of your mother.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010216"/>He had spoken himself into boldness. Stephen, shielding the gaping
<lb n="010217"/>wounds which the words had left in his heart, said very coldly:
<lb n="010218"/><said who="sd">―I am not thinking of the offence to my mother.</said>
<lb n="010219"/><said who="bm">―Of what then?</said> Buck Mulligan asked.
<lb n="010220"/><said who="sd">―Of the offence to me,</said> Stephen answered.</p>
<p><lb n="010221"/>Buck Mulligan swung round on his heel.
<lb n="010222"/><said who="bm">―O, an impossible person!</said> he exclaimed.</p>
<p><lb n="010223"/>He walked off quickly round the parapet. Stephen stood at his post,
<lb n="010224"/>gazing over the calm sea towards the headland. Sea and headland now
<lb n="010225"/>grew dim. Pulses were beating in his eyes, veiling their sight, and he felt the
<lb n="010226"/>fever of his cheeks.</p>
<p><lb n="010227"/>A voice within the tower called loudly:
<lb n="010228"/><said who="ha">―Are you up there, Mulligan?</said>
<lb n="010229"/><said who="bm">―I'm coming,</said> Buck Mulligan answered.</p>
<p><lb n="010230"/>He turned towards Stephen and said:
<lb n="010231"/><said who="bm">―Look at the sea. What does it care about offences? Chuck Loyola, Kinch,
<lb n="010232"/>and come on down. The Sassenach wants his morning rashers.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010233"/>His head halted again for a moment at the top of the staircase, level
<lb n="010234"/>with the roof:
<lb n="010235"/><said who="bm">―Don't mope over it all day,</said> he said. <said who="bm">I'm inconsequent. Give up the moody
<lb n="010236"/>brooding.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010237"/>His head vanished but the drone of his descending voice boomed out
<lb n="010238"/>of the stairhead:</p>
<lb n="010239"/><said who="bm">―<quote><lg rend="italics"><l>And no more turn aside and brood</l>
<lb n="010240"/><l>Upon love's bitter mystery</l>
<lb n="010241"/><l>For Fergus rules the brazen cars.</l></lg></quote></said>
<p><lb n="010242"/>Woodshadows floated silently by through the morning peace from the
<lb n="010243"/>stairhead seaward where he gazed. Inshore and farther out the mirror of
<lb n="010244"/>water whitened, spurned by lightshod hurrying feet. White breast of the
<lb n="010245"/>dim sea. The twining stresses, two by two. A hand plucking the harpstrings,
<lb n="010246"/>merging their twining chords. Wavewhite wedded words shimmering on the
<lb n="010247"/>dim tide.</p>
<p><lb n="010248"/>A cloud began to cover the sun slowly, wholly, shadowing the bay in
<lb n="010249"/>deeper green. It lay beneath him, a bowl of bitter waters. <said who="sd" aloud="false">Fergus' song: I
<lb n="010250"/>sang it alone in the house, holding down the long dark chords. Her door
<lb n="010251"/>was open: she wanted to hear my music. Silent with awe and pity I went to
<lb n="010252"/>her bedside. She was crying in her wretched bed. For those words, Stephen:
<lb n="010253"/>love's bitter mystery.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010254"/>Where now?</p>
<p><lb n="010255"/>Her secrets: old featherfans, tasselled dancecards, powdered with
<lb n="010256"/>musk, a gaud of amber beads in her locked drawer. A birdcage hung in the
<lb n="010257"/>sunny window of her house when she was a girl. She heard old Royce sing
<lb n="010258"/>in the pantomime of <title type="pantomime">Turko the Terrible</title> and laughed with others when he
<lb n="010259"/>sang:</p>
<said who="or" direct="false"><quote><lg rend="italics"><lb n="010260"/><l>I am the boy</l>
<lb n="010261"/><l>That can enjoy</l>
<lb n="010262"/><l>Invisibility.</l></lg></quote></said>
<p><lb n="010263"/>Phantasmal mirth, folded away: muskperfumed.</p>
<quote><lg rend="italics"><lb n="010264"/><l>And no more turn aside and brood.</l></lg></quote>
<p><lb n="010265"/>Folded away in the memory of nature with her toys. Memories beset
<lb n="010266"/>his brooding brain. Her glass of water from the kitchen tap when she had
<lb n="010267"/>approached the sacrament. A cored apple, filled with brown sugar, roasting
<lb n="010268"/>for her at the hob on a dark autumn evening. Her shapely fingernails
<lb n="010269"/>reddened by the blood of squashed lice from the children's shirts.</p>
<p><lb n="010270"/>In a dream, silently, she had come to him, her wasted body within its
<lb n="010271"/>loose graveclothes giving off an odour of wax and rosewood, her breath,
<lb n="010272"/>bent over him with mute secret words, a faint odour of wetted ashes.</p>
<p><lb n="010273"/><said who="sd" aloud="false">Her glazing eyes, staring out of death, to shake and bend my soul. On
<lb n="010274"/>me alone. The ghostcandle to light her agony. Ghostly light on the tortured
<lb n="010275"/>face. Her hoarse loud breath rattling in horror, while all prayed on their
<lb n="010276"/>knees. Her eyes on me to strike me down. <quote xml:lang="la">Liliata rutilantium te confessorum
<lb n="010277"/>turma circumdet: iubilantium te virginum chorus excipiat.</quote></p>
<p><lb n="010278"/>Ghoul! Chewer of corpses!</p>
<p><lb n="010279"/>No, mother! Let me be and let me live.</said>
<lb n="010280"/><said who="bm">―Kinch ahoy!</said></p>
<p><lb n="010281"/>Buck Mulligan's voice sang from within the tower. It came nearer up
<lb n="010282"/>the staircase, calling again. Stephen, still trembling at his soul's cry, heard
<lb n="010283"/>warm running sunlight and in the air behind him friendly words.
<lb n="010284"/><said who="bm">―Dedalus, come down, like a good mosey. Breakfast is ready. Haines is
<lb n="010285"/>apologising for waking us last night. It's all right.</said>
<lb n="010286"/><said who="sd">―I'm coming,</said> Stephen said, turning.
<lb n="010287"/><said who="bm">―Do, for Jesus' sake,</said> Buck Mulligan said. <said who="bm">For my sake and for all our
<lb n="010288"/>sakes.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010289"/>His head disappeared and reappeared.
<lb n="010290"/><said who="bm">―I told him your symbol of Irish art. He says it's very clever. Touch him
<lb n="010291"/>for a quid, will you? A guinea, I mean.</said>
<lb n="010292"/><said who="sd">―I get paid this morning,</said> Stephen said.
<lb n="010293"/><said who="bm">―The school kip?</said> Buck Mulligan said. <said who="bm">How much? Four quid? Lend us
<lb n="010294"/>one.</said>
<lb n="010295"/><said who="sd">―If you want it,</said> Stephen said.
<lb n="010296"/><said who="bm">―Four shining sovereigns,</said> Buck Mulligan cried with delight. <said who="bm">We'll have a
<lb n="010297"/>glorious drunk to astonish the druidy druids. Four omnipotent sovereigns.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010298"/>He flung up his hands and tramped down the stone stairs, singing out
<lb n="010299"/>of tune with a Cockney accent:</p>
<lb n="010300"/><said who="bm">―<quote><lg rend="italics"><l>O, won't we have a merry time,</l>
<lb n="010301"/><l>Drinking whisky, beer and wine!</l>
<lb n="010302"/><l>On coronation,</l>
<lb n="010303"/><l>Coronation day!</l>
<lb n="010304"/><l>O, won't we have a merry time</l>
<lb n="010305"/><l>On coronation day!</l></lg></quote></said>
<p><lb n="010306"/>Warm sunshine merrying over the sea. The nickel shavingbowl shone,
<lb n="010307"/>forgotten, on the parapet. <said who="sd" aloud="false">Why should I bring it down? Or leave it there all
<lb n="010308"/>day, forgotten friendship?</said></p>
<p><lb n="010309"/>He went over to it, held it in his hands awhile, feeling its coolness,
<lb n="010310"/>smelling the clammy slaver of the lather in which the brush was stuck. <said who="sd" aloud="false">So I
<lb n="010311"/>carried the boat of incense then at Clongowes. I am another now and yet
<lb n="010312"/>the same. A servant too. A server of a servant.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010313"/>In the gloomy domed livingroom of the tower Buck Mulligan's
<lb n="010314"/>gowned form moved briskly to and fro about the hearth, hiding and
<lb n="010315"/>revealing its yellow glow. Two shafts of soft daylight fell across the flagged
<lb n="010316"/>floor from the high barbacans: and at the meeting of their rays a cloud of
<lb n="010317"/>coalsmoke and fumes of fried grease floated, turning.
<lb n="010318"/><said who="bm">―We'll be choked,</said> Buck Mulligan said. <said who="bm">Haines, open that door, will you?</said></p>
<p><lb n="010319"/>Stephen laid the shavingbowl on the locker. A tall figure rose from the
<lb n="010320"/>hammock where it had been sitting, went to the doorway and pulled open
<lb n="010321"/>the inner doors.
<lb n="010322"/><said who="ha">―Have you the key?</said> a voice asked.
<lb n="010323"/><said who="bm">―Dedalus has it,</said> Buck Mulligan said. <said who="bm">Janey Mack, I'm choked!</said></p>
<p><lb n="010324"/>He howled, without looking up from the fire:
<lb n="010325"/><said who="bm">―Kinch!</said>
<lb n="010326"/><said who="sd">―It's in the lock,</said> Stephen said, coming forward.</p>
<p><lb n="010327"/>The key scraped round harshly twice and, when the heavy door had
<lb n="010328"/>been set ajar, welcome light and bright air entered. Haines stood at the
<lb n="010329"/>doorway, looking out. Stephen haled his upended valise to the table and sat
<lb n="010330"/>down to wait. Buck Mulligan tossed the fry on to the dish beside him. Then
<lb n="010331"/>he carried the dish and a large teapot over to the table, set them down
<lb n="010332"/>heavily and sighed with relief.
<lb n="010333"/><said who="bm">―I'm melting,</said> he said, <said who="bm">as the candle remarked when .... But, hush! Not a
<lb n="010334"/>word more on that subject! Kinch, wake up! Bread, butter, honey. Haines,
<lb n="010335"/>come in. The grub is ready. Bless us, O Lord, and these thy gifts. Where's
<lb n="010336"/>the sugar? O, jay, there's no milk.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010337"/>Stephen fetched the loaf and the pot of honey and the buttercooler
<lb n="010338"/>from the locker. Buck Mulligan sat down in a sudden pet.
<lb n="010339"/><said who="bm">―What sort of a kip is this?</said> he said. <said who="bm">I told her to come after eight.</said>
<lb n="010340"/><said who="sd">―We can drink it black,</said> Stephen said thirstily. <said who="sd">There's a lemon in the
<lb n="010341"/>locker.</said>
<lb n="010342"/><said who="bm">―O, damn you and your Paris fads!</said> Buck Mulligan said. <said who="bm">I want Sandycove
<lb n="010343"/>milk.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010344"/>Haines came in from the doorway and said quietly:
<lb n="010345"/><said who="ha">―That woman is coming up with the milk.</said>
<lb n="010346"/><said who="bm">―The blessings of God on you!</said> Buck Mulligan cried, jumping up from his
<lb n="010347"/>chair. <said who="bm">Sit down. Pour out the tea there. The sugar is in the bag. Here, I
<lb n="010348"/>can't go fumbling at the damned eggs.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010349"/>He hacked through the fry on the dish and slapped it out on three
<lb n="010350"/>plates, saying:
<lb n="010351"/><said who="bm">―<quote xml:lang="la">In nomine Patris et Filii et Spiritus Sancti.</quote></said></p>
<p><lb n="010352"/>Haines sat down to pour out the tea.
<lb n="010353"/><said who="ha">―I'm giving you two lumps each,</said> he said. <said who="ha">But, I say, Mulligan, you do
<lb n="010354"/>make strong tea, don't you?</said></p>
<p><lb n="010355"/>Buck Mulligan, hewing thick slices from the loaf, said in an old
<lb n="010356"/>woman's wheedling voice:
<lb n="010357"/><said who="bm">―<said who="mg" rend="none">When I makes tea I makes tea</said>, as old mother Grogan said. <said who="mg" rend="none">And when I
<lb n="010358"/>makes water I makes water.</said></said>
<lb n="010359"/><said who="ha">―By Jove, it is tea,</said> Haines said.</p>
<p><lb n="010360"/>Buck Mulligan went on hewing and wheedling:
<lb n="010361"/><said who="bm">―<said who="mg" rend="italics">So I do, Mrs Cahill</said>, says she. <said who="mrsc" rend="italics">Begob, ma'am</said>, says Mrs Cahill, <said who="mrsc" rend="italics">God send
<lb n="010362"/>you don't make them in the one pot</said>.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010363"/>He lunged towards his messmates in turn a thick slice of bread,
<lb n="010364"/>impaled on his knife.
<lb n="010365"/><said who="bm">―That's folk,</said> he said very earnestly, <said who="bm">for your book, Haines. Five lines of
<lb n="010366"/>text and ten pages of notes about the folk and the fishgods of Dundrum.
<lb n="010367"/>Printed by the weird sisters in the year of the big wind.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010368"/>He turned to Stephen and asked in a fine puzzled voice, lifting his
<lb n="010369"/>brows:
<lb n="010370"/><said who="bm">―Can you recall, brother, is mother Grogan's tea and water pot spoken of
<lb n="010371"/>in the <title rend="none">Mabinogion</title> or is it in the <title rend="none">Upanishads</title>?</said>
<lb n="010372"/><said who="sd">―I doubt it,</said> said Stephen gravely.
<lb n="010373"/><said who="bm">―Do you now?</said> Buck Mulligan said in the same tone. <said who="bm">Your reasons, pray?</said>
<lb n="010374"/><said who="sd">―I fancy,</said> Stephen said as he ate, <said who="sd">it did not exist in or out of the
<lb n="010375"/><title rend="none">Mabinogion</title>. Mother Grogan was, one imagines, a kinswoman of Mary
<lb n="010376"/>Ann.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010377"/>Buck Mulligan's face smiled with delight.
<lb n="010378"/><said who="bm">―Charming!</said> he said in a finical sweet voice, showing his white teeth and
<lb n="010379"/>blinking his eyes pleasantly. <said who="bm">Do you think she was? Quite charming!</said></p>
<p><lb n="010380"/>Then, suddenly overclouding all his features, he growled in a
<lb n="010381"/>hoarsened rasping voice as he hewed again vigorously at the loaf:</p>
<lb n="010382"/><said who="bm">―<quote><lg rend="italics"><l>For old Mary Ann</l>
<lb n="010383"/><l>She doesn't care a damn.</l>
<lb n="010384"/><l>But, hising up her petticoats ....</l></lg></quote></said>
<p><lb n="010385"/>He crammed his mouth with fry and munched and droned.</p>
<p><lb n="010386"/>The doorway was darkened by an entering form.
<lb n="010387"/><said who="umw">―The milk, sir!</said>
<lb n="010388"/><said who="bm">―Come in, ma'am,</said> Mulligan said. <said who="bm">Kinch, get the jug.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010389"/>An old woman came forward and stood by Stephen's elbow.
<lb n="010390"/><said who="umw">―That's a lovely morning, sir,</said> she said. <said who="umw">Glory be to God.</said>
<lb n="010391"/><said who="bm">―To whom?</said> Mulligan said, glancing at her. <said who="bm">Ah, to be sure!</said></p>
<p><lb n="010392"/>Stephen reached back and took the milkjug from the locker.
<lb n="010393"/><said who="bm">―The islanders,</said> Mulligan said to Haines casually, <said who="bm">speak frequently of the
<lb n="010394"/>collector of prepuces.</said>
<lb n="010395"/><said who="umw">―How much, sir?</said> asked the old woman.
<lb n="010396"/><said who="sd">―A quart,</said> Stephen said.</p>
<p><lb n="010397"/>He watched her pour into the measure and thence into the jug rich
<lb n="010398"/>white milk, not hers. <said who="sd" aloud="false">Old shrunken paps.</said> She poured again a measureful
<lb n="010399"/>and a tilly. Old and secret she had entered from a morning world, maybe a
<lb n="010400"/>messenger. She praised the goodness of the milk, pouring it out. Crouching
<lb n="010401"/>by a patient cow at daybreak in the lush field, a witch on her toadstool, her
<lb n="010402"/>wrinkled fingers quick at the squirting dugs. They lowed about her whom
<lb n="010403"/>they knew, dewsilky cattle. Silk of the kine and poor old woman, names
<lb n="010404"/>given her in old times. A wandering crone, lowly form of an immortal
<lb n="010405"/>serving her conqueror and her gay betrayer, their common cuckquean, a
<lb n="010406"/>messenger from the secret morning. To serve or to upbraid, whether he
<lb n="010407"/>could not tell: but scorned to beg her favour.
<lb n="010408"/><said who="bm">―It is indeed, ma'am,</said> Buck Mulligan said, pouring milk into their cups.
<lb n="010409"/><said who="umw">―Taste it, sir,</said> she said.</p>
<p><lb n="010410"/>He drank at her bidding.
<lb n="010411"/><said who="bm">―If we could live on good food like that,</said> he said to her somewhat loudly,
<lb n="010412"/><said who="bm">we wouldn't have the country full of rotten teeth and rotten guts. Living in
<lb n="010413"/>a bogswamp, eating cheap food and the streets paved with dust, horsedung
<lb n="010414"/>and consumptives' spits.</said>
<lb n="010415"/><said who="umw">―Are you a medical student, sir?</said> the old woman asked.
<lb n="010416"/><said who="bm">―I am, ma'am,</said> Buck Mulligan answered.
<lb n="010417"/><said who="umw">―Look at that now,</said> she said.</p>
<p><lb n="010418"/>Stephen listened in scornful silence. <said who="sd" aloud="false">She bows her old head to a voice
<lb n="010419"/>that speaks to her loudly, her bonesetter, her medicineman: me she slights.
<lb n="010420"/>To the voice that will shrive and oil for the grave all there is of her but her
<lb n="010421"/>woman's unclean loins, of man's flesh made not in God's likeness, the
<lb n="010422"/>serpent's prey. And to the loud voice that now bids her be silent with
<lb n="010423"/>wondering unsteady eyes.</said>
<lb n="010424"/><said who="sd">―Do you understand what he says?</said> Stephen asked her.
<lb n="010425"/><said who="umw">―Is it French you are talking, sir?</said> the old woman said to Haines.</p>
<p><lb n="010426"/>Haines spoke to her again a longer speech, confidently.
<lb n="010427"/><said who="bm">―Irish,</said> Buck Mulligan said. <said who="bm">Is there Gaelic on you?</said>
<lb n="010428"/><said who="umw">―I thought it was Irish,</said> she said, <said who="umw">by the sound of it. Are you from the west,
<lb n="010429"/>sir?</said>
<lb n="010430"/><said who="ha">―I am an Englishman,</said> Haines answered.
<lb n="010431"/><said who="bm">―He's English,</said> Buck Mulligan said, <said who="bm">and he thinks we ought to speak Irish
<lb n="010432"/>in Ireland.</said>
<lb n="010433"/><said who="umw">―Sure we ought to,</said> the old woman said, <said who="umw">and I'm ashamed I don't speak the
<lb n="010434"/>language myself. I'm told it's a grand language by them that knows.</said>
<lb n="010435"/><said who="bm">―Grand is no name for it,</said> said Buck Mulligan. <said who="bm">Wonderful entirely. Fill us
<lb n="010436"/>out some more tea, Kinch. Would you like a cup, ma'am?</said>
<lb n="010437"/><said who="umw">―No, thank you, sir,</said> the old woman said, slipping the ring of the milkcan
<lb n="010438"/>on her forearm and about to go.</p>
<p><lb n="010439"/>Haines said to her:
<lb n="010440"/><said who="ha">―Have you your bill? We had better pay her, Mulligan, hadn't we?</said></p>
<p><lb n="010441"/>Stephen filled again the three cups.
<lb n="010442"/><said who="umw">―Bill, sir?</said> she said, halting. <said who="umw">Well, it's seven mornings a pint at twopence is
<lb n="010443"/>seven twos is a shilling and twopence over and these three mornings a quart
<lb n="010444"/>at fourpence is three quarts is a shilling. That's a shilling and one and two is
<lb n="010445"/>two and two, sir.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010446"/>Buck Mulligan sighed and, having filled his mouth with a crust
<lb n="010447"/>thickly buttered on both sides, stretched forth his legs and began to search
<lb n="010448"/>his trouser pockets.
<lb n="010449"/><said who="ha">―Pay up and look pleasant,</said> Haines said to him, smiling.</p>
<p><lb n="010450"/>Stephen filled a third cup, a spoonful of tea colouring faintly the thick
<lb n="010451"/>rich milk. Buck Mulligan brought up a florin, twisted it round in his fingers
<lb n="010452"/>and cried:
<lb n="010453"/><said who="bm">―A miracle!</said></p>
<p><lb n="010454"/>He passed it along the table towards the old woman, saying:</p>
<said who="bm"><lb n="010455"/>―<quote>Ask nothing more of me, sweet.
<lb n="010456"/>All I can give you I give.</quote></said>
<p><lb n="010457"/>Stephen laid the coin in her uneager hand.
<lb n="010458"/><said who="sd">―We'll owe twopence,</said> he said.
<lb n="010459"/><said who="umw">―Time enough, sir,</said> she said, taking the coin. <said who="umw">Time enough. Good morning,
<lb n="010460"/>sir.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010461"/>She curtseyed and went out, followed by Buck Mulligan's tender
<lb n="010462"/>chant:
<lb n="010463"/><said who="bm">―<quote>Heart of my heart, were it more,
<lb n="010464"/>More would be laid at your feet.</quote></said></p>
<p><lb n="010465"/>He turned to Stephen and said:
<lb n="010466"/><said who="bm">―Seriously, Dedalus. I'm stony. Hurry out to your school kip and bring us
<lb n="010467"/>back some money. Today the bards must drink and junket. Ireland expects
<lb n="010468"/>that every man this day will do his duty.</said>
<lb n="010469"/><said who="ha">―That reminds me,</said> Haines said, rising, <said who="ha">that I have to visit your national
<lb n="010470"/>library today.</said>
<lb n="010471"/><said who="bm">―Our swim first,</said> Buck Mulligan said.</p>
<p><lb n="010472"/>He turned to Stephen and asked blandly:
<lb n="010473"/><said who="bm">―Is this the day for your monthly wash, Kinch?</said></p>
<p><lb n="010474"/>Then he said to Haines:
<lb n="010475"/><said who="bm">―The unclean bard makes a point of washing once a month.</said>
<lb n="010476"/><said who="sd">―All Ireland is washed by the gulfstream,</said> Stephen said as he let honey
<lb n="010477"/>trickle over a slice of the loaf.</p>
<p><lb n="010478"/>Haines from the corner where he was knotting easily a scarf about
<lb n="010479"/>the loose collar of his tennis shirt spoke:
<lb n="010480"/><said who="ha">―I intend to make a collection of your sayings if you will let me.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010481"/><said who="sd" aloud="false">Speaking to me. They wash and tub and scrub. <ref xml:id="lb_010481">Agenbite of inwit.</ref>
<lb n="010482"/>Conscience. Yet here's a spot.</said>
<lb n="010483"/><said who="ha">―That one about the cracked lookingglass of a servant being the symbol of
<lb n="010484"/>Irish art is deuced good.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010485"/>Buck Mulligan kicked Stephen's foot under the table and said with
<lb n="010486"/>warmth of tone:
<lb n="010487"/><said who="bm">―Wait till you hear him on Hamlet, Haines.</said>
<lb n="010488"/><said who="ha">―Well, I mean it,</said> Haines said, still speaking to Stephen. <said who="ha">I was just thinking
<lb n="010489"/>of it when that poor old creature came in.</said>
<lb n="010490"/><said who="sd">―Would I make any money by it?</said> Stephen asked.</p>
<p><lb n="010491"/>Haines laughed and, as he took his soft grey hat from the holdfast of
<lb n="010492"/>the hammock, said:
<lb n="010493"/><said who="ha">―I don't know, I'm sure.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010494"/>He strolled out to the doorway. Buck Mulligan bent across to Stephen
<lb n="010495"/>and said with coarse vigour:
<lb n="010496"/><said who="bm">―You put your hoof in it now. What did you say that for?</said>
<lb n="010497"/><said who="sd">―Well?</said> Stephen said. <said who="sd">The problem is to get money. From whom? From the
<lb n="010498"/>milkwoman or from him. It's a toss up, I think.</said>
<lb n="010499"/><said who="bm">―I blow him out about you,</said> Buck Mulligan said, <said who="bm">and then you come along
<lb n="010500"/>with your lousy leer and your gloomy jesuit jibes.</said>
<lb n="010501"/><said who="sd">―I see little hope,</said> Stephen said, <said who="sd">from her or from him.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010502"/>Buck Mulligan sighed tragically and laid his hand on Stephen's arm.
<lb n="010503"/><said who="bm">―From me, Kinch,</said> he said.</p>
<p><lb n="010504"/>In a suddenly changed tone he added:
<lb n="010505"/><said who="bm">―To tell you the God's truth I think you're right. Damn all else they are
<lb n="010506"/>good for. Why don't you play them as I do? To hell with them all. Let us get
<lb n="010507"/>out of the kip.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010508"/>He stood up, gravely ungirdled and disrobed himself of his gown,
<lb n="010509"/>saying resignedly:
<lb n="010510"/><said who="bm">―Mulligan is stripped of his garments.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010511"/>He emptied his pockets on to the table.
<lb n="010512"/><said who="bm">―There's your snotrag,</said> he said.</p>
<p><lb n="010513"/>And putting on his stiff collar and rebellious tie he spoke to them,
<lb n="010514"/>chiding them, and to his dangling watchchain. His hands plunged and
<lb n="010515"/>rummaged in his trunk while he called for a clean handkerchief. God, we'll
<lb n="010516"/>simply have to dress the character. I want puce gloves and green boots.
<lb n="010517"/>Contradiction. Do I contradict myself? Very well then, I contradict myself.
<lb n="010518"/>Mercurial Malachi. A limp black missile flew out of his talking hands.
<lb n="010519"/><said who="bm">―And there's your Latin quarter hat,</said> he said.</p>
<p><lb n="010520"/>Stephen picked it up and put it on. Haines called to them from the
<lb n="010521"/>doorway:
<lb n="010522"/><said who="ha">―Are you coming, you fellows?</said>
<lb n="010523"/><said who="bm">―I'm ready,</said> Buck Mulligan answered, going towards the door. <said who="bm">Come out,
<lb n="010524"/>Kinch. You have eaten all we left, I suppose.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010525"/>Resigned he passed out with grave words and gait, saying, wellnigh
<lb n="010526"/>with sorrow:
<lb n="010527"/><said who="bm">―And going forth he met Butterly.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010528"/>Stephen, taking his ashplant from its leaningplace, followed them out
<lb n="010529"/>and, as they went down the ladder, pulled to the slow iron door and locked
<lb n="010530"/>it. He put the huge key in his inner pocket.</p>
<p><lb n="010531"/>At the foot of the ladder Buck Mulligan asked:
<lb n="010532"/><said who="bm">―Did you bring the key?</said>
<lb n="010533"/><said who="sd">―I have it,</said> Stephen said, preceding them.</p>
<p><lb n="010534"/>He walked on. Behind him he heard Buck Mulligan club with his
<lb n="010535"/>heavy bathtowel the leader shoots of ferns or grasses.
<lb n="010536"/><said who="bm">―Down, sir! How dare you, sir!</said></p>
<p><lb n="010537"/>Haines asked:
<lb n="010538"/><said who="ha">―Do you pay rent for this tower?</said>
<lb n="010539"/><said who="bm">―Twelve quid,</said> Buck Mulligan said.
<lb n="010540"/><said who="sd">―To the secretary of state for war,</said> Stephen added over his shoulder.</p>
<p><lb n="010541"/>They halted while Haines surveyed the tower and said at last:
<lb n="010542"/><said who="ha">―Rather bleak in wintertime,</said> I should say. <said who="ha">Martello you call it?</said>
<lb n="010543"/><said who="bm">―Billy Pitt had them built,</said> Buck Mulligan said, <said who="bm">when the French were on
<lb n="010544"/>the sea. But ours is the <foreign xml:lang="grc-Latin">omphalos</foreign>.</said>
<lb n="010545"/><said who="ha">―What is your idea of Hamlet?</said> Haines asked Stephen.
<lb n="010546"/><said who="bm">―No, no,</said> Buck Mulligan shouted in pain. <said who="bm">I'm not equal to Thomas
<lb n="010547"/>Aquinas and the fiftyfive reasons he has made out to prop it up. Wait till I
<lb n="010548"/>have a few pints in me first.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010549"/>He turned to Stephen, saying, as he pulled down neatly the peaks of
<lb n="010550"/>his primrose waistcoat:
<lb n="010551"/><said who="bm">―You couldn't manage it under three pints, Kinch, could you?</said>
<lb n="010552"/><said who="sd">―It has waited so long,</said> Stephen said listlessly, <said who="sd">it can wait longer.</said>
<lb n="010553"/><said who="ha">―You pique my curiosity,</said> Haines said amiably. <said who="ha">Is it some paradox?</said>
<lb n="010554"/><said who="bm">―Pooh!</said> Buck Mulligan said. <said who="bm">We have grown out of Wilde and paradoxes.
<lb n="010555"/>It's quite simple. He proves by algebra that Hamlet's grandson is
<lb n="010556"/>Shakespeare's grandfather and that he himself is the ghost of his own
<lb n="010557"/>father.</said>
<lb n="010558"/><said who="ha">―What?</said> Haines said, beginning to point at Stephen. <said who="ha">He himself?</said></p>
<p><lb n="010559"/>Buck Mulligan slung his towel stolewise round his neck and, bending
<lb n="010560"/>in loose laughter, said to Stephen's ear:
<lb n="010561"/><said who="bm">―O, shade of Kinch the elder! Japhet in search of a father!</said>
<lb n="010562"/><said who="sd">―We're always tired in the morning,</said> Stephen said to Haines. <said who="sd">And it is
<lb n="010563"/>rather long to tell.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010564"/>Buck Mulligan, walking forward again, raised his hands.
<lb n="010565"/><said who="bm">―The sacred pint alone can unbind the tongue of Dedalus,</said> he said.
<lb n="010566"/><said who="ha">―I mean to say,</said> Haines explained to Stephen as they followed, <said who="ha">this tower
<lb n="010567"/>and these cliffs here remind me somehow of Elsinore. <quote>That beetles o'er his
<lb n="010568"/>base into the sea</quote>, isn't it?</said></p>
<p><lb n="010569"/>Buck Mulligan turned suddenly for an instant towards Stephen but
<lb n="010570"/>did not speak. In the bright silent instant Stephen saw his own image in
<lb n="010571"/>cheap dusty mourning between their gay attires.
<lb n="010572"/><said who="ha">―It's a wonderful tale,</said> Haines said, bringing them to halt again.</p>
<p><lb n="010573"/>Eyes, pale as the sea the wind had freshened, paler, firm and prudent.
<lb n="010574"/>The seas' ruler, he gazed southward over the bay, empty save for the
<lb n="010575"/>smokeplume of the mailboat vague on the bright skyline and a sail tacking
<lb n="010576"/>by the Muglins.
<lb n="010577"/><said who="ha">―I read a theological interpretation of it somewhere,</said> he said bemused. <said who="ha">The
<lb n="010578"/>Father and the Son idea. The Son striving to be atoned with the Father.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010579"/>Buck Mulligan at once put on a blithe broadly smiling face. He
<lb n="010580"/>looked at them, his wellshaped mouth open happily, his eyes, from which he
<lb n="010581"/>had suddenly withdrawn all shrewd sense, blinking with mad gaiety. He
<lb n="010582"/>moved a doll's head to and fro, the brims of his Panama hat quivering, and
<lb n="010583"/>began to chant in a quiet happy foolish voice:
<lb n="010584"/><said who="bm">―<quote>I'm the queerest young fellow that ever you heard.
<lb n="010585"/>My mother's a jew, my father's a bird.
<lb n="010586"/>With Joseph the joiner I cannot agree.
<lb n="010587"/>So here's to disciples and Calvary.</quote></said></p>
<p><lb n="010588"/>He held up a forefinger of warning.
<lb n="010589"/><said who="bm">―<quote>If anyone thinks that I amn't divine
<lb n="010590"/>He'll get no free drinks when I'm making the wine
<lb n="010591"/>But have to drink water and wish it were plain
<lb n="010592"/>That I make when the wine becomes water again.</quote></said></p>
<p><lb n="010593"/>He tugged swiftly at Stephen's ashplant in farewell and, running
<lb n="010594"/>forward to a brow of the cliff, fluttered his hands at his sides like fins or
<lb n="010595"/>wings of one about to rise in the air, and chanted:
<lb n="010596"/><said who="bm">―<quote>Goodbye, now, goodbye! Write down all I said
<lb n="010597"/>And tell Tom, Dick and Harry I rose from the dead.
<lb n="010598"/>What's bred in the bone cannot fail me to fly
<lb n="010599"/>And Olivet's breezy – Goodbye, now, goodbye!</quote></said></p>
<p><lb n="010600"/>He capered before them down towards the fortyfoot hole, fluttering
<lb n="010601"/>his winglike hands, leaping nimbly, Mercury's hat quivering in the fresh
<lb n="010602"/>wind that bore back to them his brief birdsweet cries.</p>
<p><lb n="010603"/>Haines, who had been laughing guardedly, walked on beside Stephen
<lb n="010604"/>and said:
<lb n="010605"/><said who="ha">―We oughtn't to laugh, I suppose. He's rather blasphemous. I'm not a
<lb n="010606"/>believer myself, that is to say. Still his gaiety takes the harm out of it
<lb n="010607"/>somehow, doesn't it? What did he call it? Joseph the Joiner?</said>
<lb n="010608"/><said who="sd">―The ballad of joking Jesus,</said> Stephen answered.
<lb n="010609"/><said who="ha">―O,</said> Haines said, <said who="ha">you have heard it before?</said>
<lb n="010610"/><said who="sd">―Three times a day, after meals,</said> Stephen said drily.
<lb n="010611"/><said who="ha">―You're not a believer, are you?</said> Haines asked. <said who="ha">I mean, a believer in the
<lb n="010612"/>narrow sense of the word. Creation from nothing and miracles and a
<lb n="010613"/>personal God.</said>
<lb n="010614"/><said who="sd">―There's only one sense of the word, it seems to me,</said> Stephen said.</p>
<p><lb n="010615"/>Haines stopped to take out a smooth silver case in which twinkled a
<lb n="010616"/>green stone. He sprang it open with his thumb and offered it.
<lb n="010617"/><said who="sd">―Thank you,</said> Stephen said, taking a cigarette.</p>
<p><lb n="010618"/>Haines helped himself and snapped the case to. He put it back in his
<lb n="010619"/>sidepocket and took from his waistcoatpocket a nickel tinderbox, sprang it
<lb n="010620"/>open too, and, having lit his cigarette, held the flaming spunk towards
<lb n="010621"/>Stephen in the shell of his hands.
<lb n="010622"/><said who="ha">―Yes, of course,</said> he said, as they went on again. <said who="ha">Either you believe or you
<lb n="010623"/>don't, isn't it? Personally I couldn't stomach that idea of a personal God.
<lb n="010624"/>You don't stand for that, I suppose?</said>
<lb n="010625"/><said who="sd">―You behold in me,</said> Stephen said with grim displeasure, <said who="sd">a horrible example
<lb n="010626"/>of free thought.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010627"/>He walked on, waiting to be spoken to, trailing his ashplant by his
<lb n="010628"/>side. Its ferrule followed lightly on the path, squealing at his heels. My
<lb n="010629"/>familiar, after me, calling, Steeeeeeeeeeeephen! A wavering line along <said who="sd" aloud="false">the
<lb n="010630"/>path. They will walk on it tonight, coming here in the dark. He wants that
<lb n="010631"/>key. It is mine. I paid the rent. Now I eat his salt bread. Give him the key
<lb n="010632"/>too. All. He will ask for it. That was in his eyes.</said>
<lb n="010633"/><said who="ha">―After all,</said> Haines began ....</p>
<p><lb n="010634"/>Stephen turned and saw that the cold gaze which had measured him
<lb n="010635"/>was not all unkind.
<lb n="010636"/><said who="ha">―After all, I should think you are able to free yourself. You are your own
<lb n="010637"/>master, it seems to me.</said>
<lb n="010638"/><said who="sd">―I am a servant of two masters,</said> Stephen said, <said who="sd">an English and an Italian.</said>
<lb n="010639"/><said who="ha">―Italian?</said> Haines said.</p>
<p><lb n="010640"/><said who="sd" aloud="false">A crazy queen, old and jealous. Kneel down before me.</said>
<lb n="010641"/><said who="sd">―And a third,</said> Stephen said, <said who="sd">there is who wants me for odd jobs.</said>
<lb n="010642"/><said who="ha">―Italian?</said> Haines said again. <said who="ha">What do you mean?</said>
<lb n="010643"/><said who="sd">―The imperial British state,</said> Stephen answered, his colour rising, <said who="sd">and the
<lb n="010644"/>holy Roman catholic and apostolic church.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010645"/>Haines detached from his underlip some fibres of tobacco before he
<lb n="010646"/>spoke.
<lb n="010647"/><said who="ha">―I can quite understand that,</said> he said calmly. <said who="ha">An Irishman must think like
<lb n="010648"/>that, I daresay. We feel in England that we have treated you rather unfairly.
<lb n="010649"/>It seems history is to blame.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010650"/>The proud potent titles clanged over Stephen's memory the triumph
<lb n="010651"/>of their brazen bells: <quote xml:lang="la">et unam sanctam catholicam et apostolicam ecclesiam</quote>:
<lb n="010652"/>the slow growth and change of rite and dogma like his own rare thoughts, a
<lb n="010653"/>chemistry of stars. Symbol of the apostles in the mass for pope Marcellus,
<lb n="010654"/>the voices blended, singing alone loud in affirmation: and behind their
<lb n="010655"/>chant the vigilant angel of the church militant disarmed and menaced her
<lb n="010656"/>heresiarchs. A horde of heresies fleeing with mitres awry: Photius and the
<lb n="010657"/>brood of mockers of whom Mulligan was one, and Arius, warring his life
<lb n="010658"/>long upon the consubstantiality of the Son with the Father, and Valentine,
<lb n="010659"/>spurning Christ's terrene body, and the subtle African heresiarch Sabellius
<lb n="010660"/>who held that the Father was Himself His own Son. Words Mulligan had
<lb n="010661"/>spoken a moment since in mockery to the stranger. Idle mockery. The void
<lb n="010662"/>awaits surely all them that weave the wind: a menace, a disarming and a
<lb n="010663"/>worsting from those embattled angels of the church, Michael's host, who
<lb n="010664"/>defend her ever in the hour of conflict with their lances and their shields.</p>
<p><lb n="010665"/>Hear, hear! Prolonged applause. <foreign xml:lang="fr">Zut! Nom de Dieu!</foreign>
<lb n="010666"/><said who="ha">―Of course I'm a Britisher,</said> Haines's voice said, <said who="ha">and I feel as one. I don't
<lb n="010667"/>want to see my country fall into the hands of German jews either. That's
<lb n="010668"/>our national problem, I'm afraid, just now.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010669"/>Two men stood at the verge of the cliff, watching: businessman,
<lb n="010670"/>boatman.
<lb n="010671"/><said xml:id="said_010671_unclear" who="ubm">―She's making for Bullock harbour.<certainty target="#said_010671_unclear" match="@who" locus="value" assertedValue="uboat" degree="0.5"> <desc>It's unclear whether the businessman or the boatman speaks.</desc></certainty></said></p>
<p><lb n="010672"/>The boatman nodded towards the north of the bay with some disdain.
<lb n="010673"/><said who="uboat">―There's five fathoms out there,</said> he said. <said who="uboat">It'll be swept up that way when
<lb n="010674"/>the tide comes in about one. It's nine days today.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010675"/><said who="sd" aloud="false">The man that was drowned. A sail veering about the blank bay
<lb n="010676"/>waiting for a swollen bundle to bob up, roll over to the sun a puffy face,
<lb n="010677"/>saltwhite. Here I am.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010678"/>They followed the winding path down to the creek. Buck Mulligan
<lb n="010679"/>stood on a stone, in shirtsleeves, his unclipped tie rippling over his shoulder.
<lb n="010680"/>A young man clinging to a spur of rock near him, moved slowly frogwise
<lb n="010681"/>his green legs in the deep jelly of the water.
<lb n="010682"/><said who="uym">―Is the brother with you, Malachi?</said>
<lb n="010683"/><said who="bm">―Down in Westmeath. With the Bannons.</said>
<lb n="010684"/><said who="uym">―Still there? I got a card from Bannon. Says he found a sweet young thing
<lb n="010685"/>down there. Photo girl he calls her.</said>
<lb n="010686"/><said who="bm">―Snapshot, eh? Brief exposure.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010687"/>Buck Mulligan sat down to unlace his boots. An elderly man shot up
<lb n="010688"/>near the spur of rock a blowing red face. He scrambled up by the stones,
<lb n="010689"/>water glistening on his pate and on its garland of grey hair, water rilling
<lb n="010690"/>over his chest and paunch and spilling jets out of his black sagging
<lb n="010691"/>loincloth.</p>
<p><lb n="010692"/>Buck Mulligan made way for him to scramble past and, glancing at
<lb n="010693"/>Haines and Stephen, crossed himself piously with his thumbnail at brow
<lb n="010694"/>and lips and breastbone.
<lb n="010695"/><said who="uym">―Seymour's back in town,</said> the young man said, grasping again his spur of
<lb n="010696"/>rock. <said who="uym">Chucked medicine and going in for the army.</said>
<lb n="010697"/><said who="bm">―Ah, go to God!</said> Buck Mulligan said.
<lb n="010698"/><said who="uym">―Going over next week to stew. You know that red Carlisle girl, Lily?</said>
<lb n="010699"/><said who="bm">―Yes.</said>
<lb n="010700"/><said who="uym">―Spooning with him last night on the pier. The father is rotto with money.</said>
<lb n="010701"/><said who="bm">―Is she up the pole?</said>
<lb n="010702"/><said who="uym">―Better ask Seymour that.</said>
<lb n="010703"/><said who="bm">―Seymour a bleeding officer!</said> Buck Mulligan said.</p>
<p><lb n="010704"/>He nodded to himself as he drew off his trousers and stood up, saying
<lb n="010705"/>tritely:
<lb n="010706"/><said who="bm">―Redheaded women buck like goats.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010707"/>He broke off in alarm, feeling his side under his flapping shirt.
<lb n="010708"/><said who="bm">―My twelfth rib is gone,</said> he cried. <said who="bm">I'm the <foreign xml:lang="de">Übermensch</foreign>. Toothless Kinch
<lb n="010709"/>and I, the supermen.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010710"/>He struggled out of his shirt and flung it behind him to where his
<lb n="010711"/>clothes lay.
<lb n="010712"/><said who="uym">―Are you going in here, Malachi?</said>
<lb n="010713"/><said who="bm">―Yes. Make room in the bed.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010714"/>The young man shoved himself backward through the water and
<lb n="010715"/>reached the middle of the creek in two long clean strokes. Haines sat down
<lb n="010716"/>on a stone, smoking.
<lb n="010717"/><said who="bm">―Are you not coming in?</said> Buck Mulligan asked.
<lb n="010718"/><said who="ha">―Later on,</said> Haines said. <said who="ha">Not on my breakfast.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010719"/>Stephen turned away.
<lb n="010720"/><said who="sd">―I'm going, Mulligan,</said> he said.
<lb n="010721"/><said who="bm">―Give us that key, Kinch,</said> Buck Mulligan said, <said who="bm">to keep my chemise flat.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010722"/>Stephen handed him the key. Buck Mulligan laid it across his heaped
<lb n="010723"/>clothes.
<lb n="010724"/><said who="bm">―And twopence,</said> he said, <said who="bm">for a pint. Throw it there.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010725"/>Stephen threw two pennies on the soft heap. Dressing, undressing.
<lb n="010726"/>Buck Mulligan erect, with joined hands before him, said solemnly:
<lb n="010727"/><said who="bm">―He who stealeth from the poor lendeth to the Lord. Thus spake
<lb n="010728"/>Zarathustra.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010729"/>His plump body plunged.
<lb n="010730"/><said who="ha">―We'll see you again,</said> Haines said, turning as Stephen walked up the path
<lb n="010731"/>and smiling at wild Irish.</p>
<p><lb n="010732"/>Horn of a bull, hoof of a horse, smile of a Saxon.
<lb n="010733"/><said who="bm">―The Ship,</said> Buck Mulligan cried. <said who="bm">Half twelve.</said>
<lb n="010734"/><said who="sd">―Good,</said> Stephen said.</p>
<p><lb n="010735"/>He walked along the upwardcurving path.</p>
<quote xml:lang="la"><lg rend="italics"><lb n="010736"/><l>Liliata rutilantium.</l>
<lb n="010737"/><l>Turma circumdet.</l>
<lb n="010738"/><l>Iubilantium te virginum.</l></lg></quote>
<p><lb n="010739"/><said who="sd" aloud="false">The priest's grey nimbus in a niche where he dressed discreetly. I will
<lb n="010740"/>not sleep here tonight. Home also I cannot go.</said></p>
<p><lb n="010741"/>A voice, sweettoned and sustained, called to him from the sea.
<lb n="010742"/>Turning the curve he waved his hand. It called again. A sleek brown head, a
<lb n="010743"/>seal's, far out on the water, round.</p>
<p><lb n="010744"/><said who="sd" aloud="false">Usurper.</said></p>
</div> <!-- End of Episode 1, "Telemachus" -->
