<div type="episode" n="17">
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170001"/>What parallel courses did Bloom and Stephen follow returning?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170002"/>Starting united both at normal walking pace from Beresford place they
<lb n="170003"/>followed in the order named <place type="street"><placeName>Lower and Middle Gardiner streets</placeName></place> and
<lb n="170004"/><place><placeName>Mountjoy square, west</placeName></place>: then, at reduced pace, each bearing left, <place><placeName>Gardiner's
<lb n="170005"/>place</placeName></place> by an inadvertence as far as the farther corner of <place type="street"><placeName>Temple street</placeName></place>: then,
<lb n="170006"/>at reduced pace with interruptions of halt, bearing right, <place type="street"><placeName>Temple street</placeName></place>,
<lb n="170007"/>north, as far as <place type="street"><placeName>Hardwicke place</placeName></place>. Approaching, disparate, at relaxed
<lb n="170008"/>walking pace they crossed both the circus before <place><placeName>George's church</placeName></place>
<lb n="170009"/>diametrically, the chord in any circle being less than the arc which it
<lb n="170010"/>subtends.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170011"/>Of what did the duumvirate deliberate during their itinerary?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170012"/>Music, literature, <place type="country"><placeName>Ireland</placeName></place>, 
<place type="city"><placeName>Dublin</placeName></place>, <place type="city"><placeName>Paris</placeName></place>, friendship, woman, prostitution,
<lb n="170013"/>diet, the influence of gaslight or the light of arc and glowlamps on the
<lb n="170014"/>growth of adjoining paraheliotropic trees, exposed corporation emergency
<lb n="170015"/>dustbuckets, the Roman catholic church, ecclesiastical celibacy, the Irish
<lb n="170016"/>nation, jesuit education, careers, the study of medicine, the past day, the
<lb n="170017"/>maleficent influence of the presabbath, Stephen's collapse.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170018"/>Did Bloom discover common factors of similarity between their respective
<lb n="170019"/>like and unlike reactions to experience?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170020"/>Both were sensitive to artistic impressions, musical in preference to plastic
<lb n="170021"/>or pictorial. Both preferred a continental to an insular manner of life, a
<lb n="170022"/>cisatlantic to a transatlantic place of residence. Both indurated by early
<lb n="170023"/>domestic training and an inherited tenacity of heterodox resistance
<lb n="170024"/>professed their disbelief in many orthodox religious, national, social and
<lb n="170025"/>ethical doctrines. Both admitted the alternately stimulating and obtunding
<lb n="170026"/>influence of heterosexual magnetism.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170027"/>Were their views on some points divergent?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170028"/>Stephen dissented openly from Bloom's views on the importance of dietary
<lb n="170029"/>and civic selfhelp while Bloom dissented tacitly from Stephen's views on the
<lb n="170030"/>eternal affirmation of the spirit of man in literature. Bloom assented
<lb n="170031"/>covertly to Stephen's rectification of the anachronism involved in assigning
<lb n="170032"/>the date of the conversion of the Irish nation to christianity from druidism
<lb n="170033"/>by Patrick son of Calpornus, son of Potitus, son of Odyssus, sent by pope
<lb n="170034"/>Celestine I in the year 432 in the reign of Leary to the year 260 or
<lb n="170035"/>thereabouts in the reign of Cormac MacArt (†  266 A.D.), suffocated by
<lb n="170036"/>imperfect deglutition of aliment at Sletty and interred at Rossnaree. The
<lb n="170037"/>collapse which Bloom ascribed to gastric inanition and certain chemical
<lb n="170038"/>compounds of varying degrees of adulteration and alcoholic strength,
<lb n="170039"/>accelerated by mental exertion and the velocity of rapid circular motion in a
<lb n="170040"/>relaxing atmosphere, Stephen attributed to the reapparition of a matutinal
<lb n="170041"/>cloud (perceived by both from two different points of observation,
<lb n="170042"/><place><placeName>Sandycove</placeName></place> and <place type="city"><placeName>Dublin</placeName></place>) at first no bigger than a woman's hand.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170043"/>Was there one point on which their views were equal and negative?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170044"/>The influence of gaslight or electric light on the growth of adjoining
<lb n="170045"/>paraheliotropic trees.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170046"/>Had Bloom discussed similar subjects during nocturnal perambulations in
<lb n="170047"/>the past?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170048"/>In 1884 with Owen Goldberg and Cecil Turnbull at night on public
<lb n="170049"/>thoroughfares between <place type="street"><placeName>Longwood avenue</placeName></place> and <place type="street"><placeName>Leonard's corner</placeName></place> and
<lb n="170050"/><place type="street"><placeName>Leonard's corner</placeName></place> and <place type="street"><placeName>Synge street</placeName></place> and <place type="street"><placeName>Synge street</placeName></place> and <place type="street"><placeName>Bloomfield avenue</placeName></place>.
<lb n="170051"/>In 1885 with Percy Apjohn in the evenings, reclined against the wall
<lb n="170052"/>between <place><placeName>Gibraltar villa</placeName></place> and <place><placeName>Bloomfield house</placeName></place> in <place><placeName>Crumlin, barony of
<lb n="170053"/>Uppercross</placeName></place>. In 1886 occasionally with casual acquaintances and
<lb n="170054"/>prospective purchasers on doorsteps, in front parlours, in third class
<lb n="170055"/>railway carriages of suburban lines. In 1888 frequently with major Brian
<lb n="170056"/>Tweedy and his daughter Miss Marion Tweedy, together and separately on
<lb n="170057"/>the lounge in <place><placeName>Matthew Dillon's house</placeName></place> in <place><placeName>Roundtown</placeName></place>. Once in 1892 and
<lb n="170058"/>once in 1893 with Julius (Juda) Mastiansky, on both occasions in <place><placeName>the
<lb n="170059"/>parlour of his (Bloom's) house</placeName></place> in <place type="street"><placeName>Lombard street, west</placeName></place>.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170060"/>What reflection concerning the irregular sequence of dates 1884, 1885,
<lb n="170061"/>1886, 1888, 1892, 1893, 1904 did Bloom make before their arrival at their
<lb n="170062"/>destination?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170063"/>He reflected that the progressive extension of the field of individual
<lb n="170064"/>development and experience was regressively accompanied by a restriction
<lb n="170065"/>of the converse domain of interindividual relations.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170066"/>As in what ways?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170067"/>From inexistence to existence he came to many and was as one received:
<lb n="170068"/>existence with existence he was with any as any with any: from existence to
<lb n="170069"/>nonexistence gone he would be by all as none perceived.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170070"/>What act did Bloom make on their arrival at their destination?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170071"/>At the housesteps of the 4th of the equidifferent uneven numbers, <place type="street"><placeName><num>number 7</num>
<lb n="170072"/>Eccles street</placeName></place>, he inserted his hand mechanically into the back pocket of his
<lb n="170073"/>trousers to obtain his latchkey.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170074"/>Was it there?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170075"/>It was in the corresponding pocket of the trousers which he had worn on
<lb n="170076"/>the day but one preceding.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170077"/>Why was he doubly irritated?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170078"/>Because he had forgotten and because he remembered that he had reminded
<lb n="170079"/>himself twice not to forget.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170080"/>What were then the alternatives before the, premeditatedly (respectively)
<lb n="170081"/>and inadvertently, keyless couple?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170082"/>To enter or not to enter. To knock or not to knock.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170083"/>Bloom's decision?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170084"/>A stratagem. Resting his feet on the dwarf wall, he climbed over the area
<lb n="170085"/>railings, compressed his hat on his head, grasped two points at the lower
<lb n="170086"/>union of rails and stiles, lowered his body gradually by its length of five feet
<lb n="170087"/>nine inches and a half to within two feet ten inches of the area pavement
<lb n="170088"/>and allowed his body to move freely in space by separating himself from the
<lb n="170089"/>railings and crouching in preparation for the impact of the fall.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170090"/>Did he fall?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170091"/>By his body's known weight of eleven stone and four pounds in avoirdupois
<lb n="170092"/>measure, as certified by the graduated machine for periodical selfweighing
<lb n="170093"/>in the premises of Francis Froedman, pharmaceutical chemist of <place type="street"><placeName><num>19</num>
<lb n="170094"/>Frederick street, north</placeName></place>, on the last feast of the Ascension, to wit, the twelfth
<lb n="170095"/>day of May of the bissextile year one thousand nine hundred and four of
<lb n="170096"/>the christian era (jewish era five thousand six hundred and sixtyfour,
<lb n="170097"/>mohammadan era one thousand three hundred and twentytwo), golden
<lb n="170098"/>number 5, epact 13, solar cycle 9, dominical letters C B, Roman indiction 2,
<lb n="170099"/>Julian period 6617, MCMIV.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170100"/>Did he rise uninjured by concussion?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170101"/>Regaining new stable equilibrium he rose uninjured though concussed by
<lb n="170102"/>the impact, raised the latch of the area door by the exertion of force at its
<lb n="170103"/>freely moving flange and by leverage of the first kind applied at its fulcrum,
<lb n="170104"/>gained retarded access to the kitchen through the subadjacent scullery,
<lb n="170105"/>ignited a lucifer match by friction, set free inflammable coal gas by turning
<lb n="170106"/>on the ventcock, lit a high flame which, by regulating, he reduced to
<lb n="170107"/>quiescent candescence and lit finally a portable candle.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170108"/>What discrete succession of images did Stephen meanwhile perceive?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170109"/>Reclined against the area railings he perceived through the transparent
<lb n="170110"/>kitchen panes a man regulating a gasflame of 14 CP, a man lighting a
<lb n="170111"/>candle of 1 CP, a man removing in turn each of his two boots, a man
<lb n="170112"/>leaving the kitchen holding a candle.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170113"/>Did the man reappear elsewhere?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170114"/>After a lapse of four minutes the glimmer of his candle was discernible
<lb n="170115"/>through the semitransparent semicircular glass fanlight over the halldoor.
<lb n="170116"/>The halldoor turned gradually on its hinges. In the open space of the
<lb n="170117"/>doorway the man reappeared without his hat, with his candle.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170118"/>Did Stephen obey his sign?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170119"/>Yes, entering softly, he helped to close and chain the door and followed
<lb n="170120"/>softly along the hallway the man's back and listed feet and lighted candle
<lb n="170121"/>past a lighted crevice of doorway on the left and carefully down a turning
<lb n="170122"/>staircase of more than five steps into the kitchen of <place><placeName>Bloom's house</placeName></place>.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170123"/>What did Bloom do?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170124"/>He extinguished the candle by a sharp expiration of breath upon its flame,
<lb n="170125"/>drew two spoonseat deal chairs to the hearthstone, one for Stephen with its
<lb n="170126"/>back to the area window, the other for himself when necessary, knelt on one
<lb n="170127"/>knee, composed in the grate a pyre of crosslaid resintipped sticks and
<lb n="170128"/>various coloured papers and irregular polygons of best Abram coal at
<lb n="170129"/>twentyone shillings a ton from the yard of Messrs Flower and M'Donald of
<lb n="170130"/><place type="street"><placeName><num>14</num> D'Olier street</placeName></place>, kindled it at three projecting points of paper with one
<lb n="170131"/>ignited lucifer match, thereby releasing the potential energy contained in the
<lb n="170132"/>fuel by allowing its carbon and hydrogen elements to enter into free union
<lb n="170133"/>with the oxygen of the air.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170134"/>Of what similar apparitions did Stephen think?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170135"/>Of others elsewhere in other times who, kneeling on one knee or on two,
<lb n="170136"/>had kindled fires for him, of Brother Michael in the infirmary of the college
<lb n="170137"/>of the Society of Jesus at Clongowes Wood, Sallins, in the county of
<lb n="170138"/>Kildare: of his father, Simon Dedalus, in an unfurnished room of his first
<lb n="170139"/>residence in <place type="city"><placeName>Dublin</placeName></place>, <place type="street"><placeName><num>number thirteen</num> Fitzgibbon street</placeName></place>: of his godmother
<lb n="170140"/>Miss Kate Morkan in the house of her dying sister Miss Julia Morkan at <place type="street"><placeName><num>15</num>
<lb n="170141"/>Usher's Island</placeName></place>: of his aunt Sara, wife of Richie (Richard) Goulding, in the
<lb n="170142"/>kitchen of their lodgings at <place type="street"><placeName><num>62</num> Clanbrassil street</placeName></place>: of his mother Mary, wife
<lb n="170143"/>of Simon Dedalus, in the kitchen of <place type="street"><placeName><num>number twelve</num> North Richmond street</placeName></place>
<lb n="170144"/>on the morning of the feast of Saint Francis Xavier 1898: of the dean of
<lb n="170145"/>studies, Father Butt, in the physics' theatre of university College, <place type="street"><placeName><num>16</num>
<lb n="170146"/>Stephen's Green, north</placeName></place>: of his sister Dilly (Delia) in his father's house in
<lb n="170147"/><place><placeName>Cabra</placeName></place>.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170148"/>What did Stephen see on raising his gaze to the height of a yard from the
<lb n="170149"/>fire towards the opposite wall?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170150"/>Under a row of five coiled spring housebells a curvilinear rope, stretched
<lb n="170151"/>between two holdfasts athwart across the recess beside the chimney pier,
<lb n="170152"/>from which hung four smallsized square handkerchiefs folded unattached
<lb n="170153"/>consecutively in adjacent rectangles and one pair of ladies' grey hose with
<lb n="170154"/>Lisle suspender tops and feet in their habitual position clamped by three
<lb n="170155"/>erect wooden pegs two at their outer extremities and the third at their point
<lb n="170156"/>of junction.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170157"/>What did Bloom see on the range?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170158"/>On the right (smaller) hob a blue enamelled saucepan: on the left (larger)
<lb n="170159"/>hob a black iron kettle.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170160"/>What did Bloom do at the range?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170161"/>He removed the saucepan to the left hob, rose and carried the iron kettle to
<lb n="170162"/>the sink in order to tap the current by turning the faucet to let it flow.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170163"/>Did it flow?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170164"/>Yes. From <place><placeName>Roundwood reservoir</placeName></place> in <place><placeName>county Wicklow</placeName></place> of a cubic capacity of
<lb n="170165"/>2400 million gallons, percolating through a subterranean aqueduct of filter
<lb n="170166"/>mains of single and double pipeage constructed at an initial plant cost of £5
<lb n="170167"/>per linear yard by way of the <place><placeName>Dargle</placeName></place>, <place><placeName>Rathdown</placeName></place>, <place><placeName>Glen of the Downs</placeName></place> and
<lb n="170168"/><place><placeName>Callowhill</placeName></place> to the 26 acre reservoir at <place><placeName>Stillorgan</placeName></place>, a distance of 22 statute
<lb n="170169"/>miles, and thence, through a system of relieving tanks, by a gradient of 250
<lb n="170170"/>feet to the city boundary at <place><placeName>Eustace bridge, upper Leeson street</placeName></place>, though
<lb n="170171"/>from prolonged summer drouth and daily supply of 12½ million gallons the
<lb n="170172"/>water had fallen below the sill of the overflow weir for which reason the
<lb n="170173"/>borough surveyor and waterworks engineer, Mr Spencer Harty, C. E., on
<lb n="170174"/>the instructions of the waterworks committee had prohibited the use of
<lb n="170175"/>municipal water for purposes other than those of consumption (envisaging
<lb n="170176"/>the possibility of recourse being had to the impotable water of the <place><placeName>Grand
<lb n="170177"/>and Royal canals</placeName></place> as in 1893) particularly as the South Dublin Guardians,
<lb n="170178"/>notwithstanding their ration of 15 gallons per day per pauper supplied
<lb n="170179"/>through a 6 inch meter, had been convicted of a wastage of 20,000 gallons
<lb n="170180"/>per night by a reading of their meter on the affirmation of the law agent of
<lb n="170181"/>the corporation, Mr Ignatius Rice, solicitor, thereby acting to the detriment
<lb n="170182"/>of another section of the public, selfsupporting taxpayers, solvent, sound.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170183"/>What in water did Bloom, waterlover, drawer of water, watercarrier,
<lb n="170184"/>returning to the range, admire?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170185"/>Its universality: its democratic equality and constancy to its nature in
<lb n="170186"/>seeking its own level: its vastness in the ocean of Mercator's projection: its
<lb n="170187"/>unplumbed profundity in the <place><placeName>Sundam trench of the Pacific</placeName></place> exceeding 8000
<lb n="170188"/>fathoms: the restlessness of its waves and surface particles visiting in turn
<lb n="170189"/>all points of its seaboard: the independence of its units: the variability of
<lb n="170190"/>states of sea: its hydrostatic quiescence in calm: its hydrokinetic turgidity in
<lb n="170191"/>neap and spring tides: its subsidence after devastation: its sterility in the
<lb n="170192"/>circumpolar icecaps, arctic and antarctic: its climatic and commercial
<lb n="170193"/>significance: its preponderance of 3 to 1 over the dry land of the globe: its
<lb n="170194"/>indisputable hegemony extending in square leagues over all the region
<lb n="170195"/>below the subequatorial tropic of Capricorn: the multisecular stability of its
<lb n="170196"/>primeval basin: its luteofulvous bed: its capacity to dissolve and hold in
<lb n="170197"/>solution all soluble substances including millions of tons of the most
<lb n="170198"/>precious metals: its slow erosions of peninsulas and islands, its persistent
<lb n="170199"/>formation of homothetic islands, peninsulas and downwardtending
<lb n="170200"/>promontories: its alluvial deposits: its weight and volume and density: its
<lb n="170201"/>imperturbability in lagoons and highland tarns: its gradation of colours
<lb n="170202"/>in the torrid and temperate and frigid zones: its vehicular ramifications in
<lb n="170203"/>continental lakecontained streams and confluent oceanflowing rivers with
<lb n="170204"/>their tributaries and transoceanic currents, gulfstream, north and south
<lb n="170205"/>equatorial courses: its violence in seaquakes, waterspouts, Artesian wells,
<lb n="170206"/>eruptions, torrents, eddies, freshets, spates, groundswells, watersheds,
<lb n="170207"/>waterpartings, geysers, cataracts, whirlpools, maelstroms, inundations,
<lb n="170208"/>deluges, cloudbursts: its vast circumterrestrial ahorizontal curve: its secrecy
<lb n="170209"/>in springs and latent humidity, revealed by rhabdomantic or hygrometric
<lb n="170210"/>instruments and exemplified by the well by the hole in the wall at <place><placeName>Ashtown
<lb n="170211"/>gate</placeName></place>, saturation of air, distillation of dew: the simplicity of its composition,
<lb n="170212"/>two constituent parts of hydrogen with one constituent part of oxygen: its
<lb n="170213"/>healing virtues: its buoyancy in the waters of the <place><placeName>Dead Sea</placeName></place>: its persevering
<lb n="170214"/>penetrativeness in runnels, gullies, inadequate dams, leaks on shipboard: its
<lb n="170215"/>properties for cleansing, quenching thirst and fire, nourishing vegetation:
<lb n="170216"/>its infallibility as paradigm and paragon: its metamorphoses as vapour,
<lb n="170217"/>mist, cloud, rain, sleet, snow, hail: its strength in rigid hydrants: its variety
<lb n="170218"/>of forms in loughs and bays and gulfs and bights and guts and lagoons and
<lb n="170219"/>atolls and archipelagos and sounds and fjords and minches and tidal
<lb n="170220"/>estuaries and arms of sea: its solidity in glaciers, icebergs, icefloes: its
<lb n="170221"/>docility in working hydraulic millwheels, turbines, dynamos, electric power
<lb n="170222"/>stations, bleachworks, tanneries, scutchmills: its utility in canals, rivers, if
<lb n="170223"/>navigable, floating and graving docks: its potentiality derivable from
<lb n="170224"/>harnessed tides or watercourses falling from level to level: its submarine
<lb n="170225"/>fauna and flora (anacoustic, photophobe), numerically, if not literally, the
<lb n="170226"/>inhabitants of the globe: its ubiquity as constituting 90% of the human
<lb n="170227"/>body: the noxiousness of its effluvia in lacustrine marshes, pestilential fens,
<lb n="170228"/>faded flowerwater, stagnant pools in the waning moon.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170229"/>Having set the halffilled kettle on the now burning coals, why did he return
<lb n="170230"/>to the stillflowing tap?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170231"/>To wash his soiled hands with a partially consumed tablet of Barrington's
<lb n="170232"/>lemonflavoured soap, to which paper still adhered, <ref target="u05_lotus-eaters.xml#lb_050513">(bought thirteen hours
<lb n="170233"/>previously for fourpence and still unpaid for)</ref>, in fresh cold neverchanging
<lb n="170234"/>everchanging water and dry them, face and hands, in a long redbordered
<lb n="170235"/>holland cloth passed over a wooden revolving roller.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170236"/>What reason did Stephen give for declining Bloom's offer?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170237"/>That he was hydrophobe, hating partial contact by immersion or total by
<lb n="170238"/>submersion in cold water, (his last bath having taken place in the month of
<lb n="170239"/>October of the preceding year), disliking the aqueous substances of glass
<lb n="170240"/>and crystal, distrusting aquacities of thought and language.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170241"/>What impeded Bloom from giving Stephen counsels of hygiene and
<lb n="170242"/>prophylactic to which should be added suggestions concerning a
<lb n="170243"/>preliminary wetting of the head and contraction of the muscles with rapid
<lb n="170244"/>splashing of the face and neck and thoracic and epigastric region in case of
<lb n="170245"/>sea or river bathing, the parts of the human anatomy most sensitive to cold
<lb n="170246"/>being the nape, stomach and thenar or sole of foot?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170247"/>The incompatibility of aquacity with the erratic originality of genius.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170248"/>What additional didactic counsels did he similarly repress?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170249"/>Dietary: concerning the respective percentage of protein and caloric energy
<lb n="170250"/>in bacon, salt ling and butter, the absence of the former in the lastnamed
<lb n="170251"/>and the abundance of the latter in the firstnamed.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170252"/>Which seemed to the host to be the predominant qualities of his guest?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170253"/>Confidence in himself, an equal and opposite power of abandonment and
<lb n="170254"/>recuperation.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170255"/>What concomitant phenomenon took place in the vessel of liquid by the
<lb n="170256"/>agency of fire?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170257"/>The phenomenon of ebullition. Fanned by a constant updraught of
<lb n="170258"/>ventilation between the kitchen and the chimneyflue, ignition was
<lb n="170259"/>communicated from the faggots of precombustible fuel to polyhedral
<lb n="170260"/>masses of bituminous coal, containing in compressed mineral form the
<lb n="170261"/>foliated fossilised decidua of primeval forests which had in turn derived
<lb n="170262"/>their vegetative existence from the sun, primal source of heat (radiant),
<lb n="170263"/>transmitted through omnipresent luminiferous diathermanous ether. Heat
<lb n="170264"/>(convected), a mode of motion developed by such combustion, was
<lb n="170265"/>constantly and increasingly conveyed from the source of calorification to
<lb n="170266"/>the liquid contained in the vessel, being radiated through the uneven
<lb n="170267"/>unpolished dark surface of the metal iron, in part reflected, in part
<lb n="170268"/>absorbed, in part transmitted, gradually raising the temperature of the
<lb n="170269"/>water from normal to boiling point, a rise in temperature expressible as the
<lb n="170270"/>result of an expenditure of 72 thermal units needed to raise 1 pound of
<lb n="170271"/>water from 50° to 212° Fahrenheit.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170272"/>What announced the accomplishment of this rise in temperature?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170273"/>A double falciform ejection of water vapour from under the kettlelid at both
<lb n="170274"/>sides simultaneously.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170275"/>For what personal purpose could Bloom have applied the water so boiled?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170276"/>To shave himself.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170277"/>What advantages attended shaving by night?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170278"/>A softer beard: a softer brush if intentionally allowed to remain from shave
<lb n="170279"/>to shave in its agglutinated lather: a softer skin if unexpectedly
<lb n="170280"/>encountering female acquaintances in remote places at incustomary hours:
<lb n="170281"/>quiet reflections upon the course of the day: a cleaner sensation when
<lb n="170282"/>awaking after a fresher sleep since matutinal noises, premonitions and
<lb n="170283"/>perturbations, a clattered milkcan, a postman's double knock, a paper read,
<lb n="170284"/>reread while lathering, relathering the same spot, a shock, a shoot, with
<lb n="170285"/>thought of aught he sought though fraught with nought might cause a
<lb n="170286"/>faster rate of shaving and a nick on which incision plaster with precision
<lb n="170287"/>cut and humected and applied adhered: which was to be done.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170288"/>Why did absence of light disturb him less than presence of noise?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170289"/>Because of the surety of the sense of touch in his firm full masculine
<lb n="170290"/>feminine passive active hand.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170291"/>What quality did it (his hand) possess but with what counteracting
<lb n="170292"/>influence?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170293"/>The operative surgical quality but that he was reluctant to shed human
<lb n="170294"/>blood even when the end justified the means, preferring, in their natural
<lb n="170295"/>order, heliotherapy, psychophysicotherapeutics, osteopathic surgery.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170296"/>What lay under exposure on the lower, middle and upper shelves of the
<lb n="170297"/>kitchen dresser, opened by Bloom?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170298"/>On the lower shelf five vertical breakfast plates, six horizontal breakfast
<lb n="170299"/>saucers on which rested inverted breakfast cups, a moustachecup,
<lb n="170300"/>uninverted, and saucer of Crown Derby, four white goldrimmed eggcups,
<lb n="170301"/>an open shammy purse displaying coins, mostly copper, and a phial of
<lb n="170302"/>aromatic (violet) comfits. On the middle shelf a chipped eggcup containing
<lb n="170303"/>pepper, a drum of table salt, four conglomerated black olives in oleaginous
<lb n="170304"/>paper, an empty pot of Plumtree's potted meat, an oval wicker basket
<lb n="170305"/>bedded with fibre and containing one Jersey pear, a halfempty bottle of
<lb n="170306"/>William Gilbey and Co's white invalid port, half disrobed of its swathe of
<lb n="170307"/>coralpink tissue paper, a packet of Epps's soluble cocoa, five ounces of
<lb n="170308"/>Anne Lynch's choice tea at 2/- per lb in a crinkled leadpaper bag, a
<lb n="170309"/>cylindrical canister containing the best crystallised lump sugar, two onions,
<lb n="170310"/>one, the larger, Spanish, entire, the other, smaller, Irish, bisected with
<lb n="170311"/>augmented surface and more redolent, a jar of Irish Model Dairy's cream, a
<lb n="170312"/>jug of brown crockery containing a naggin and a quarter of soured
<lb n="170313"/>adulterated milk, converted by heat into water, acidulous serum and
<lb n="170314"/>semisolidified curds, which added to the quantity subtracted for Mr
<lb n="170315"/>Bloom's and Mrs Fleming's breakfasts, made one imperial pint, the total
<lb n="170316"/>quantity originally delivered, two cloves, a halfpenny and a small dish
<lb n="170317"/>containing a slice of fresh ribsteak. On the upper shelf a battery of jamjars
<lb n="170318"/>(empty) of various sizes and proveniences.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170319"/>What attracted his attention lying on the apron of the dresser?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170320"/>Four polygonal fragments of two lacerated scarlet betting tickets, numbered
<lb n="170321"/>8 87, 88 6.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170322"/>What reminiscences temporarily corrugated his brow?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170323"/>Reminiscences of coincidences, truth stranger than fiction, preindicative of
<lb n="170324"/>the result of the Gold Cup flat handicap, the official and definitive result of
<lb n="170325"/>which he had read in the <title type="newspaper">Evening Telegraph</title>, late pink edition, in <place><placeName>the
<lb n="170326"/>cabman's shelter, at Butt bridge</placeName></place>.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170327"/>Where had previous intimations of the result, effected or projected, been
<lb n="170328"/>received by him?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170329"/>In Bernard Kiernan's licensed premises <place type="street"><placeName><num>8, 9 and 10</num> Little Britain street</placeName></place>: in
<lb n="170330"/>David Byrne's licensed premises, <place type="street"><placeName><num>14</num> Duke street</placeName></place>: 
in <placeName type="street"><place>O'Connell street lower</place></placeName>,
<lb n="170331"/>outside Graham Lemon's when a dark man had placed in his hand a
<lb n="170332"/>throwaway (subsequently thrown away), advertising Elijah, restorer of the
<lb n="170333"/>church in Zion: in <place type="street"><placeName>Lincoln place</placeName></place> outside the premises of <place><placeName>F. W. Sweny and
<lb n="170334"/>Co (Limited), dispensing chemists</placeName></place>, when, when Frederick M. (Bantam)
<lb n="170335"/>Lyons had rapidly and successively requested, perused and restituted the
<lb n="170336"/>copy of the current issue of the <title type="newspaper">Freeman's Journal</title> and <title type="newspaper">National Press</title>
<lb n="170337"/>which he had been about to throw away (subsequently thrown away), he
<lb n="170338"/>had proceeded towards the oriental edifice of the Turkish and Warm Baths,
<lb n="170339"/><place type="street"><placeName><num>11</num> Leinster street</placeName></place>, with the light of inspiration shining in his countenance
<lb n="170340"/>and bearing in his arms the secret of the race, graven in the language of
<lb n="170341"/>prediction.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170342"/>What qualifying considerations allayed his perturbations?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170343"/>The difficulties of interpretation since the significance of any event followed
<lb n="170344"/>its occurrence as variably as the acoustic report followed the electrical
<lb n="170345"/>discharge and of counterestimating against an actual loss by failure to
<lb n="170346"/>interpret the total sum of possible losses proceeding originally from a
<lb n="170347"/>successful interpretation.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170348"/>His mood?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170349"/>He had not risked, he did not expect, he had not been disappointed, he was
<lb n="170350"/>satisfied.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170351"/>What satisfied him?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170352"/>To have sustained no positive loss. To have brought a positive gain to
<lb n="170353"/>others. Light to the gentiles.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170354"/>How did Bloom prepare a collation for a gentile?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170355"/>He poured into two teacups two level spoonfuls, four in all, of Epps's
<lb n="170356"/>soluble cocoa and proceeded according to the directions for use printed on
<lb n="170357"/>the label, to each adding after sufficient time for infusion the prescribed
<lb n="170358"/>ingredients for diffusion in the manner and in the quantity prescribed.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170359"/>What supererogatory marks of special hospitality did the host show his
<lb n="170360"/>guest?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170361"/>Relinquishing his symposiarchal right to the moustache cup of imitation
<lb n="170362"/>Crown Derby presented to him by his only daughter, Millicent (Milly), he
<lb n="170363"/>substituted a cup identical with that of his guest and served extraordinarily
<lb n="170364"/>to his guest and, in reduced measure, to himself the viscous cream
<lb n="170365"/>ordinarily reserved for the breakfast of his wife Marion (Molly).</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170366"/>Was the guest conscious of and did he acknowledge these marks of
<lb n="170367"/>hospitality?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170368"/>His attention was directed to them by his host jocosely, and he accepted
<lb n="170369"/>them seriously as they drank in jocoserious silence Epps's massproduct, the
<lb n="170370"/>creature cocoa.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170371"/>Were there marks of hospitality which he contemplated but suppressed,
<lb n="170372"/>reserving them for another and for himself on future occasions to complete
<lb n="170373"/>the act begun?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170374"/>The reparation of a fissure of the length of 1½ inches in the right side of his
<lb n="170375"/>guest's jacket. A gift to his guest of one of the four lady's handkerchiefs, if
<lb n="170376"/>and when ascertained to be in a presentable condition.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170377"/>Who drank more quickly?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170378"/>Bloom, having the advantage of ten seconds at the initiation and taking,
<lb n="170379"/>from the concave surface of a spoon along the handle of which a steady
<lb n="170380"/>flow of heat was conducted, three sips to his opponent's one, six to two,
<lb n="170381"/>nine to three.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170382"/>What cerebration accompanied his frequentative act?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170383"/>Concluding by inspection but erroneously that his silent companion was
<lb n="170384"/>engaged in mental composition he reflected on the pleasures derived from
<lb n="170385"/>literature of instruction rather than of amusement as he himself had applied
<lb n="170386"/>to the works of William Shakespeare more than once for the solution of
<lb n="170387"/>difficult problems in imaginary or real life.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170388"/>Had he found their solution?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170389"/>In spite of careful and repeated reading of certain classical passages, aided
<lb n="170390"/>by a glossary, he had derived imperfect conviction from the text, the
<lb n="170391"/>answers not bearing in all points.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170392"/>What lines concluded his first piece of original verse written by him,
<lb n="170393"/>potential poet, at the age of 11 in 1877 on the occasion of the offering of
<lb n="170394"/>three prizes of 10/-, 5/- and 2/6 respectively for competition by the
<lb n="170395"/><title type="newspaper">Shamrock</title>, a weekly newspaper?</p>
<q><lg rend="italics"><lb n="170396"/><l>An ambition to squint</l>
<lb n="170397"/><l>At my verses in print</l>
<lb n="170398"/><l>Makes me hope that for these you'll find room.</l>
<lb n="170399"/><l>If you so condescend</l>
<lb n="170400"/><l>Then please place at the end</l>
<lb n="170401"/><l>The name of yours truly, L. Bloom.</l></lg></q>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170402"/>Did he find four separating forces between his temporary guest and him?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170403"/>Name, age, race, creed.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170404"/>What anagrams had he made on his name in youth?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170405"/>Leopold Bloom
<lb n="170406"/>Ellpodbomool
<lb n="170407"/>Molldopeloob
<lb n="170408"/>Bollopedoom
<lb n="170409"/>Old Ollebo, M. P.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170410"/>What acrostic upon the abbreviation of his first name had he (kinetic poet)
<lb n="170411"/>sent to Miss Marion (Molly) Tweedy on the 14 February 1888?</p>
<q><lg rend="italics"><lb n="170412"/><l><hi rend="bold">P</hi>oets oft have sung in rhyme</l>
<lb n="170413"/><l><hi rend="bold">O</hi>f music sweet their praise divine.</l>
<lb n="170414"/><l><hi rend="bold">L</hi>et them hymn it nine times nine.</l>
<lb n="170415"/><l><hi rend="bold">D</hi>earer far than song or wine.</l>
<lb n="170416"/><l><hi rend="bold">Y</hi>ou are mine. The world is mine.</l></lg></q>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170417"/>What had prevented him from completing a topical song (music by R. G.
<lb n="170418"/>Johnston) on the events of the past, or fixtures for the actual, years, entitled
<lb n="170419"/><title type="song">If Brian Boru could but come back and see old Dublin now</title>, commissioned
<lb n="170420"/>by Michael Gunn, lessee of the <place><placeName>Gaiety Theatre</placeName></place>, <place type="street"><placeName><num>46, 47, 48, 49</num> South King
<lb n="170421"/>street</placeName></place>, and to be introduced into the sixth scene, the valley of diamonds, of
<lb n="170422"/>the second edition (30 January 1893) of the grand annual Christmas
<lb n="170423"/>pantomime <ref target="#lb_172322"><title type="pantomime">Sinbad the Sailor</title></ref> (produced by R Shelton 26 December 1892,
<lb n="170424"/>written by Greenleaf Whittier, scenery by George A. Jackson and Cecil
<lb n="170425"/>Hicks, costumes by Mrs and Miss Whelan under the personal supervision
<lb n="170426"/>of Mrs Michael Gunn, ballets by Jessie Noir, harlequinade by Thomas
<lb n="170427"/>Otto) and sung by Nelly Bouverist, principal girl?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170428"/>Firstly, oscillation between events of imperial and of local interest, the
<lb n="170429"/>anticipated diamond jubilee of Queen Victoria (born 1820, acceded 1837)
<lb n="170430"/>and the posticipated opening of the new municipal fish market: secondly,
<lb n="170431"/>apprehension of opposition from extreme circles on the questions of the
<lb n="170432"/>respective visits of Their Royal Highnesses the duke and duchess of York
<lb n="170433"/>(real) and of His Majesty King Brian Boru (imaginary): thirdly, a conflict
<lb n="170434"/>between professional etiquette and professional emulation concerning the
<lb n="170435"/>recent erections of the Grand Lyric Hall on Burgh Quay and the Theatre
<lb n="170436"/>Royal in <place type="street"><placeName>Hawkins street</placeName></place>: fourthly, distraction resultant from compassion
<lb n="170437"/>for Nelly Bouverist's non-intellectual, non-political, non-topical expression
<lb n="170438"/>of countenance and concupiscence caused by Nelly Bouverist's revelations
<lb n="170439"/>of white articles of non-intellectual, non-political, non-topical
<lb n="170440"/>underclothing while she (Nelly Bouverist) was in the articles: fifthly, the
<lb n="170441"/>difficulties of the selection of appropriate music and humorous allusions
<lb n="170442"/>from <title type="book">Everybody's Book of Jokes</title> (1000 pages and a laugh in every one):
<lb n="170443"/>sixthly, the rhymes, homophonous and cacophonous, associated with the
<lb n="170444"/>names of the new lord mayor, Daniel Tallon, the new high sheriff, Thomas
<lb n="170445"/>Pile and the new solicitorgeneral, Dunbar Plunket Barton.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170446"/>What relation existed between their ages?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170447"/>16 years before in 1888 when Bloom was of Stephen's present age Stephen
<lb n="170448"/>was 6. 16 years after in 1920 when Stephen would be of Bloom's present age
<lb n="170449"/>Bloom would be 54. In 1936 when Bloom would be 70 and Stephen 54 their
<lb n="170450"/>ages initially in the ratio of 16 to 0 would be as 17 ½ to 13 ½, the proportion
<lb n="170451"/>increasing and the disparity diminishing according as arbitrary future years
<lb n="170452"/>were added, for if the proportion existing in 1883 had continued immutable,
<lb n="170453"/>conceiving that to be possible, till then 1904 when Stephen was 22 Bloom
<lb n="170454"/>would be 374 and in 1920 when Stephen would be 38, as Bloom then was,
<lb n="170455"/>Bloom would be 646 while in 1952 when Stephen would have attained the
<lb n="170456"/>maximum postdiluvian age of 70 Bloom, being 1190 years alive having been
<lb n="170457"/>born in the year 714, would have surpassed by 221 years the maximum
<lb n="170458"/>antediluvian age, that of Methusalah, 969 years, while, if Stephen would
<lb n="170459"/>continue to live until he would attain that age in the year 3072 A.D., Bloom
<lb n="170460"/>would have been obliged to have been alive 83,300 years, having been
<lb n="170461"/>obliged to have been born in the year 81,396 B.C.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170462"/>What events might nullify these calculations?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170463"/>The cessation of existence of both or either, the inauguration of a new era
<lb n="170464"/>or calendar, the annihilation of the world and consequent extermination of
<lb n="170465"/>the human species, inevitable but impredictable.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170466"/>How many previous encounters proved their preexisting acquaintance?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170467"/>Two. The first in the lilacgarden of <place><placeName>Matthew Dillon's house, Medina Villa,
<lb n="170468"/>Kimmage road, Roundtown</placeName></place>, in 1887, in the company of Stephen's mother,
<lb n="170469"/>Stephen being then of the age of 5 and reluctant to give his hand in
<lb n="170470"/>salutation. The second in the coffeeroom of <place><placeName>Breslin's hotel</placeName></place> on a rainy
<lb n="170471"/>Sunday in the January of 1892, in the company of Stephen's father and
<lb n="170472"/>Stephen's granduncle, Stephen being then 5 years older.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170473"/>Did Bloom accept the invitation to dinner given then by the son and
<lb n="170474"/>afterwards seconded by the father?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170475"/>Very gratefully, with grateful appreciation, with sincere appreciative
<lb n="170476"/>gratitude, in appreciatively grateful sincerity of regret, he declined.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170477"/>Did their conversation on the subject of these reminiscences reveal a third
<lb n="170478"/>connecting link between them?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170479"/>Mrs Riordan (Dante), a widow of independent means, had resided in the
<lb n="170480"/>house of Stephen's parents from 1 September 1888 to 29 December 1891
<lb n="170481"/>and had also resided during the years 1892, 1893 and 1894 in <place><placeName>the City Arms
<lb n="170482"/>Hotel</placeName></place> owned by Elizabeth O'Dowd of 54 Prussia street where, during parts
<lb n="170483"/>of the years 1893 and 1894, she had been a constant informant of Bloom
<lb n="170484"/>who resided also in the same hotel, being at that time a clerk in the
<lb n="170485"/>employment of Joseph Cuffe of <place type="street"><placeName><num>5</num> Smithfield</placeName></place> for the superintendence of sales
<lb n="170486"/>in the adjacent Dublin Cattle market on the <place><placeName>North Circular road</placeName></place>.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170487"/>Had he performed any special corporal work of mercy for her?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170488"/>He had sometimes propelled her on warm summer evenings, an infirm
<lb n="170489"/>widow of independent, if limited, means, in her convalescent bathchair with
<lb n="170490"/>slow revolutions of its wheels as far as the corner of the <place><placeName>North Circular
<lb n="170491"/>road</placeName></place> opposite Mr Gavin Low's place of business where she had remained
<lb n="170492"/>for a certain time scanning through his onelensed binocular fieldglasses
<lb n="170493"/>unrecognisable citizens on tramcars, roadster bicycles equipped with
<lb n="170494"/>inflated pneumatic tyres, hackney carriages, tandems, private and hired
<lb n="170495"/>landaus, dogcarts, ponytraps and brakes passing from the city to the
<lb n="170496"/><place><placeName>Phoenix Park</placeName></place> and <foreign xml:lang="la">vice versa</foreign>.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170497"/>Why could he then support that his vigil with the greater equanimity?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170498"/>Because in middle youth he had often sat observing through a rondel of
<lb n="170499"/>bossed glass of a multicoloured pane the spectacle offered with continual
<lb n="170500"/>changes of the thoroughfare without, pedestrians, quadrupeds, velocipedes,
<lb n="170501"/>vehicles, passing slowly, quickly, evenly, round and round and round the
<lb n="170502"/>rim of a round and round precipitous globe.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170503"/>What distinct different memories had each of her now eight years deceased?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170504"/>The older, her bezique cards and counters, her Skye terrier, her
<lb n="170505"/>suppositious wealth, her lapses of responsiveness and incipient catarrhal
<lb n="170506"/>deafness: the younger, her lamp of colza oil before the statue of the
<lb n="170507"/>Immaculate Conception, her green and maroon brushes for Charles
<lb n="170508"/>Stewart Parnell and for Michael Davitt, her tissue papers.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170509"/>Were there no means still remaining to him to achieve the rejuvenation
<lb n="170510"/>which these reminiscences divulged to a younger companion rendered the
<lb n="170511"/>more desirable?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170512"/>The indoor exercises, formerly intermittently practised, subsequently
<lb n="170513"/>abandoned, prescribed in Eugen Sandow's <title type="book">Physical Strength and How to
<lb n="170514"/>Obtain It</title> which, designed particularly for commercial men engaged in
<lb n="170515"/>sedentary occupations, were to be made with mental concentration in front
<lb n="170516"/>of a mirror so as to bring into play the various families of muscles and
<lb n="170517"/>produce successively a pleasant rigidity, a more pleasant relaxation and the
<lb n="170518"/>most pleasant repristination of juvenile agility.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170519"/>Had any special agility been his in earlier youth?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170520"/>Though ringweight lifting had been beyond his strength and the full circle
<lb n="170521"/>gyration beyond his courage yet as a High school scholar he had excelled in
<lb n="170522"/>his stable and protracted execution of the half lever movement on the
<lb n="170523"/>parallel bars in consequence of his abnormally developed abdominal
<lb n="170524"/>muscles.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170525"/>Did either openly allude to their racial difference?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170526"/>Neither.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170527"/>What, reduced to their simplest reciprocal form, were Bloom's thoughts
<lb n="170528"/>about Stephen's thoughts about Bloom and about Stephen's thoughts about
<lb n="170529"/>Bloom's thoughts about Stephen?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170530"/>He thought that he thought that he was a jew whereas he knew that he
<lb n="170531"/>knew that he knew that he was not.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170532"/>What, the enclosures of reticence removed, were their respective
<lb n="170533"/>parentages?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170534"/>Bloom, only born male transubstantial heir of Rudolf Virag (subsequently
<lb n="170535"/>Rudolph Bloom) of <place type="city"><placeName>Szombathél</placeName></place>y, <place type="city"><placeName>Vienna</placeName></place>, 
<place type="city"><placeName>Budapest</placeName></place>, <place type="city"><placeName>Milan</placeName></place>, 
<place type="city"><placeName>London</placeName></place> and
<lb n="170536"/><place type="city"><placeName>Dublin</placeName></place> and of Ellen Higgins, second daughter of Julius Higgins (born
<lb n="170537"/>Karoly) and Fanny Higgins (born Hegarty). Stephen, eldest surviving male
<lb n="170538"/>consubstantial heir of Simon Dedalus of <place><placeName>Cork</placeName></place> and <place type="city"><placeName>Dublin</placeName></place> and of Mary,
<lb n="170539"/>daughter of Richard and Christina Goulding (born Grier).</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170540"/>Had Bloom and Stephen been baptised, and where and by whom, cleric or
<lb n="170541"/>layman?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170542"/>Bloom (three times), by the reverend Mr Gilmer Johnston M. A., alone, in
<lb n="170543"/><place><placeName>the protestant church of Saint Nicholas</placeName></place> Without, Coombe, by James
<lb n="170544"/>O'Connor, Philip Gilligan and James Fitzpatrick, together, under a pump
<lb n="170545"/>in the village of Swords, and by the reverend Charles Malone C. C., in the
<lb n="170546"/><place><placeName>church of the Three Patrons</placeName></place>, <place type="city"><placeName>Rathgar</placeName></place>. Stephen (once) by the reverend
<lb n="170547"/>Charles Malone C. C., alone, in <place><placeName>the church of the Three Patrons</placeName></place>, <place type="city"><placeName>Rathgar</placeName></place>.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170548"/>Did they find their educational careers similar?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170549"/>Substituting Stephen for Bloom Stoom would have passed successively
<lb n="170550"/>through a dame's school and the high school. Substituting Bloom for
<lb n="170551"/>Stephen Blephen would have passed successively through the preparatory,
<lb n="170552"/>junior, middle and senior grades of the intermediate and through the
<lb n="170553"/>matriculation, first arts, second arts and arts degree courses of the royal
<lb n="170554"/>university.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170555"/>Why did Bloom refrain from stating that he had frequented the university
<lb n="170556"/>of life?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170557"/>Because of his fluctuating incertitude as to whether this observation had or
<lb n="170558"/>had not been already made by him to Stephen or by Stephen to him.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170559"/>What two temperaments did they individually represent?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170560"/>The scientific. The artistic.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170561"/>What proofs did Bloom adduce to prove that his tendency was towards
<lb n="170562"/>applied, rather than towards pure, science?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170563"/>Certain possible inventions of which he had cogitated when reclining in a
<lb n="170564"/>state of supine repletion to aid digestion, stimulated by his appreciation of
<lb n="170565"/>the importance of inventions now common but once revolutionary, for
<lb n="170566"/>example, the aeronautic parachute, the reflecting telescope, the spiral
<lb n="170567"/>corkscrew, the safety pin, the mineral water siphon, the canal lock with
<lb n="170568"/>winch and sluice, the suction pump.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170569"/>Were these inventions principally intended for an improved scheme of
<lb n="170570"/>kindergarten?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170571"/>Yes, rendering obsolete popguns, elastic airbladders, games of hazard,
<lb n="170572"/>catapults. They comprised astronomical kaleidoscopes exhibiting the twelve
<lb n="170573"/>constellations of the zodiac from Aries to Pisces, miniature mechanical
<lb n="170574"/>orreries, arithmetical gelatine lozenges, geometrical to correspond with
<lb n="170575"/>zoological biscuits, globemap playing balls, historically costumed dolls.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170576"/>What also stimulated him in his cogitations?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170577"/>The financial success achieved by Ephraim Marks and Charles A. James,
<lb n="170578"/>the former by his 1d bazaar at <place type="street"><placeName><num>42</num> George's street, south</placeName></place>, the latter at his
<lb n="170579"/>6½d shop and world's fancy fair and waxwork exhibition at <place type="street"><placeName><num>30</num> Henry
<lb n="170580"/>street</placeName></place>, admission 2d, children 1d: and the infinite possibilities hitherto
<lb n="170581"/>unexploited of the modern art of advertisement if condensed in triliteral
<lb n="170582"/>monoideal symbols, vertically of maximum visibility (divined), horizontally
<lb n="170583"/>of maximum legibility (deciphered) and of magnetising efficacy to arrest
<lb n="170584"/>involuntary attention, to interest, to convince, to decide.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170585"/>Such as?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170586"/>K. 11. Kino's 11/- Trousers.
<lb n="170587"/>House of Keys. Alexander J. Keyes.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170588"/>Such as not?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170589"/>Look at this long candle. Calculate when it burns out and you receive gratis
<lb n="170590"/>1 pair of our special non-compo boots, guaranteed 1 candle power.
<lb n="170591"/>Address: Barclay and Cook, <place type="street"><placeName><num>18</num> Talbot street</placeName></place>.
<lb n="170592"/>Bacilikil (Insect Powder).
<lb n="170593"/>Veribest (Boot Blacking).
<lb n="170594"/>Uwantit (Combined pocket twoblade penknife with corkscrew, nailfile and
<lb n="170595"/>pipecleaner).</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170596"/>Such as never?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170597"/>What is home without Plumtree's Potted Meat?
<lb n="170598"/>Incomplete.
<lb n="170599"/>With it an abode of bliss.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170600"/>Manufactured by George Plumtree, <place type="street"><placeName><num>23</num> Merchants' quay, Dublin</placeName></place>, put up in
<lb n="170601"/>4 oz pots, and inserted by Councillor Joseph P. Nannetti, M. P., Rotunda
<lb n="170602"/>Ward, <place><placeName><num>19</num> Hardwicke street</placeName></place>, under the obituary notices and anniversaries of
<lb n="170603"/>deceases. The name on the label is Plumtree. A plumtree in a meatpot,
<lb n="170604"/>registered trade mark. Beware of imitations. Peatmot. Trumplee. Moutpat.
<lb n="170605"/>Plamtroo.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170606"/>Which example did he adduce to induce Stephen to deduce that originality,
<lb n="170607"/>though producing its own reward, does not invariably conduce to success?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170608"/>His own ideated and rejected project of an illuminated showcart, drawn by
<lb n="170609"/>a beast of burden, in which two smartly dressed girls were to be seated
<lb n="170610"/>engaged in writing.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170611"/>What suggested scene was then constructed by Stephen?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170612"/>Solitary hotel in mountain pass. Autumn. Twilight. Fire lit. In dark corner
<lb n="170613"/>young man seated. Young woman enters. Restless. Solitary. She sits. She
<lb n="170614"/>goes to window. She stands. She sits. Twilight. She thinks. On solitary hotel
<lb n="170615"/>paper she writes. She thinks. She writes. She sighs. Wheels and hoofs. She
<lb n="170616"/>hurries out. He comes from his dark corner. He seizes solitary paper. He
<lb n="170617"/>holds it towards fire. Twilight. He reads. Solitary.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170618"/>What?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170619"/>In sloping, upright and backhands: Queen's Hotel, Queen's Hotel,
<lb n="170620"/>Queen's Hotel. Queen's Ho ...</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170621"/>What suggested scene was then reconstructed by Bloom?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170622"/><place><placeName>The Queen's Hotel, Ennis, county Clare</placeName></place>, where Rudolph Bloom (Rudolf
<lb n="170623"/>Virag) died on the evening of the 27 June 1886, at some hour unstated, in
<lb n="170624"/>consequence of an overdose of monkshood (aconite) selfadministered in the
<lb n="170625"/>form of a neuralgic liniment composed of 2 parts of aconite liniment to 1 of
<lb n="170626"/>chloroform liniment (purchased by him at 10.20 a.m. on the morning of 27
<lb n="170627"/>June 1886 at the medical hall of Francis Dennehy, 17 Church street, Ennis)
<lb n="170628"/>after having, though not in consequence of having, purchased at 3.15 p.m.
<lb n="170629"/>on the afternoon of 27 June 1886 a new boater straw hat, extra smart (after
<lb n="170630"/>having, though not in consequence of having, purchased at the hour and in
<lb n="170631"/>the place aforesaid, the toxin aforesaid), at the general drapery store of
<lb n="170632"/>James Cullen, <place><placeName><num>4</num> Main street, Ennis</placeName></place>.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170633"/>Did he attribute this homonymity to information or coincidence or
<lb n="170634"/>intuition?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170635"/>Coincidence.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170636"/>Did he depict the scene verbally for his guest to see?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170637"/>He preferred himself to see another's face and listen to another's words by
<lb n="170638"/>which potential narration was realised and kinetic temperament relieved.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170639"/>Did he see only a second coincidence in the second scene narrated to him,
<lb n="170640"/>described by the narrator as <title type="short story">A Pisgah Sight of Palestine</title> or <title type="sub">The Parable of
<lb n="170641"/>the Plums</title>?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170642"/>It, with the preceding scene and with others unnarrated but existent by
<lb n="170643"/>implication, to which add essays on various subjects or moral apothegms
<lb n="170644"/>(e.g. <title type="short story">My Favourite Hero</title> or <title type="sub">Procrastination is the Thief of Time</title>) composed
<lb n="170645"/>during schoolyears, seemed to him to contain in itself and in conjunction
<lb n="170646"/>with the personal equation certain possibilities of financial, social, personal
<lb n="170647"/>and sexual success, whether specially collected and selected as model
<lb n="170648"/>pedagogic themes (of cent per cent merit) for the use of preparatory and
<lb n="170649"/>junior grade students or contributed in printed form, following the
<lb n="170650"/>precedent of Philip Beaufoy or Doctor Dick or Heblon's <title type="book">Studies in Blue</title>, to
<lb n="170651"/>a publication of certified circulation and solvency or employed verbally as
<lb n="170652"/>intellectual stimulation for sympathetic auditors, tacitly appreciative of
<lb n="170653"/>successful narrative and confidently augurative of successful achievement,
<lb n="170654"/>during the increasingly longer nights gradually following the summer
<lb n="170655"/>solstice on the day but three following, videlicet, Tuesday, 21 June (S.
<lb n="170656"/>Aloysius Gonzaga), sunrise 3.33 a.m., sunset 8.29 p.m.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170657"/>Which domestic problem as much as, if not more than, any other frequently
<lb n="170658"/>engaged his mind?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170659"/>What to do with our wives.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170660"/>What had been his hypothetical singular solutions?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170661"/>Parlour games (dominos, halma, tiddledywinks, spilikins, cup and ball, nap,
<lb n="170662"/>spoil five, bezique, twentyfive, beggar my neighbour, draughts, chess or
<lb n="170663"/>backgammon): embroidery, darning or knitting for the policeaided clothing
<lb n="170664"/>society: musical duets, mandoline and guitar, piano and flute, guitar and
<lb n="170665"/>piano: legal scrivenery or envelope addressing: biweekly visits to variety
<lb n="170666"/>entertainments: commercial activity as pleasantly commanding and
<lb n="170667"/>pleasingly obeyed mistress proprietress in a cool dairy shop or warm cigar
<lb n="170668"/>divan: the clandestine satisfaction of erotic irritation in masculine brothels,
<lb n="170669"/>state inspected and medically controlled: social visits, at regular infrequent
<lb n="170670"/>prevented intervals and with regular frequent preventive superintendence,
<lb n="170671"/>to and from female acquaintances of recognised respectability in the
<lb n="170672"/>vicinity: courses of evening instruction specially designed to render liberal
<lb n="170673"/>instruction agreeable.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170674"/>What instances of deficient mental development in his wife inclined him in
<lb n="170675"/>favour of the lastmentioned (ninth) solution?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170676"/>In disoccupied moments she had more than once covered a sheet of paper
<lb n="170677"/>with signs and hieroglyphics which she stated were Greek and Irish and
<lb n="170678"/>Hebrew characters. She had interrogated constantly at varying intervals as
<lb n="170679"/>to the correct method of writing the capital initial of the name of a city in
<lb n="170680"/>Canada, Quebec. She understood little of political complications, internal,
<lb n="170681"/>or balance of power, external. In calculating the addenda of bills she
<lb n="170682"/>frequently had recourse to digital aid. After completion of laconic epistolary
<lb n="170683"/>compositions she abandoned the implement of calligraphy in the encaustic
<lb n="170684"/>pigment, exposed to the corrosive action of copperas, green vitriol and
<lb n="170685"/>nutgall. Unusual polysyllables of foreign origin she interpreted phonetically
<lb n="170686"/>or by false analogy or by both: metempsychosis (met him pike hoses), alias
<lb n="170687"/>(a mendacious person mentioned in sacred scripture).</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170688"/>What compensated in the false balance of her intelligence for these and
<lb n="170689"/>such deficiencies of judgment regarding persons, places and things?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170690"/>The false apparent parallelism of all perpendicular arms of all balances,
<lb n="170691"/>proved true by construction. The counterbalance of her proficiency of
<lb n="170692"/>judgment regarding one person, proved true by experiment.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170693"/>How had he attempted to remedy this state of comparative ignorance?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170694"/>Variously. By leaving in a conspicuous place a certain book open at a
<lb n="170695"/>certain page: by assuming in her, when alluding explanatorily, latent
<lb n="170696"/>knowledge: by open ridicule in her presence of some absent other's
<lb n="170697"/>ignorant lapse.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170698"/>With what success had he attempted direct instruction?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170699"/>She followed not all, a part of the whole, gave attention with interest,
<lb n="170700"/>comprehended with surprise, with care repeated, with greater difficulty
<lb n="170701"/>remembered, forgot with ease, with misgiving reremembered, rerepeated
<lb n="170702"/>with error.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170703"/>What system had proved more effective?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170704"/>Indirect suggestion implicating selfinterest.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170705"/>Example?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170706"/>She disliked umbrella with rain, he liked woman with umbrella, she disliked
<lb n="170707"/>new hat with rain, he liked woman with new hat, he bought new hat with
<lb n="170708"/>rain, she carried umbrella with new hat.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170709"/>Accepting the analogy implied in his guest's parable which examples of
<lb n="170710"/>postexilic eminence did he adduce?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170711"/>Three seekers of the pure truth, Moses of Egypt, Moses Maimonides,
<lb n="170712"/>author of <title type="book">More Nebukim</title> (Guide of the Perplexed) and Moses Mendelssohn
<lb n="170713"/>of such eminence that from Moses (of Egypt) to Moses (Mendelssohn) there
<lb n="170714"/>arose none like Moses (Maimonides).</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170715"/>What statement was made, under correction, by Bloom concerning a fourth
<lb n="170716"/>seeker of pure truth, by name Aristotle, mentioned, with permission, by
<lb n="170717"/>Stephen?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170718"/>That the seeker mentioned had been a pupil of a rabbinical philosopher,
<lb n="170719"/>name uncertain.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170720"/>Were other anapocryphal illustrious sons of the law and children of a
<lb n="170721"/>selected or rejected race mentioned?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170722"/>Felix Bartholdy Mendelssohn (composer), Baruch Spinoza (philosopher),
<lb n="170723"/>Mendoza (pugilist), Ferdinand Lassalle (reformer, duellist).</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170724"/>What fragments of verse from the ancient Hebrew and ancient Irish
<lb n="170725"/>languages were cited with modulations of voice and translation of texts by
<lb n="170726"/>guest to host and by host to guest?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170727"/>By Stephen: <foreign xml:lang="ga">suil, suil, suil arun, suil go siocair agus suil go cuin</foreign> (walk, walk,
<lb n="170728"/>walk your way, walk in safety, walk with care).</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170729"/>By Bloom: <foreign xml:lang="he">kifeloch, harimon rakatejch m'baad l'zamatejch</foreign> (thy temple
<lb n="170730"/>amid thy hair is as a slice of pomegranate).</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170731"/>How was a glyphic comparison of the phonic symbols of both languages
<lb n="170732"/>made in substantiation of the oral comparison?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170733"/>By juxtaposition. On the penultimate blank page of a book of inferior
<lb n="170734"/>literary style, entituled <title type="book">Sweets of Sin</title> (produced by Bloom and so
<lb n="170735"/>manipulated that its front cover came in contact with the surface of the
<lb n="170736"/>table) with a pencil (supplied by Stephen) Stephen wrote the Irish
<lb n="170737"/>characters for gee, eh, dee, em, simple and modified, and Bloom in turn
<lb n="170738"/>wrote the Hebrew characters ghimel, aleph, daleth and (in the absence of
<lb n="170739"/>mem) a substituted qoph, explaining their arithmetical values as ordinal and
<lb n="170740"/>cardinal numbers, videlicet 3, 1, 4, and 100.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170741"/>Was the knowledge possessed by both of each of these languages, the extinct
<lb n="170742"/>and the revived, theoretical or practical?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170743"/>Theoretical, being confined to certain grammatical rules of accidence and
<lb n="170744"/>syntax and practically excluding vocabulary.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170745"/>What points of contact existed between these languages and between the
<lb n="170746"/>peoples who spoke them?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170747"/>The presence of guttural sounds, diacritic aspirations, epenthetic and servile
<lb n="170748"/>letters in both languages: their antiquity, both having been taught on the
<lb n="170749"/>plain of Shinar 242 years after the deluge in the seminary instituted by
<lb n="170750"/>Fenius Farsaigh, descendant of Noah, progenitor of Israel, and ascendant
<lb n="170751"/>of Heber and Heremon, progenitors of Ireland: their archaeological,
<lb n="170752"/>genealogical, hagiographical, exegetical, homiletic, toponomastic, historical
<lb n="170753"/>and religious literatures comprising the works of rabbis and culdees, Torah,
<lb n="170754"/>Talmud (Mischna and Ghemara), Massor, Pentateuch, Book of the Dun
<lb n="170755"/>Cow, Book of Ballymote, Garland of Howth, Book of Kells: their dispersal,
<lb n="170756"/>persecution, survival and revival: the isolation of their synagogical and
<lb n="170757"/>ecclesiastical rites in ghetto (S. Mary's Abbey) and masshouse (Adam and
<lb n="170758"/>Eve's tavern): the proscription of their national costumes in penal laws and
<lb n="170759"/>jewish dress acts: the restoration in Chanah David of Zion and the
<lb n="170760"/>possibility of Irish political autonomy or devolution.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170761"/>What anthem did Bloom chant partially in anticipation of that multiple,
<lb n="170762"/>ethnically irreducible consummation?</p>
<quote xml:lang="he"><lg rend="italics"><lb n="170763"/><l>Kolod balejwaw pnimah</l>
<lb n="170764"/><l>Nefesch, jehudi, homijah.</l></lg></quote>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170765"/>Why was the chant arrested at the conclusion of this first distich?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170766"/>In consequence of defective mnemotechnic.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170767"/>How did the chanter compensate for this deficiency?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170768"/>By a periphrastic version of the general text.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170769"/>In what common study did their mutual reflections merge?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170770"/>The increasing simplification traceable from the Egyptian epigraphic
<lb n="170771"/>hieroglyphs to the Greek and Roman alphabets and the anticipation of
<lb n="170772"/>modern stenography and telegraphic code in the cuneiform inscriptions
<lb n="170773"/>(Semitic) and the virgular quinquecostate ogham writing (Celtic).</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170774"/>Did the guest comply with his host's request?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170775"/>Doubly, by appending his signature in Irish and Roman characters.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170776"/>What was Stephen's auditive sensation?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170777"/>He heard in a profound ancient male unfamiliar melody the accumulation
<lb n="170778"/>of the past.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170779"/>What was Bloom's visual sensation?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170780"/>He saw in a quick young male familiar form the predestination of a future.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170781"/>What were Stephen's and Bloom's quasisimultaneous volitional
<lb n="170782"/>quasisensations of concealed identities?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170783"/>Visually, Stephen's: The traditional figure of hypostasis, depicted by
<lb n="170784"/>Johannes Damascenus, Lentulus Romanus and Epiphanius Monachus as
<lb n="170785"/>leucodermic, sesquipedalian with winedark hair.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170786"/>Auditively, Bloom's: The traditional accent of the ecstasy of catastrophe.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170787"/>What future careers had been possible for Bloom in the past and with what
<lb n="170788"/>exemplars?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170789"/>In the church, Roman, Anglican or Nonconformist: exemplars, the very
<lb n="170790"/>reverend John Conmee S. J., the reverend T. Salmon, D. D., provost of
<lb n="170791"/>Trinity college, Dr Alexander J. Dowie. At the bar, English or Irish:
<lb n="170792"/>exemplars, Seymour Bushe, K. C., Rufus Isaacs, K. C. On the stage,
<lb n="170793"/>modern or Shakespearean: exemplars, Charles Wyndham, high comedian,
<lb n="170794"/>Osmond Tearle († 1901), exponent of Shakespeare.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170795"/>Did the host encourage his guest to chant in a modulated voice a strange
<lb n="170796"/>legend on an allied theme?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170797"/>Reassuringly, their place, where none could hear them talk, being secluded,
<lb n="170798"/>reassured, the decocted beverages, allowing for subsolid residual sediment
<lb n="170799"/>of a mechanical mixture, water plus sugar plus cream plus cocoa, having
<lb n="170800"/>been consumed.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170801"/>Recite the first (major) part of this chanted legend.</p>
<quote><lg rend="italics"><lb n="170802"/><l>Little Harry Hughes and his schoolfellows all</l>
<lb n="170803"/><l>Went out for to play ball.</l>
<lb n="170804"/><l>And the very first ball little Harry Hughes played</l>
<lb n="170805"/><l>He drove it o'er the jew's garden wall.</l>
<lb n="170806"/><l>And the very second ball little Harry Hughes played</l>
<lb n="170807"/><l>He broke the jew's windows all.</l></lg></quote>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170808"/>[MUSIC]</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170809"/>How did the son of Rudolph receive this first part?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170810"/>With unmixed feeling. Smiling, a jew, he heard with pleasure and saw the
<lb n="170811"/>unbroken kitchen window.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170812"/>Recite the second part (minor) of the legend.</p>
<quote><lg rend="italics"><lb n="170813"/><l>Then out there came the jew's daughter</l>
<lb n="170814"/><l>And she all dressed in green.</l>
<lb n="170815"/><l>"Come back, come back, you pretty little boy,</l>
<lb n="170816"/><l>And play your ball again."</l>
<lb n="170817"/><l>"I can't come back and I won't come back</l>
<lb n="170818"/><l>Without my schoolfellows all.</l>
<lb n="170819"/><l>For if my master he did hear</l>
<lb n="170820"/><l>He'd make it a sorry ball."</l>
<lb n="170821"/><l>She took him by the lilywhite hand</l>
<lb n="170822"/><l>And led him along the hall</l>
<lb n="170823"/><l>Until she led him to a room</l>
<lb n="170824"/><l>Where none could hear him call.</l>
<lb n="170825"/><l>She took a penknife out of her pocket</l>
<lb n="170826"/><l>And cut off his little head.</l>
<lb n="170827"/><l>And now he'll play his ball no more</l>
<lb n="170828"/><l>For he lies among the dead.</l></lg></quote>
    [MUSIC]
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170829"/>How did the father of Millicent receive this second part?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170830"/>With mixed feelings. Unsmiling, he heard and saw with wonder a jew's
<lb n="170831"/>daughter, all dressed in green.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170832"/>Condense Stephen's commentary.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170833"/>One of all, the least of all, is the victim predestined. Once by inadvertence,
<lb n="170834"/>twice by design he challenges his destiny. It comes when he is abandoned
<lb n="170835"/>and challenges him reluctant and, as an apparition of hope and youth, holds
<lb n="170836"/>him unresisting. It leads him to a strange habitation, to a secret infidel
<lb n="170837"/>apartment, and there, implacable, immolates him, consenting.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170838"/>Why was the host (victim predestined) sad?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170839"/>He wished that a tale of a deed should be told of a deed not by him should
<lb n="170840"/>by him not be told.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170841"/>Why was the host (reluctant, unresisting) still?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170842"/>In accordance with the law of the conservation of energy.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170843"/>Why was the host (secret infidel) silent?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170844"/>He weighed the possible evidences for and against ritual murder: the
<lb n="170845"/>incitations of the hierarchy, the superstition of the populace, the
<lb n="170846"/>propagation of rumour in continued fraction of veridicity, the envy of
<lb n="170847"/>opulence, the influence of retaliation, the sporadic reappearance of atavistic
<lb n="170848"/>delinquency, the mitigating circumstances of fanaticism, hypnotic
<lb n="170849"/>suggestion and somnambulism.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170850"/>From which (if any) of these mental or physical disorders was he not totally
<lb n="170851"/>immune?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170852"/>From hypnotic suggestion: once, waking, he had not recognised his
<lb n="170853"/>sleeping apartment: more than once, waking, he had been for an indefinite
<lb n="170854"/>time incapable of moving or uttering sounds. From somnambulism: once,
<lb n="170855"/>sleeping, his body had risen, crouched and crawled in the direction of a
<lb n="170856"/>heatless fire and, having attained its destination, there, curled, unheated, in
<lb n="170857"/>night attire had lain, sleeping.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170858"/>Had this latter or any cognate phenomenon declared itself in any member
<lb n="170859"/>of his family?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170860"/>Twice, in <place type="street"><placeName>Holles street</placeName></place> and in <place><placeName>Ontario terrace</placeName></place>, his daughter Millicent
<lb n="170861"/>(Milly) at the ages of 6 and 8 years had uttered in sleep an exclamation of
<lb n="170862"/>terror and had replied to the interrogations of two figures in night attire
<lb n="170863"/>with a vacant mute expression.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170864"/>What other infantile memories had he of her?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170865"/>15 June 1889. A querulous newborn female infant crying to cause and
<lb n="170866"/>lessen congestion. A child renamed Padney Socks she shook with shocks
<lb n="170867"/>her moneybox: counted his three free moneypenny buttons, one, tloo, tlee:
<lb n="170868"/>a doll, a boy, a sailor she cast away: blond, born of two dark, she had blond
<lb n="170869"/>ancestry, remote, a violation, Herr Hauptmann Hainau, Austrian army,
<lb n="170870"/>proximate, a hallucination, lieutenant Mulvey, British navy.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170871"/>What endemic characteristics were present?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170872"/>Conversely the nasal and frontal formation was derived in a direct line of
<lb n="170873"/>lineage which, though interrupted, would continue at distant intervals to
<lb n="170874"/>more distant intervals to its most distant intervals.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170875"/>What memories had he of her adolescence?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170876"/>She relegated her hoop and skippingrope to a recess. On the duke's lawn,
<lb n="170877"/>entreated by an English visitor, she declined to permit him to make and take
<lb n="170878"/>away her photographic image (objection not stated). On the South Circular
<lb n="170879"/>road in the company of Elsa Potter, followed by an individual of sinister
<lb n="170880"/>aspect, she went half way down <place type="street"><placeName>Stamer street</placeName></place> and turned abruptly back
<lb n="170881"/>(reason of change not stated). On the vigil of the 15th anniversary of her
<lb n="170882"/>birth she wrote a letter from <place><placeName>Mullingar, county Westmeath</placeName></place>, making a brief
<lb n="170883"/>allusion to a local student (faculty and year not stated).</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170884"/>Did that first division, portending a second division, afflict him?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170885"/>Less than he had imagined, more than he had hoped.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170886"/>What second departure was contemporaneously perceived by him similarly,
<lb n="170887"/>if differently?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170888"/>A temporary departure of his cat.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170889"/>Why similarly, why differently?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170890"/>Similarly, because actuated by a secret purpose the quest of a new male
<lb n="170891"/>(Mullingar student) or of a healing herb (valerian). Differently, because of
<lb n="170892"/>different possible returns to the inhabitants or to the habitation.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170893"/>In other respects were their differences similar?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170894"/>In passivity, in economy, in the instinct of tradition, in unexpectedness.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170895"/>As?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170896"/>Inasmuch as leaning she sustained her blond hair for him to ribbon it for
<lb n="170897"/>her (cf neckarching cat). Moreover, on the free surface of the lake in
<lb n="170898"/>Stephen's green amid inverted reflections of trees her uncommented spit,
<lb n="170899"/>describing concentric circles of waterrings, indicated by the constancy of its
<lb n="170900"/>permanence the locus of a somnolent prostrate fish (cf mousewatching cat).
<lb n="170901"/>Again, in order to remember the date, combatants, issue and consequences
<lb n="170902"/>of a famous military engagement she pulled a plait of her hair (cf
<lb n="170903"/>earwashing cat). Furthermore, silly Milly, she dreamed of having had an
<lb n="170904"/>unspoken unremembered conversation with a horse whose name had been
<lb n="170905"/>Joseph to whom (which) she had offered a tumblerful of lemonade which it
<lb n="170906"/>(he) had appeared to have accepted (cf hearthdreaming cat). Hence, in
<lb n="170907"/>passivity, in economy, in the instinct of tradition, in unexpectedness, their
<lb n="170908"/>differences were similar.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170909"/>In what way had he utilised gifts (1) an owl, 2) a clock), given as
<lb n="170910"/>matrimonial auguries, to interest and to instruct her?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170911"/>As object lessons to explain: 1) the nature and habits of oviparous animals,
<lb n="170912"/>the possibility of aerial flight, certain abnormalities of vision, the secular
<lb n="170913"/>process of imbalsamation: 2) the principle of the pendulum, exemplified in
<lb n="170914"/>bob, wheelgear and regulator, the translation in terms of human or social
<lb n="170915"/>regulation of the various positions of clockwise moveable indicators on an
<lb n="170916"/>unmoving dial, the exactitude of the recurrence per hour of an instant in
<lb n="170917"/>each hour when the longer and the shorter indicator were at the same angle
<lb n="170918"/>of inclination, <foreign xml:lang="la">videlicet</foreign>, 5 5/₁₁ minutes past each hour per hour in
<lb n="170919"/>arithmetical progression.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170920"/>In what manners did she reciprocate?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170921"/>She remembered: on the 27th anniversary of his birth she presented to him a
<lb n="170922"/>breakfast moustachecup of imitation Crown Derby porcelain ware. She
<lb n="170923"/>provided: at quarter day or thereabouts if or when purchases had been
<lb n="170924"/>made by him not for her she showed herself attentive to his necessities,
<lb n="170925"/>anticipating his desires. She admired: a natural phenomenon having been
<lb n="170926"/>explained by him to her she expressed the immediate desire to possess
<lb n="170927"/>without gradual acquisition a fraction of his science, the moiety, the
<lb n="170928"/>quarter, a thousandth part.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170929"/>What proposal did Bloom, diambulist, father of Milly, somnambulist, make
<lb n="170930"/>to Stephen, noctambulist?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170931"/>To pass in repose the hours intervening between Thursday (proper) and
<lb n="170932"/>Friday (normal) on an extemporised cubicle in the apartment immediately
<lb n="170933"/>above the kitchen and immediately adjacent to the sleeping apartment of his
<lb n="170934"/>host and hostess.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170935"/>What various advantages would or might have resulted from a
<lb n="170936"/>prolongation of such an extemporisation?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170937"/>For the guest: security of domicile and seclusion of study. For the host:
<lb n="170938"/>rejuvenation of intelligence, vicarious satisfaction. For the hostess:
<lb n="170939"/>disintegration of obsession, acquisition of correct Italian pronunciation.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170940"/>Why might these several provisional contingencies between a guest and a
<lb n="170941"/>hostess not necessarily preclude or be precluded by a permanent eventuality
<lb n="170942"/>of reconciliatory union between a schoolfellow and a jew's daughter?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170943"/>Because the way to daughter led through mother, the way to mother
<lb n="170944"/>through daughter.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170945"/>To what inconsequent polysyllabic question of his host did the guest return
<lb n="170946"/>a monosyllabic negative answer?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170947"/>If he had known the late Mrs Emily Sinico, accidentally killed at <place><placeName>Sydney
<lb n="170948"/>Parade railway station</placeName></place>, 14 October 1903.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170949"/>What inchoate corollary statement was consequently suppressed by the
<lb n="170950"/>host?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170951"/>A statement explanatory of his absence on the occasion of the interment of
<lb n="170952"/>Mrs Mary Dedalus (born Goulding), 26 June 1903, vigil of the anniversary
<lb n="170953"/>of the decease of Rudolph Bloom (born Virag).</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170954"/>Was the proposal of asylum accepted?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170955"/>Promptly, inexplicably, with amicability, gratefully it was declined.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170956"/>What exchange of money took place between host and guest?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170957"/>The former returned to the latter, without interest, a sum of money
<lb n="170958"/>(£1-7-0), one pound seven shillings sterling, advanced by the latter to the
<lb n="170959"/>former.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170960"/>What counterproposals were alternately advanced, accepted, modified,
<lb n="170961"/>declined, restated in other terms, reaccepted, ratified, reconfirmed?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170962"/>To inaugurate a prearranged course of Italian instruction, place the
<lb n="170963"/>residence of the instructed. To inaugurate a course of vocal instruction,
<lb n="170964"/>place the residence of the instructress. To inaugurate a series of static,
<lb n="170965"/>semistatic and peripatetic intellectual dialogues, places the residence of both
<lb n="170966"/>speakers (if both speakers were resident in the same place), the Ship hotel
<lb n="170967"/>and tavern, <place type="street"><placeName><num>6</num> Lower Abbey street</placeName></place> (W. and E. Connery, proprietors), the
<lb n="170968"/>National Library of Ireland, <place><placeName type="street"><num>10</num> Kildare street</placeName></place>, the National Maternity
<lb n="170969"/>Hospital, <place type="street"><placeName><num>29, 30 and 31</num> Holles street</placeName></place>, a public garden, the vicinity of a place
<lb n="170970"/>of worship, a conjunction of two or more public thoroughfares, the point of
<lb n="170971"/>bisection of a right line drawn between their residences (if both speakers
<lb n="170972"/>were resident in different places).</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170973"/>What rendered problematic for Bloom the realisation of these mutually
<lb n="170974"/>selfexcluding propositions?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170975"/>The irreparability of the past: once at a performance of Albert Hengler's
<lb n="170976"/>circus in the Rotunda, Rutland square, Dublin, an intuitive particoloured
<lb n="170977"/>clown in quest of paternity had penetrated from the ring to a place in the
<lb n="170978"/>auditorium where Bloom, solitary, was seated and had publicly declared to
<lb n="170979"/>an exhilarated audience that he (Bloom) was his (the clown's) papa. The
<lb n="170980"/>imprevidibility of the future: once in the summer of 1898 he (Bloom) had
<lb n="170981"/>marked a florin (2/-) with three notches on the milled edge and tendered it
<lb n="170982"/>in payment of an account due to and received by J. and T. Davy, family
<lb n="170983"/>grocers, <place type="street"><placeName><num>1</num> Charlemont Mall, Grand Canal</placeName></place>, for circulation on the waters of
<lb n="170984"/>civic finance, for possible, circuitous or direct, return.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170985"/>Was the clown Bloom's son?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170986"/>No.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170987"/>Had Bloom's coin returned?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170988"/>Never.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170989"/>Why would a recurrent frustration the more depress him?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170990"/>Because at the critical turningpoint of human existence he desired to amend
<lb n="170991"/>many social conditions, the product of inequality and avarice and
<lb n="170992"/>international animosity.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170993"/>He believed then that human life was infinitely perfectible, eliminating these
<lb n="170994"/>conditions?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="170995"/>There remained the generic conditions imposed by natural, as distinct from
<lb n="170996"/>human law, as integral parts of the human whole: the necessity of
<lb n="170997"/>destruction to procure alimentary sustenance: the painful character of the
<lb n="170998"/>ultimate functions of separate existence, the agonies of birth and death: the
<lb n="170999"/>monotonous menstruation of simian and (particularly) human females
<lb n="171000"/>extending from the age of puberty to the menopause: inevitable accidents at
<lb n="171001"/>sea, in mines and factories: certain very painful maladies and their resultant
<lb n="171002"/>surgical operations, innate lunacy and congenital criminality, decimating
<lb n="171003"/>epidemics: catastrophic cataclysms which make terror the basis of human
<lb n="171004"/>mentality: seismic upheavals the epicentres of which are located in densely
<lb n="171005"/>populated regions: the fact of vital growth, through convulsions of
<lb n="171006"/>metamorphosis, from infancy through maturity to decay.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171007"/>Why did he desist from speculation?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171008"/>Because it was a task for a superior intelligence to substitute other more
<lb n="171009"/>acceptable phenomena in the place of the less acceptable phenomena to be
<lb n="171010"/>removed.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171011"/>Did Stephen participate in his dejection?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171012"/>He affirmed his significance as a conscious rational animal proceeding
<lb n="171013"/>syllogistically from the known to the unknown and a conscious rational
<lb n="171014"/>reagent between a micro and a macrocosm ineluctably constructed upon the
<lb n="171015"/>incertitude of the void.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171016"/>Was this affirmation apprehended by Bloom?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171017"/>Not verbally. Substantially.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171018"/>What comforted his misapprehension?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171019"/>That as a competent keyless citizen he had proceeded energetically from the
<lb n="171020"/>unknown to the known through the incertitude of the void.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171021"/>In what order of precedence, with what attendant ceremony was the exodus
<lb n="171022"/>from the house of bondage to the wilderness of inhabitation effected?</p>
<p rend="inset"><lb n="171023"/>Lighted Candle in Stick
<lb n="171024"/>borne by
<lb n="171025"/>BLOOM
<lb n="171026"/>Diaconal Hat on Ashplant
<lb n="171027"/>borne by
<lb n="171028"/>STEPHEN</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171029"/>With what intonation <foreign xml:lang="la">secreto</foreign> of what commemorative psalm?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171030"/>The 113th, <foreign xml:lang="la">modus peregrinus</foreign>: <quote source="bible" xml:lang="la">In exitu Israel de Egypto: domus Jacob de
<lb n="171031"/>populo barbaro</quote>.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171032"/>What did each do at the door of egress?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171033"/>Bloom set the candlestick on the floor. Stephen put the hat on his head.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171034"/>For what creature was the door of egress a door of ingress?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171035"/>For a cat.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171036"/>What spectacle confronted them when they, first the host, then the guest,
<lb n="171037"/>emerged silently, doubly dark, from obscurity by a passage from the rere of
<lb n="171038"/>the house into the penumbra of the garden?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171039"/>The heaventree of stars hung with humid nightblue fruit.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171040"/>With what meditations did Bloom accompany his demonstration to his
<lb n="171041"/>companion of various constellations?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171042"/>Meditations of evolution increasingly vaster: of the moon invisible in
<lb n="171043"/>incipient lunation, approaching perigee: of the infinite lattiginous
<lb n="171044"/>scintillating uncondensed milky way, discernible by daylight by an observer
<lb n="171045"/>placed at the lower end of a cylindrical vertical shaft 5000 ft deep sunk
<lb n="171046"/>from the surface towards the centre of the earth: of Sirius (alpha in Canis
<lb n="171047"/>Maior) 10 lightyears (57,000,000,000,000 miles) distant and in volume 900
<lb n="171048"/>times the dimension of our planet: of Arcturus: of the precession of
<lb n="171049"/>equinoxes: of Orion with belt and sextuple sun theta and nebula in which
<lb n="171050"/>100 of our solar systems could be contained: of moribund and of nascent
<lb n="171051"/>new stars such as Nova in 1901: of our system plunging towards the
<lb n="171052"/>constellation of Hercules: of the parallax or parallactic drift of socalled
<lb n="171053"/>fixed stars, in reality evermoving wanderers from immeasurably remote
<lb n="171054"/>eons to infinitely remote futures in comparison with which the years,
<lb n="171055"/>threescore and ten, of allotted human life formed a parenthesis of
<lb n="171056"/>infinitesimal brevity.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171057"/>Were there obverse meditations of involution increasingly less vast?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171058"/>Of the eons of geological periods recorded in the stratifications of the earth:
<lb n="171059"/>of the myriad minute entomological organic existences concealed in cavities
<lb n="171060"/>of the earth, beneath removable stones, in hives and mounds, of microbes,
<lb n="171061"/>germs, bacteria, bacilli, spermatozoa: of the incalculable trillions of billions
<lb n="171062"/>of millions of imperceptible molecules contained by cohesion of molecular
<lb n="171063"/>affinity in a single pinhead: of the universe of human serum constellated
<lb n="171064"/>with red and white bodies, themselves universes of void space constellated
<lb n="171065"/>with other bodies, each, in continuity, its universe of divisible component
<lb n="171066"/>bodies of which each was again divisible in divisions of redivisible
<lb n="171067"/>component bodies, dividends and divisors ever diminishing without actual
<lb n="171068"/>division till, if the progress were carried far enough, nought nowhere was
<lb n="171069"/>never reached.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171070"/>Why did he not elaborate these calculations to a more precise result?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171071"/>Because some years previously in 1886 when occupied with the problem of
<lb n="171072"/>the quadrature of the circle he had learned of the existence of a number
<lb n="171073"/>computed to a relative degree of accuracy to be of such magnitude and of so
<lb n="171074"/>many places, e.g., the 9th power of the 9th power of 9, that, the result having
<lb n="171075"/>been obtained, 33 closely printed volumes of 1000 pages each of
<lb n="171076"/>innumerable quires and reams of India paper would have to be
<lb n="171077"/>requisitioned in order to contain the complete tale of its printed integers of
<lb n="171078"/>units, tens, hundreds, thousands, tens of thousands, hundreds of thousands,
<lb n="171079"/>millions, tens of millions, hundreds of millions, billions, the nucleus of the
<lb n="171080"/>nebula of every digit of every series containing succinctly the potentiality of
<lb n="171081"/>being raised to the utmost kinetic elaboration of any power of any of its
<lb n="171082"/>powers.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171083"/>Did he find the problems of the inhabitability of the planets and their
<lb n="171084"/>satellites by a race, given in species, and of the possible social and moral
<lb n="171085"/>redemption of said race by a redeemer, easier of solution?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171086"/>Of a different order of difficulty. Conscious that the human organism,
<lb n="171087"/>normally capable of sustaining an atmospheric pressure of 19 tons, when
<lb n="171088"/>elevated to a considerable altitude in the terrestrial atmosphere suffered
<lb n="171089"/>with arithmetical progression of intensity, according as the line of
<lb n="171090"/>demarcation between troposphere and stratosphere was approximated,
<lb n="171091"/>from nasal hemorrhage, impeded respiration and vertigo, when proposing
<lb n="171092"/>this problem for solution, he had conjectured as a working hypothesis
<lb n="171093"/>which could not be proved impossible that a more adaptable and differently
<lb n="171094"/>anatomically constructed race of beings might subsist otherwise under
<lb n="171095"/>Martian, Mercurial, Veneral, Jovian, Saturnian, Neptunian or Uranian
<lb n="171096"/>sufficient and equivalent conditions, though an apogean humanity of beings
<lb n="171097"/>created in varying forms with finite differences resulting similar to the
<lb n="171098"/>whole and to one another would probably there as here remain inalterably
<lb n="171099"/>and inalienably attached to vanities, to vanities of vanities and to all that is
<lb n="171100"/>vanity.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171101"/>And the problem of possible redemption?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171102"/>The minor was proved by the major.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171103"/>Which various features of the constellations were in turn considered?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171104"/>The various colours significant of various degrees of vitality (white, yellow,
<lb n="171105"/>crimson, vermilion, cinnabar): their degrees of brilliancy: their magnitudes
<lb n="171106"/>revealed up to and including the 7th: their positions: the waggoner's star:
<lb n="171107"/>Walsingham way: the chariot of David: the annular cinctures of Saturn:
<lb n="171108"/>the condensation of spiral nebulae into suns: the interdependent gyrations
<lb n="171109"/>of double suns: the independent synchronous discoveries of Galileo, Simon
<lb n="171110"/>Marius, Piazzi, Le Verrier, Herschel, Galle: the systematisations attempted
<lb n="171111"/>by Bode and Kepler of cubes of distances and squares of times of
<lb n="171112"/>revolution: the almost infinite compressibility of hirsute comets and their
<lb n="171113"/>vast elliptical egressive and reentrant orbits from perihelion to aphelion: the
<lb n="171114"/>sidereal origin of meteoric stones: the Libyan floods on Mars about the
<lb n="171115"/>period of the birth of the younger astroscopist: the annual recurrence of
<lb n="171116"/>meteoric showers about the period of the feast of S. Lawrence (martyr, 10
<lb n="171117"/>August): the monthly recurrence known as the new moon with the old
<lb n="171118"/>moon in her arms: the posited influence of celestial on human bodies: the
<lb n="171119"/>appearance of a star (1st magnitude) of exceeding brilliancy dominating by
<lb n="171120"/>night and day (a new luminous sun generated by the collision and
<lb n="171121"/>amalgamation in incandescence of two nonluminous exsuns) about the
<lb n="171122"/>period of the birth of William Shakespeare over delta in the recumbent
<lb n="171123"/>neversetting constellation of Cassiopeia and of a star (2nd magnitude) of
<lb n="171124"/>similar origin but of lesser brilliancy which had appeared in and
<lb n="171125"/>disappeared from the constellation of the Corona Septentrionalis about the
<lb n="171126"/>period of the birth of Leopold Bloom and of other stars of (presumably)
<lb n="171127"/>similar origin which had (effectively or presumably) appeared in and
<lb n="171128"/>disappeared from the constellation of Andromeda about the period of the
<lb n="171129"/>birth of Stephen Dedalus, and in and from the constellation of Auriga some
<lb n="171130"/>years after the birth and death of Rudolph Bloom, junior, and in and from
<lb n="171131"/>other constellations some years before or after the birth or death of other
<lb n="171132"/>persons: the attendant phenomena of eclipses, solar and lunar, from
<lb n="171133"/>immersion to emersion, abatement of wind, transit of shadow, taciturnity of
<lb n="171134"/>winged creatures, emergence of nocturnal or crepuscular animals,
<lb n="171135"/>persistence of infernal light, obscurity of terrestrial waters, pallor of human
<lb n="171136"/>beings.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171137"/>His (Bloom's) logical conclusion, having weighed the matter and allowing
<lb n="171138"/>for possible error?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171139"/>That it was not a heaventree, not a heavengrot, not a heavenbeast, not a
<lb n="171140"/>heavenman. That it was a Utopia, there being no known method from the
<lb n="171141"/>known to the unknown: an infinity renderable equally finite by the
<lb n="171142"/>suppositious apposition of one or more bodies equally of the same and of
<lb n="171143"/>different magnitudes: a mobility of illusory forms immobilised in space,
<lb n="171144"/>remobilised in air: a past which possibly had ceased to exist as a present
<lb n="171145"/>before its probable spectators had entered actual present existence.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171146"/>Was he more convinced of the esthetic value of the spectacle?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171147"/>Indubitably in consequence of the reiterated examples of poets in the
<lb n="171148"/>delirium of the frenzy of attachment or in the abasement of rejection
<lb n="171149"/>invoking ardent sympathetic constellations or the frigidity of the satellite of
<lb n="171150"/>their planet.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171151"/>Did he then accept as an article of belief the theory of astrological
<lb n="171152"/>influences upon sublunary disasters?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171153"/>It seemed to him as possible of proof as of confutation and the
<lb n="171154"/>nomenclature employed in its selenographical charts as attributable to
<lb n="171155"/>verifiable intuition as to fallacious analogy: the lake of dreams, the sea of
<lb n="171156"/>rains, the gulf of dews, the ocean of fecundity.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171157"/>What special affinities appeared to him to exist between the moon and
<lb n="171158"/>woman?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171159"/>Her antiquity in preceding and surviving successive tellurian generations:
<lb n="171160"/>her nocturnal predominance: her satellitic dependence: her luminary
<lb n="171161"/>reflection: her constancy under all her phases, rising and setting by her
<lb n="171162"/>appointed times, waxing and waning: the forced invariability of her aspect:
<lb n="171163"/>her indeterminate response to inaffirmative interrogation: her potency over
<lb n="171164"/>effluent and refluent waters: her power to enamour, to mortify, to invest
<lb n="171165"/>with beauty, to render insane, to incite to and aid delinquency: the tranquil
<lb n="171166"/>inscrutability of her visage: the terribility of her isolated dominant
<lb n="171167"/>implacable resplendent propinquity: her omens of tempest and of calm: the
<lb n="171168"/>stimulation of her light, her motion and her presence: the admonition of her
<lb n="171169"/>craters, her arid seas, her silence: her splendour, when visible: her
<lb n="171170"/>attraction, when invisible.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171171"/>What visible luminous sign attracted Bloom's, who attracted Stephen's,
<lb n="171172"/>gaze?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171173"/>In the second storey (rere) of <place><placeName>his (Bloom's) house</placeName></place> the light of a paraffin oil
<lb n="171174"/>lamp with oblique shade projected on a screen of roller blind supplied by
<lb n="171175"/>Frank O'Hara, window blind, curtain pole and revolving shutter
<lb n="171176"/>manufacturer, <place type="street"><placeName><num>16</num> Aungier street</placeName></place>.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171177"/>How did he elucidate the mystery of an invisible attractive person, his wife
<lb n="171178"/>Marion (Molly) Bloom, denoted by a visible splendid sign, a lamp?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171179"/>With indirect and direct verbal allusions or affirmations: with subdued
<lb n="171180"/>affection and admiration: with description: with impediment: with
<lb n="171181"/>suggestion.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171182"/>Both then were silent?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171183"/>Silent, each contemplating the other in both mirrors of the reciprocal flesh
<lb n="171184"/>of theirhisnothis fellowfaces.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171185"/>Were they indefinitely inactive?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171186"/>At Stephen's suggestion, at Bloom's instigation both, first Stephen, then
<lb n="171187"/>Bloom, in penumbra urinated, their sides contiguous, their organs of
<lb n="171188"/>micturition reciprocally rendered invisible by manual circumposition, their
<lb n="171189"/>gazes, first Bloom's, then Stephen's, elevated to the projected luminous and
<lb n="171190"/>semiluminous shadow.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171191"/>Similarly?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171192"/>The trajectories of their, first sequent, then simultaneous, urinations were
<lb n="171193"/>dissimilar: Bloom's longer, less irruent, in the incomplete form of the
<lb n="171194"/>bifurcated penultimate alphabetical letter, who in his ultimate year at High
<lb n="171195"/>School (1880) had been capable of attaining the point of greatest altitude
<lb n="171196"/>against the whole concurrent strength of the institution, 210 scholars:
<lb n="171197"/>Stephen's higher, more sibilant, who in the ultimate hours of the previous
<lb n="171198"/>day had augmented by diuretic consumption an insistent vesical pressure.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171199"/>What different problems presented themselves to each concerning the
<lb n="171200"/>invisible audible collateral organ of the other?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171201"/>To Bloom: the problems of irritability, tumescence, rigidity, reactivity,
<lb n="171202"/>dimension, sanitariness, pilosity.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171203"/>To Stephen: the problem of the sacerdotal integrity of Jesus circumcised (1
<lb n="171204"/>January, holiday of obligation to hear mass and abstain from unnecessary
<lb n="171205"/>servile work) and the problem as to whether the divine prepuce, the carnal
<lb n="171206"/>bridal ring of the holy Roman catholic apostolic church, conserved in
<lb n="171207"/><place type="city"><placeName>Calcata</placeName></place>, were deserving of simple hyperduly or of the fourth degree of
<lb n="171208"/>latria accorded to the abscission of such divine excrescences as hair and
<lb n="171209"/>toenails.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171210"/>What celestial sign was by both simultaneously observed?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171211"/>A star precipitated with great apparent velocity across the firmament from
<lb n="171212"/>Vega in the Lyre above the zenith beyond the stargroup of the Tress of
<lb n="171213"/>Berenice towards the zodiacal sign of Leo.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171214"/>How did the centripetal remainer afford egress to the centrifugal departer?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171215"/>By inserting the barrel of an arruginated male key in the hole of an unstable
<lb n="171216"/>female lock, obtaining a purchase on the bow of the key and turning its
<lb n="171217"/>wards from right to left, withdrawing a bolt from its staple, pulling inward
<lb n="171218"/>spasmodically an obsolescent unhinged door and revealing an aperture for
<lb n="171219"/>free egress and free ingress.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171220"/>How did they take leave, one of the other, in separation?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171221"/>Standing perpendicular at the same door and on different sides of its base,
<lb n="171222"/>the lines of their valedictory arms, meeting at any point and forming any
<lb n="171223"/>angle less than the sum of two right angles.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171224"/>What sound accompanied the union of their tangent, the disunion of their
<lb n="171225"/>(respectively) centrifugal and centripetal hands?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171226"/>The sound of the peal of the hour of the night by the chime of the bells in
<lb n="171227"/>the church of Saint George.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171228"/>What echoes of that sound were by both and each heard?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171229"/>By Stephen:</p>
<quote xml:lang="la"><lg rend="italics"><lb n="171230"/><l>Liliata rutilantium. Turma circumdet.</l>
<lb n="171231"/><l>Iubilantium te virginum. Chorus excipiat.</l></lg></quote>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171232"/>By Bloom:</p>
<said who="gc" direct="false" rend="italics"><lg rend="italics"><lb n="171233"/><l>Heigho, heigho,</l>
<lb n="171234"/><l>Heigho, heigho.</l></lg></said>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171235"/>Where were the several members of the company which with Bloom that
<lb n="171236"/>day at the bidding of that peal had travelled from <place><placeName>Sandymount<place><placeName> in the south
<lb n="171237"/>to <place><placeName>Glasnevin</placeName></place> in the north?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171238"/>Martin Cunningham (in bed), Jack Power (in bed), Simon Dedalus (in
<lb n="171239"/>bed), Ned Lambert (in bed), Tom Kernan (in bed), Joe Hynes (in bed),
<lb n="171240"/>John Henry Menton (in bed), Bernard Corrigan (in bed), Patsy Dignam (in
<lb n="171241"/>bed), Paddy Dignam (in the grave).</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171242"/>Alone, what did Bloom hear?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171243"/>The double reverberation of retreating feet on the heavenborn earth, the
<lb n="171244"/>double vibration of a jew's harp in the resonant lane.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171245"/>Alone, what did Bloom feel?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171246"/>The cold of interstellar space, thousands of degrees below freezing point or
<lb n="171247"/>the absolute zero of Fahrenheit, Centigrade or Réaumur: the incipient
<lb n="171248"/>intimations of proximate dawn.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171249"/>Of what did bellchime and handtouch and footstep and lonechill remind
<lb n="171250"/>him?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171251"/>Of companions now in various manners in different places defunct: Percy
<lb n="171252"/>Apjohn (killed in action, <place><placeName>Modder River</placeName></place>), Philip Gilligan (phthisis, <place><placeName>Jervis
<lb n="171253"/>Street hospital</placeName></place>), Matthew F. Kane (accidental drowning, <place><placeName>Dublin Bay</placeName></place>),
<lb n="171254"/>Philip Moisel (pyemia, <place><placeName>Heytesbury street</placeName></place>), Michael Hart (phthisis, <place><placeName>Mater
<lb n="171255"/>Misericordiae hospital</placeName></place>), Patrick Dignam (apoplexy, <place><placeName>Sandymount</placeName></place>).</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171256"/>What prospect of what phenomena inclined him to remain?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171257"/>The disparition of three final stars, the diffusion of daybreak, the apparition
<lb n="171258"/>of a new solar disk.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171259"/>Had he ever been a spectator of those phenomena?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171260"/>Once, in 1887, after a protracted performance of charades in <place><placeName>the house of
<lb n="171261"/>Luke Doyle, Kimmage</placeName></place>, he had awaited with patience the apparition of the
<lb n="171262"/>diurnal phenomenon, seated on a wall, his gaze turned in the direction of
<lb n="171263"/><place><placeName>Mizrach</placeName></place>, the east.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171264"/>He remembered the initial paraphenomena?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171265"/>More active air, a matutinal distant cock, ecclesiastical clocks at various
<lb n="171266"/>points, avine music, the isolated tread of an early wayfarer, the visible
<lb n="171267"/>diffusion of the light of an invisible luminous body, the first golden limb of
<lb n="171268"/>the resurgent sun perceptible low on the horizon.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171269"/>Did he remain?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171270"/>With deep inspiration he returned, retraversing the garden, reentering the
<lb n="171271"/>passage, reclosing the door. With brief suspiration he reassumed the candle,
<lb n="171272"/>reascended the stairs, reapproached the door of the front room, hallfloor,
<lb n="171273"/>and reentered.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171274"/>What suddenly arrested his ingress?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171275"/>The right temporal lobe of the hollow sphere of his cranium came into
<lb n="171276"/>contact with a solid timber angle where, an infinitesimal but sensible
<lb n="171277"/>fraction of a second later, a painful sensation was located in consequence of
<lb n="171278"/>antecedent sensations transmitted and registered.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171279"/>Describe the alterations effected in the disposition of the articles of
<lb n="171280"/>furniture.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171281"/>A sofa upholstered in prune plush had been translocated from opposite the
<lb n="171282"/>door to the ingleside near the compactly furled Union Jack (an alteration
<lb n="171283"/>which he had frequently intended to execute): the blue and white checker
<lb n="171284"/>inlaid majolicatopped table had been placed opposite the door in the place
<lb n="171285"/>vacated by the prune plush sofa: the walnut sideboard (a projecting angle
<lb n="171286"/>of which had momentarily arrested his ingress) had been moved from its
<lb n="171287"/>position beside the door to a more advantageous but more perilous position
<lb n="171288"/>in front of the door: two chairs had been moved from right and left of the
<lb n="171289"/>ingleside to the position originally occupied by the blue and white checker
<lb n="171290"/>inlaid majolicatopped table.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171291"/>Describe them.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171292"/>One: a squat stuffed easychair, with stout arms extended and back slanted
<lb n="171293"/>to the rere, which, repelled in recoil, had then upturned an irregular fringe
<lb n="171294"/>of a rectangular rug and now displayed on its amply upholstered seat a
<lb n="171295"/>centralised diffusing and diminishing discolouration. The other: a slender
<lb n="171296"/>splayfoot chair of glossy cane curves, placed directly opposite the former,
<lb n="171297"/>its frame from top to seat and from seat to base being varnished dark
<lb n="171298"/>brown, its seat being a bright circle of white plaited rush.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171299"/>What significances attached to these two chairs?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171300"/>Significances of similitude, of posture, of symbolism, of circumstantial
<lb n="171301"/>evidence, of testimonial supermanence.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171302"/>What occupied the position originally occupied by the sideboard?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171303"/>A vertical piano (Cadby) with exposed keyboard, its closed coffin
<lb n="171304"/>supporting a pair of long yellow ladies' gloves and an emerald ashtray
<lb n="171305"/>containing four consumed matches, a partly consumed cigarette and two
<lb n="171306"/>discoloured ends of cigarettes, its musicrest supporting the music in the key
<lb n="171307"/>of G natural for voice and piano of <title type="song">Love's Old Sweet Song</title> (words by G.
<lb n="171308"/>Clifton Bingham, composed by J. L. Molloy, sung by Madam Antoinette
<lb n="171309"/>Sterling) open at the last page with the final indications <foreign xml:lang="la">ad libitum</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="it">forte</foreign>,
<lb n="171310"/>pedal, <foreign xml:lang="it">animato</foreign>, sustained pedal, <foreign xml:lang="it">ritirando</foreign>, close.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171311"/>With what sensations did Bloom contemplate in rotation these objects?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171312"/>With strain, elevating a candlestick: with pain, feeling on his right temple a
<lb n="171313"/>contused tumescence: with attention, focussing his gaze on a large dull
<lb n="171314"/>passive and a slender bright active: with solicitation, bending and
<lb n="171315"/>downturning the upturned rugfringe: with amusement, remembering Dr
<lb n="171316"/>Malachi Mulligan's scheme of colour containing the gradation of green:
<lb n="171317"/>with pleasure, repeating the words and antecedent act and perceiving
<lb n="171318"/>through various channels of internal sensibility the consequent and
<lb n="171319"/>concomitant tepid pleasant diffusion of gradual discolouration.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171320"/>His next proceeding?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171321"/>From an open box on the majolicatopped table he extracted a black
<lb n="171322"/>diminutive cone, one inch in height, placed it on its circular base on a small
<lb n="171323"/>tin plate, placed his candlestick on the right corner of the mantelpiece,
<lb n="171324"/>produced from his waistcoat a folded page of prospectus (illustrated)
<lb n="171325"/>entitled Agendath Netaim, unfolded the same, examined it superficially,
<lb n="171326"/>rolled it into a thin cylinder, ignited it in the candleflame, applied it when
<lb n="171327"/>ignited to the apex of the cone till the latter reached the stage of rutilance,
<lb n="171328"/>placed the cylinder in the basin of the candlestick disposing its unconsumed
<lb n="171329"/>part in such a manner as to facilitate total combustion.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171330"/>What followed this operation?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171331"/>The truncated conical crater summit of the diminutive volcano emitted a
<lb n="171332"/>vertical and serpentine fume redolent of aromatic oriental incense.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171333"/>What homothetic objects, other than the candlestick, stood on the
<lb n="171334"/>mantelpiece?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171335"/>A timepiece of striated Connemara marble, stopped at the hour of
<lb n="171336"/>4.46 a.m. on the 21 March 1896, matrimonial gift of Matthew Dillon: a
<lb n="171337"/>dwarf tree of glacial arborescence under a transparent bellshade,
<lb n="171338"/>matrimonial gift of Luke and Caroline Doyle: an embalmed owl,
<lb n="171339"/>matrimonial gift of Alderman John Hooper.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171340"/>What interchanges of looks took place between these three objects and
<lb n="171341"/>Bloom?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171342"/>In the mirror of the giltbordered pierglass the undecorated back of the
<lb n="171343"/>dwarf tree regarded the upright back of the embalmed owl. Before the
<lb n="171344"/>mirror the matrimonial gift of Alderman John Hooper with a clear
<lb n="171345"/>melancholy wise bright motionless compassionate gaze regarded Bloom
<lb n="171346"/>while Bloom with obscure tranquil profound motionless compassionated
<lb n="171347"/>gaze regarded the matrimonial gift of Luke and Caroline Doyle.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171348"/>What composite asymmetrical image in the mirror then attracted his
<lb n="171349"/>attention?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171350"/>The image of a solitary (ipsorelative) mutable (aliorelative) man.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171351"/>Why solitary (ipsorelative)?</p>
<quote><lg rend="italics"><lb n="171352"/><l>Brothers and sisters had he none.</l>
<lb n="171353"/><l>Yet that man's father was his grandfather's son.</l></lg></quote>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171354"/>Why mutable (aliorelative)?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171355"/>From infancy to maturity he had resembled his maternal procreatrix. From
<lb n="171356"/>maturity to senility he would increasingly resemble his paternal procreator.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171357"/>What final visual impression was communicated to him by the mirror?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171358"/>The optical reflection of several inverted volumes improperly arranged and
<lb n="171359"/>not in the order of their common letters with scintillating titles on the two
<lb n="171360"/>bookshelves opposite.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171361"/>Catalogue these books.
<lb n="171362"/><title type="book">Thom's Dublin Post Office Directory</title>, 1886.
<lb n="171363"/>Denis Florence M'Carthy's <title type="book">Poetical Works</title> (copper beechleaf bookmark at
<lb n="171364"/>p. 5).
<lb n="171365"/>Shakespeare's <title type="book">Works</title> (dark crimson morocco, goldtooled).
<lb n="171366"/><title type="book">The Useful Ready Reckoner</title> (brown cloth).
<lb n="171367"/><title type="book">The Secret History of the Court of Charles II</title> (red cloth, tooled binding).
<lb n="171368"/><title type="book">The Child's Guide</title> (blue cloth).
<lb n="171369"/><title type="book">The Beauties of Killarney</title> (wrappers).
<lb n="171370"/><title type="book">When We Were Boys</title> by William O'Brien M. P. (green cloth, slightly faded,
<lb n="171371"/>envelope bookmark at p. 217).
<lb n="171372"/><title type="book">Thoughts from Spinoza</title> (maroon leather).
<lb n="171373"/><title type="book">The Story of the Heavens</title> by Sir Robert Ball (blue cloth).
<lb n="171374"/>Ellis's <title type="book">Three Trips to Madagascar</title> (brown cloth, title obliterated).
<lb n="171375"/><title type="book">The Stark-Munro Letters</title> by A. Conan Doyle, property of the <place type="street"><placeName>City of
<lb n="171376"/>Dublin Public Library, <num>106</num> Capel street</placeName></place>, lent 21 May (Whitsun Eve)
<lb n="171377"/>1904, due 4 June 1904, 13 days overdue (black cloth binding, bearing
<lb n="171378"/>white letternumber ticket).
<lb n="171379"/><title type="book">Voyages in China</title> by "Viator" (recovered with brown paper, red ink title).
<lb n="171380"/><title type="book">Philosophy of the Talmud</title> (sewn pamphlet).
<lb n="171381"/>Lockhart's <title type="book">Life of Napoleon</title> (cover wanting, marginal annotations,
<lb n="171382"/>minimising victories, aggrandising defeats of the protagonist).
<lb n="171383"/><title type="book">Soll und Haben</title> by Gustav Freytag (black boards, Gothic characters,
<lb n="171384"/>cigarette coupon bookmark at p. 24).
<lb n="171385"/>Hozier's <title type="book">History of the Russo-Turkish War</title> (brown cloth, 2 volumes, with
<lb n="171386"/>gummed label, Garrison Library, Governor's Parade, Gibraltar, on verso
<lb n="171387"/>of cover).
<lb n="171388"/><title type="book">Laurence Bloomfield in Ireland</title> by William Allingham (second edition,
<lb n="171389"/>green cloth, gilt trefoil design, previous owner's name on recto of flyleaf
<lb n="171390"/>erased).
<lb n="171391"/><title type="book">A Handbook of Astronomy</title> (cover, brown leather, detached, 5 plates,
<lb n="171392"/>antique letterpress long primer, author's footnotes nonpareil, marginal
<lb n="171393"/>clues brevier, captions small pica).
<lb n="171394"/><title type="book">The Hidden Life of Christ</title> (black boards).
<lb n="171395"/><title type="book">In the Track of the Sun</title> (yellow cloth, titlepage missing, recurrent title
<lb n="171396"/>intestation).
<lb n="171397"/><title type="book">Physical Strength and How to Obtain It</title> by Eugen Sandow (red cloth).
<lb n="171398"/><title type="book">Short but yet Plain Elements of Geometry</title> written in French by F. Ignat.
<lb n="171399"/>Pardies and rendered into Engliſh by John Harris D. D. London, printed
<lb n="171400"/>for R. Knaplock at the Biſhop's Head, MDCCXI, with dedicatory epiſtle
<lb n="171401"/>to his worthy friend Charles Cox, eſquire, Member of Parliament for the
<lb n="171402"/>burgh of <place><placeName>Southwark</placeName></place> and having ink calligraphed statement on the flyleaf
<lb n="171403"/>certifying that the book was the property of Michael Gallagher, dated
<lb n="171404"/>this 10th day of May 1822 and requeſting the perſon who should find it, if
<lb n="171405"/>the book should be loſt or go aſtray, to reſtore it to Michael Gallagher,
<lb n="171406"/>carpenter, <place><placeName>Dufery Gate, Enniſcorthy, county Wicklow</placeName></place>, the fineſt place in
<lb n="171407"/>the world.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171408"/>What reflections occupied his mind during the process of reversion of the
<lb n="171409"/>inverted volumes?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171410"/>The necessity of order, a place for everything and everything in its place:
<lb n="171411"/>the deficient appreciation of literature possessed by females: the incongruity
<lb n="171412"/>of an apple incuneated in a tumbler and of an umbrella inclined in a
<lb n="171413"/>closestool: the insecurity of hiding any secret document behind, beneath or
<lb n="171414"/>between the pages of a book.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171415"/>Which volume was the largest in bulk?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171416"/>Hozier's <title type="book">History of the Russo-Turkish War</title>.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171417"/>What among other data did the second volume of the work in question
<lb n="171418"/>contain?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171419"/>The name of a decisive battle (forgotten), frequently remembered by a
<lb n="171420"/>decisive officer, major Brian Cooper Tweedy (remembered).</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171421"/>Why, firstly and secondly, did he not consult the work in question?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171422"/>Firstly, in order to exercise mnemotechnic: secondly, because after an
<lb n="171423"/>interval of amnesia, when, seated at the central table, about to consult the
<lb n="171424"/>work in question, he remembered by mnemotechnic the name of the
<lb n="171425"/>military engagement, Plevna.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171426"/>What caused him consolation in his sitting posture?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171427"/>The candour, nudity, pose, tranquility, youth, grace, sex, counsel of a statue
<lb n="171428"/>erect in the centre of the table, an image of Narcissus purchased by auction
<lb n="171429"/>from P. A. Wren, <place type="street"><placeName><num>9</num> Bachelor's Walk</placeName></place>.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171430"/>What caused him irritation in his sitting posture?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171431"/>Inhibitory pressure of collar (size 17) and waistcoat (5 buttons), two
<lb n="171432"/>articles of clothing superfluous in the costume of mature males and inelastic
<lb n="171433"/>to alterations of mass by expansion.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171434"/>How was the irritation allayed?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171435"/>He removed his collar, with contained black necktie and collapsible stud,
<lb n="171436"/>from his neck to a position on the left of the table. He unbuttoned
<lb n="171437"/>successively in reversed direction waistcoat, trousers, shirt and vest along
<lb n="171438"/>the medial line of irregular incrispated black hairs extending in triangular
<lb n="171439"/>convergence from the pelvic basin over the circumference of the abdomen
<lb n="171440"/>and umbilicular fossicle along the medial line of nodes to the intersection of
<lb n="171441"/>the sixth pectoral vertebrae, thence produced both ways at right angles and
<lb n="171442"/>terminating in circles described about two equidistant points, right and left,
<lb n="171443"/>on the summits of the mammary prominences. He unbraced successively
<lb n="171444"/>each of six minus one braced trouser buttons, arranged in pairs, of which
<lb n="171445"/>one incomplete.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171446"/>What involuntary actions followed?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171447"/>He compressed between 2 fingers the flesh circumjacent to a cicatrice in the
<lb n="171448"/>left infracostal region below the diaphragm resulting from a sting inflicted 2
<lb n="171449"/>weeks and 3 days previously (23 May 1904) by a bee. He scratched
<lb n="171450"/>imprecisely with his right hand, though insensible of prurition, various
<lb n="171451"/>points and surfaces of his partly exposed, wholly abluted skin. He inserted
<lb n="171452"/>his left hand into the left lower pocket of his waistcoat and extracted and
<lb n="171453"/>replaced a silver coin (1 shilling), placed there (presumably) on the occasion
<lb n="171454"/>(17 October 1903) of the interment of Mrs Emily Sinico, Sydney Parade.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171455"/>Compile the budget for 16 June 1904.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171456"/><emph>Debit</emph> <emph>Credit</emph>
<lb n="171457"/>£ - s - d £ - s - d
<lb n="171458"/>1 Pork kidney 0 - 0 - 3 Cash in Hand 0 - 4 - 9
<lb n="171459"/>1 Copy <title type="newspaper">Freeman's Journal</title> 0 - 0 - 1 Commission rec'd... <title type="newspaper">Freeman's Journal</title> 1 - 7 - 6
<lb n="171460"/>1 Bath and Gratification 0 - 1 - 6 Loan (Stephen Dedalus) 1 - 7 - 0
<lb n="171461"/>Tramfare 0 - 0 - 1
<lb n="171462"/>1 In Memoriam Patrick Dignam 0 - 5 - 0
<lb n="171463"/>2 Banbury cakes 0 - 0 - 1
<lb n="171464"/>1 Lunch 0 - 0 - 7
<lb n="171465"/>1 Renewal fee for book 0 - 1 - 0
<lb n="171466"/>1 Packet Notepaper and Envelopes 0 - 0 - 2
<lb n="171467"/>1 Dinner and Gratification 0 - 2 - 0
<lb n="171468"/>1 Postal Order and Stamp 0 - 2 - 8
<lb n="171469"/>Tramfare 0 - 0 - 1
<lb n="171470"/>1 Pig's Foot 0 - 0 - 4
<lb n="171471"/>1 Sheep's Trotter 0 - 0 - 3
<lb n="171472"/>1 Cake Fry's Plain Chocolate 0 - 1 - 0
<lb n="171473"/>1 Square Soda Bread 0 - 0 - 4
<lb n="171474"/>1 Coffee and Bun 0 - 0 - 4
<lb n="171475"/>Loan (Stephen Dedalus) refunded 1 - 7 - 0
<lb n="171476"/>Balance 0 - 16 - 6
<lb n="171477"/>                     
<lb n="171478"/>£ 2 - 19 - 3 £ 2 - 19 - 3</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171479"/>Did the process of divestiture continue?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171480"/>Sensible of a benignant persistent ache in his footsoles he extended his foot
<lb n="171481"/>to one side and observed the creases, protuberances and salient points
<lb n="171482"/>caused by foot pressure in the course of walking repeatedly in several
<lb n="171483"/>different directions, then, inclined, he disnoded the laceknots, unhooked
<lb n="171484"/>and loosened the laces, took off each of his two boots for the second time,
<lb n="171485"/>detached the partially moistened right sock through the fore part of which
<lb n="171486"/>the nail of his great toe had again effracted, raised his right foot and, having
<lb n="171487"/>unhooked a purple elastic sock suspender, took off his right sock, placed his
<lb n="171488"/>unclothed right foot on the margin of the seat of his chair, picked at and
<lb n="171489"/>gently lacerated the protruding part of the great toenail, raised the part
<lb n="171490"/>lacerated to his nostrils and inhaled the odour of the quick, then, with
<lb n="171491"/>satisfaction, threw away the lacerated ungual fragment.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171492"/>Why with satisfaction?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171493"/>Because the odour inhaled corresponded to other odours inhaled of other
<lb n="171494"/>ungual fragments, picked and lacerated by Master Bloom, pupil of Mrs
<lb n="171495"/>Ellis's juvenile school, patiently each night in the act of brief genuflection
<lb n="171496"/>and nocturnal prayer and ambitious meditation.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171497"/>In what ultimate ambition had all concurrent and consecutive ambitions
<lb n="171498"/>now coalesced?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171499"/>Not to inherit by right of primogeniture, gavelkind or borough English, or
<lb n="171500"/>possess in perpetuity an extensive demesne of a sufficient number of acres,
<lb n="171501"/>roods and perches, statute land measure (valuation £42), of grazing turbary
<lb n="171502"/>surrounding a baronial hall with gatelodge and carriage drive nor, on the
<lb n="171503"/>other hand, a terracehouse or semidetached villa, described as <foreign xml:lang="la">Rus in Urbe</foreign>
<lb n="171504"/>or <foreign xml:lang="it">Qui si sana</foreign>, but to purchase by private treaty in fee simple a thatched
<lb n="171505"/>bungalowshaped 2 storey dwellinghouse of southerly aspect, surmounted
<lb n="171506"/>by vane and lightning conductor, connected with the earth, with porch
<lb n="171507"/>covered by parasitic plants (ivy or Virginia creeper), halldoor, olive green,
<lb n="171508"/>with smart carriage finish and neat doorbrasses, stucco front with gilt
<lb n="171509"/>tracery at eaves and gable, rising, if possible, upon a gentle eminence with
<lb n="171510"/>agreeable prospect from balcony with stone pillar parapet over unoccupied
<lb n="171511"/>and unoccupyable interjacent pastures and standing in 5 or 6 acres of its
<lb n="171512"/>own ground, at such a distance from the nearest public thoroughfare as to
<lb n="171513"/>render its houselights visible at night above and through a quickset
<lb n="171514"/>hornbeam hedge of topiary cutting, situate at a given point not less than 1
<lb n="171515"/>statute mile from the periphery of the metropolis, within a time limit of not
<lb n="171516"/>more than 15 minutes from tram or train line (e.g., <place><placeName>Dundrum</placeName></place>, south, or
<lb n="171517"/><place><placeName>Sutton</placeName></place>, north, both localities equally reported by trial to resemble the
<lb n="171518"/>terrestrial poles in being favourable climates for phthisical subjects), the
<lb n="171519"/>premises to be held under feefarm grant, lease 999 years, the messuage to
<lb n="171520"/>consist of 1 drawingroom with baywindow (2 lancets), thermometer
<lb n="171521"/>affixed, 1 sittingroom, 4 bedrooms, 2 servants' rooms, tiled kitchen with
<lb n="171522"/>close range and scullery, lounge hall fitted with linen wallpresses, fumed
<lb n="171523"/>oak sectional bookcase containing the <title type="book">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title> and <title type="book">New
<lb n="171524"/>Century Dictionary</title>, transverse obsolete medieval and oriental weapons,
<lb n="171525"/>dinner gong, alabaster lamp, bowl pendant, vulcanite automatic telephone
<lb n="171526"/>receiver with adjacent directory, handtufted Axminster carpet with cream
<lb n="171527"/>ground and trellis border, loo table with pillar and claw legs, hearth with
<lb n="171528"/>massive firebrasses and ormolu mantel chronometer clock, guaranteed
<lb n="171529"/>timekeeper with cathedral chime, barometer with hygrographic chart,
<lb n="171530"/>comfortable lounge settees and corner fitments, upholstered in ruby plush
<lb n="171531"/>with good springing and sunk centre, three banner Japanese screen and
<lb n="171532"/>cuspidors (club style, rich winecoloured leather, gloss renewable with a
<lb n="171533"/>minimum of labour by use of linseed oil and vinegar) and pyramidically
<lb n="171534"/>prismatic central chandelier lustre, bentwood perch with fingertame parrot
<lb n="171535"/>(expurgated language), embossed mural paper at 10/- per dozen with
<lb n="171536"/>transverse swags of carmine floral design and top crown frieze, staircase,
<lb n="171537"/>three continuous flights at successive right angles, of varnished cleargrained
<lb n="171538"/>oak, treads and risers, newel, balusters and handrail, with steppedup panel
<lb n="171539"/>dado, dressed with camphorated wax: bathroom, hot and cold supply,
<lb n="171540"/>reclining and shower: water closet on mezzanine provided with opaque
<lb n="171541"/>singlepane oblong window, tipup seat, bracket lamp, brass tierod and brace,
<lb n="171542"/>armrests, footstool and artistic oleograph on inner face of door: ditto,
<lb n="171543"/>plain: servants' apartments with separate sanitary and hygienic necessaries
<lb n="171544"/>for cook, general and betweenmaid (salary, rising by biennial unearned
<lb n="171545"/>increments of £2, with comprehensive fidelity insurance, annual bonus (£1)
<lb n="171546"/>and retiring allowance (based on the 65 system) after 30 years' service),
<lb n="171547"/>pantry, buttery, larder, refrigerator, outoffices, coal and wood cellarage
<lb n="171548"/>with winebin (still and sparkling vintages) for distinguished guests, if
<lb n="171549"/>entertained to dinner (evening dress), carbon monoxide gas supply
<lb n="171550"/>throughout.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171551"/>What additional attractions might the grounds contain?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171552"/>As addenda, a tennis and fives court, a shrubbery, a glass summerhouse
<lb n="171553"/>with tropical palms, equipped in the best botanical manner, a rockery with
<lb n="171554"/>waterspray, a beehive arranged on humane principles, oval flowerbeds in
<lb n="171555"/>rectangular grassplots set with eccentric ellipses of scarlet and chrome
<lb n="171556"/>tulips, blue scillas, crocuses, polyanthus, sweet William, sweet pea, lily of
<lb n="171557"/>the valley (bulbs obtainable from sir James W. Mackey (Limited) wholesale
<lb n="171558"/>and retail seed and bulb merchants and nurserymen, agents for chemical
<lb n="171559"/>manures, <place type="street"><placeName><num>23</num> Sackville street, upper</placeName></place>), an orchard, kitchen garden and vinery,
<lb n="171560"/>protected against illegal trespassers by glasstopped mural enclosures, a
<lb n="171561"/>lumbershed with padlock for various inventoried implements.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171562"/>As?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171563"/>Eeltraps, lobsterpots, fishingrods, hatchet, steelyard, grindstone,
<lb n="171564"/>clodcrusher, swatheturner, carriagesack, telescope ladder, 10 tooth rake,
<lb n="171565"/>washing clogs, haytedder, tumbling rake, billhook, paintpot, brush, hoe and
<lb n="171566"/>so on.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171567"/>What improvements might be subsequently introduced?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171568"/>A rabbitry and fowlrun, a dovecote, a botanical conservatory, 2 hammocks
<lb n="171569"/>(lady's and gentleman's), a sundial shaded and sheltered by laburnum or
<lb n="171570"/>lilac trees, an exotically harmonically accorded Japanese tinkle gatebell
<lb n="171571"/>affixed to left lateral gatepost, a capacious waterbutt, a lawnmower with
<lb n="171572"/>side delivery and grassbox, a lawnsprinkler with hydraulic hose.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171573"/>What facilities of transit were desirable?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171574"/>When citybound frequent connection by train or tram from their respective
<lb n="171575"/>intermediate station or terminal. When countrybound velocipedes, a
<lb n="171576"/>chainless freewheel roadster cycle with side basketcar attached, or draught
<lb n="171577"/>conveyance, a donkey with wicker trap or smart phaeton with good
<lb n="171578"/>working solidungular cob (roan gelding, 14 h).</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171579"/>What might be the name of this erigible or erected residence?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171580"/>Bloom Cottage. Saint Leopold's. Flowerville.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171581"/>Could Bloom of <place><placeName><num>7</num> Eccles street</placeName></place> foresee Bloom of Flowerville?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171582"/>In loose allwool garments with Harris tweed cap, price 8/6, and useful
<lb n="171583"/>garden boots with elastic gussets and wateringcan, planting aligned young
<lb n="171584"/>firtrees, syringing, pruning, staking, sowing hayseed, trundling a weedladen
<lb n="171585"/>wheelbarrow without excessive fatigue at sunset amid the scent of
<lb n="171586"/>newmown hay, ameliorating the soil, multiplying wisdom, achieving
<lb n="171587"/>longevity.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171588"/>What syllabus of intellectual pursuits was simultaneously possible?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171589"/>Snapshot photography, comparative study of religions, folklore relative to
<lb n="171590"/>various amatory and superstitious practices, contemplation of the celestial
<lb n="171591"/>constellations.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171592"/>What lighter recreations?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171593"/>Outdoor: garden and fieldwork, cycling on level macadamised causeways,
<lb n="171594"/>ascents of moderately high hills, natation in secluded fresh water and
<lb n="171595"/>unmolested river boating in secure wherry or light curricle with kedge
<lb n="171596"/>anchor on reaches free from weirs and rapids (period of estivation),
<lb n="171597"/>vespertinal perambulation or equestrian circumprocession with inspection
<lb n="171598"/>of sterile landscape and contrastingly agreeable cottagers' fires of smoking
<lb n="171599"/>peat turves (period of hibernation). Indoor: discussion in tepid security of
<lb n="171600"/>unsolved historical and criminal problems: lecture of unexpurgated exotic
<lb n="171601"/>erotic masterpieces: house carpentry with toolbox containing hammer, awl,
<lb n="171602"/>nails, screws, tintacks, gimlet, tweezers, bullnose plane and turnscrew.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171603"/>Might he become a gentleman farmer of field produce and live stock?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171604"/>Not impossibly, with 1 or 2 stripper cows, 1 pike of upland hay and
<lb n="171605"/>requisite farming implements, e.g., an end-to-end churn, a turnip pulper etc.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171606"/>What would be his civic functions and social status among the county
<lb n="171607"/>families and landed gentry?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171608"/>Arranged successively in ascending powers of hierarchical order, that of
<lb n="171609"/>gardener, groundsman, cultivator, breeder, and at the zenith of his career,
<lb n="171610"/>resident magistrate or justice of the peace with a family crest and coat of
<lb n="171611"/>arms and appropriate classical motto (<foreign xml:lang="la">Semper paratus</foreign>), duly recorded in
<lb n="171612"/>the court directory (Bloom, Leopold P., M. P., P. C., K. P., L. L. D.
<lb n="171613"/>(<foreign xml:lang="la">honoris causa</foreign>), Bloomville, <place><placeName>Dundrum</placeName></place>) and mentioned in court and
<lb n="171614"/>fashionable intelligence (Mr and Mrs Leopold Bloom have left <place><placeName>Kingstown</placeName></place>
<lb n="171615"/>for <place><placeName>England</placeName></place>).</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171616"/>What course of action did he outline for himself in such capacity?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171617"/>A course that lay between undue clemency and excessive rigour: the
<lb n="171618"/>dispensation in a heterogeneous society of arbitrary classes, incessantly
<lb n="171619"/>rearranged in terms of greater and lesser social inequality, of unbiassed
<lb n="171620"/>homogeneous indisputable justice, tempered with mitigants of the widest
<lb n="171621"/>possible latitude but exactable to the uttermost farthing with confiscation of
<lb n="171622"/>estate, real and personal, to the crown. Loyal to the highest constituted
<lb n="171623"/>power in the land, actuated by an innate love of rectitude his aims would be
<lb n="171624"/>the strict maintenance of public order, the repression of many abuses
<lb n="171625"/>though not of all simultaneously (every measure of reform or retrenchment
<lb n="171626"/>being a preliminary solution to be contained by fluxion in the final
<lb n="171627"/>solution), the upholding of the letter of the law (common, statute and law
<lb n="171628"/>merchant) against all traversers in covin and trespassers acting in
<lb n="171629"/>contravention of bylaws and regulations, all resuscitators (by trespass and
<lb n="171630"/>petty larceny of kindlings) of venville rights, obsolete by desuetude, all
<lb n="171631"/>orotund instigators of international persecution, all perpetuators of
<lb n="171632"/>international animosities, all menial molestors of domestic conviviality, all
<lb n="171633"/>recalcitrant violators of domestic connubiality.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171634"/>Prove that he had loved rectitude from his earliest youth.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171635"/>To Master Percy Apjohn at High School in 1880 he had divulged his
<lb n="171636"/>disbelief in the tenets of the Irish (protestant) church (to which his father
<lb n="171637"/>Rudolf Virag (later Rudolph Bloom) had been converted from the Israelitic
<lb n="171638"/>faith and communion in 1865 by the Society for promoting Christianity
<lb n="171639"/>among the jews) subsequently abjured by him in favour of Roman
<lb n="171640"/>catholicism at the epoch of and with a view to his matrimony in 1888. To
<lb n="171641"/>Daniel Magrane and Francis Wade in 1882 during a juvenile friendship
<lb n="171642"/>(terminated by the premature emigration of the former) he had advocated
<lb n="171643"/>during nocturnal perambulations the political theory of colonial (e.g.
<lb n="171644"/>Canadian) expansion and the evolutionary theories of Charles Darwin,
<lb n="171645"/>expounded in <title type="book">The Descent of Man</title> and <title type="book">The Origin of Species</title>. In 1885 he
<lb n="171646"/>had publicly expressed his adherence to the collective and national
<lb n="171647"/>economic programme advocated by James Fintan Lalor, John Fisher
<lb n="171648"/>Murray, John Mitchel, J. F. X. O'Brien and others, the agrarian policy of
<lb n="171649"/>Michael Davitt, the constitutional agitation of Charles Stewart Parnell
<lb n="171650"/>(M. P. for <place><placeName>Cork City</placeName></place>), the programme of peace, retrenchment and reform
<lb n="171651"/>of William Ewart Gladstone (M. P. for Midlothian, N. B.) and, in support
<lb n="171652"/>of his political convictions, had climbed up into a secure position amid the
<lb n="171653"/>ramifications of a tree on <place><placeName>Northumberland road</placeName></place> to see the entrance
<lb n="171654"/>(2 February 1888) into the capital of a demonstrative torchlight procession
<lb n="171655"/>of 20,000 torchbearers, divided into 120 trade corporations, bearing 2000
<lb n="171656"/>torches in escort of the marquess of Ripon and (honest) John Morley.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171657"/>How much and how did he propose to pay for this country residence?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171658"/>As per prospectus of the Industrious Foreign Acclimatised Nationalised
<lb n="171659"/>Friendly Stateaided Building Society (incorporated 1874), a maximum of
<lb n="171660"/>£60 per annum, being ⅙ of an assured income, derived from giltedged
<lb n="171661"/>securities, representing at 5% simple interest on capital of £1200 (estimate
<lb n="171662"/>of price at 20 years' purchase), of which ⅓ to be paid on acquisition and the
<lb n="171663"/>balance in the form of annual rent, viz. £800 plus 2½% interest on the same,
<lb n="171664"/>repayable quarterly in equal annual instalments until extinction by
<lb n="171665"/>amortisation of loan advanced for purchase within a period of 20 years,
<lb n="171666"/>amounting to an annual rental of £64, headrent included, the titledeeds to
<lb n="171667"/>remain in possession of the lender or lenders with a saving clause
<lb n="171668"/>envisaging forced sale, foreclosure and mutual compensation in the event of
<lb n="171669"/>protracted failure to pay the terms assigned, otherwise the messuage to
<lb n="171670"/>become the absolute property of the tenant occupier upon expiry of the
<lb n="171671"/>period of years stipulated.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171672"/>What rapid but insecure means to opulence might facilitate immediate
<lb n="171673"/>purchase?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171674"/>A private wireless telegraph which would transmit by dot and dash system
<lb n="171675"/>the result of a national equine handicap (flat or steeplechase) of 1 or more
<lb n="171676"/>miles and furlongs won by an outsider at odds of 50 to 1 at
<lb n="171677"/>3 hr 8 m p.m. at Ascot (Greenwich time), the message being received and
<lb n="171678"/>available for betting purposes in Dublin at 2.59 p.m. (Dunsink time). The
<lb n="171679"/>unexpected discovery of an object of great monetary value (precious stone,
<lb n="171680"/>valuable adhesive or impressed postage stamps (7 schilling, mauve,
<lb n="171681"/>imperforate, <place type="city"><placeName>Hamburg</placeName></place>, 1866: 4 pence, rose, blue paper, perforate, <place><placeName>Great
<lb n="171682"/>Britain</placeName></place>, 1855: 1 franc, stone, official, rouletted, diagonal surcharge,
<lb n="171683"/><place type="city"><placeName>Luxemburg</placeName></place>, 1878), antique dynastical ring, unique relic) in unusual
<lb n="171684"/>repositories or by unusual means: from the air (dropped by an eagle in
<lb n="171685"/>flight), by fire (amid the carbonised remains of an incendiated edifice), in
<lb n="171686"/>the sea (amid flotsam, jetsam, lagan and derelict), on earth (in the gizzard
<lb n="171687"/>of a comestible fowl). A Spanish prisoner's donation of a distant treasure of
<lb n="171688"/>valuables or specie or bullion lodged with a solvent banking corporation
<lb n="171689"/>100 years previously at 5% compound interest of the collective worth of
<lb n="171690"/>£5,000,000 stg (five million pounds sterling). A contract with an
<lb n="171691"/>inconsiderate contractee for the delivery of 32 consignments of some given
<lb n="171692"/>commodity in consideration of cash payment on delivery per delivery at the
<lb n="171693"/>initial rate of ¼d to be increased constantly in the geometrical progression
<lb n="171694"/>of 2 (¼d, ½d, 1d, 2d, 4d, 8d, 1s 4d, 2s 8d to 32 terms). A prepared scheme
<lb n="171695"/>based on a study of the laws of probability to break the bank at Monte
<lb n="171696"/>Carlo. A solution of the secular problem of the quadrature of the circle,
<lb n="171697"/>government premium £1,000,000 sterling.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171698"/>Was vast wealth acquirable through industrial channels?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171699"/>The reclamation of dunams of waste arenary soil, proposed in the
<lb n="171700"/>prospectus of Agendath Netaim, Bleibtreustrasse, Berlin, W. 15, by the
<lb n="171701"/>cultivation of orange plantations and melonfields and reafforestation. The
<lb n="171702"/>utilisation of waste paper, fells of sewer rodents, human excrement
<lb n="171703"/>possessing chemical properties, in view of the vast production of the first,
<lb n="171704"/>vast number of the second and immense quantity of the third, every normal
<lb n="171705"/>human being of average vitality and appetite producing annually, cancelling
<lb n="171706"/>byproducts of water, a sum total of 80 lbs. (mixed animal and vegetable
<lb n="171707"/>diet), to be multiplied by 4,386,035, the total population of <place><placeName>Ireland</placeName></place>
<lb n="171708"/>according to census returns of 1901.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171709"/>Were there schemes of wider scope?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171710"/>A scheme to be formulated and submitted for approval to the harbour
<lb n="171711"/>commissioners for the exploitation of white coal (hydraulic power),
<lb n="171712"/>obtained by hydroelectric plant at peak of tide at <place><placeName>Dublin bar</placeName></place> or at head of
<lb n="171713"/>water at <place><placeName>Poulaphouca</placeName></place> or <place><placeName>Powerscourt</placeName></place> or catchment basins of main streams
<lb n="171714"/>for the economic production of 500,000 W. H. P. of electricity. A scheme
<lb n="171715"/>to enclose the peninsular delta of the North Bull at <place><placeName>Dollymount</placeName></place> and erect
<lb n="171716"/>on the space of the foreland, used for golf links and rifle ranges, an
<lb n="171717"/>asphalted esplanade with casinos, booths, shooting galleries, hotels,
<lb n="171718"/>boardinghouses, readingrooms, establishments for mixed bathing. A
<lb n="171719"/>scheme for the use of dogvans and goatvans for the delivery of early
<lb n="171720"/>morning milk. A scheme for the development of Irish tourist traffic in and
<lb n="171721"/>around Dublin by means of petrolpropelled riverboats, plying in the fluvial
<lb n="171722"/>fairway between <place><placeName>Island bridge</placeName></place> and <place><placeName>Ringsend</placeName></place>, charabancs, narrow gauge
<lb n="171723"/>local railways, and pleasure steamers for coastwise navigation (10/- per
<lb n="171724"/>person per day, guide (trilingual) included). A scheme for the repristination
<lb n="171725"/>of passenger and goods traffics over Irish waterways, when freed from
<lb n="171726"/>weedbeds. A scheme to connect by tramline the <place><placeName>Cattle Market (North
<lb n="171727"/>Circular road and Prussia street)</placeName></place> with the <place><placeName>quays (Sheriff street, lower, and
<lb n="171728"/>East Wall)</placeName></place>, parallel with the Link line railway laid (in conjunction with the
<lb n="171729"/>Great Southern and Western railway line) between the cattle park, Liffey
<lb n="171730"/>junction, and terminus of Midland Great Western Railway <place type="street"><placeName><num>43 to 45</num> North
<lb n="171731"/>Wall</placeName></place>, in proximity to the terminal stations or Dublin branches of Great
<lb n="171732"/>Central Railway, Midland Railway of England, City of Dublin Steam
<lb n="171733"/>Packet Company, Lancashire and Yorkshire Railway Company, Dublin
<lb n="171734"/>and Glasgow Steam Packet Company, Glasgow, Dublin and Londonderry
<lb n="171735"/>Steam Packet Company (Laird line), British and Irish Steam Packet
<lb n="171736"/>Company, Dublin and Morecambe Steamers, London and North Western
<lb n="171737"/>Railway Company, Dublin Port and Docks Board Landing Sheds and
<lb n="171738"/>transit sheds of Palgrave, Murphy and Company, steamship owners, agents
<lb n="171739"/>for steamers from Mediterranean, Spain, Portugal, France, Belgium and
<lb n="171740"/>Holland and for Liverpool Underwriters' Association, the cost of acquired
<lb n="171741"/>rolling stock for animal transport and of additional mileage operated by the
<lb n="171742"/>Dublin United Tramways Company, limited, to be covered by graziers'
<lb n="171743"/>fees.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171744"/>Positing what protasis would the contraction for such several schemes
<lb n="171745"/>become a natural and necessary apodosis?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171746"/>Given a guarantee equal to the sum sought, the support, by deed of gift and
<lb n="171747"/>transfer vouchers during donor's lifetime or by bequest after donor's
<lb n="171748"/>painless extinction, of eminent financiers (Blum Pasha, Rothschild,
<lb n="171749"/>Guggenheim, Hirsch, Montefiore, Morgan, Rockefeller) possessing
<lb n="171750"/>fortunes in 6 figures, amassed during a successful life, and joining capital
<lb n="171751"/>with opportunity the thing required was done.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171752"/>What eventuality would render him independent of such wealth?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171753"/>The independent discovery of a goldseam of inexhaustible ore.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171754"/>For what reason did he meditate on schemes so difficult of realisation?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171755"/>It was one of his axioms that similar meditations or the automatic relation
<lb n="171756"/>to himself of a narrative concerning himself or tranquil recollection of the
<lb n="171757"/>past when practised habitually before retiring for the night alleviated
<lb n="171758"/>fatigue and produced as a result sound repose and renovated vitality.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171759"/>His justifications?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171760"/>As a physicist he had learned that of the 70 years of complete human life at
<lb n="171761"/>least 2/₇, viz. 20 years are passed in sleep. As a philosopher he knew that at
<lb n="171762"/>the termination of any allotted life only an infinitesimal part of any person's
<lb n="171763"/>desires has been realised. As a physiologist he believed in the artificial
<lb n="171764"/>placation of malignant agencies chiefly operative during somnolence.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171765"/>What did he fear?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171766"/>The committal of homicide or suicide during sleep by an aberration of the
<lb n="171767"/>light of reason, the incommensurable categorical intelligence situated in the
<lb n="171768"/>cerebral convolutions.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171769"/>What were habitually his final meditations?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171770"/>Of some one sole unique advertisement to cause passers to stop in wonder,
<lb n="171771"/>a poster novelty, with all extraneous accretions excluded, reduced to its
<lb n="171772"/>simplest and most efficient terms not exceeding the span of casual vision and
<lb n="171773"/>congruous with the velocity of modern life.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171774"/>What did the first drawer unlocked contain?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171775"/>A Vere Foster's handwriting copybook, property of Milly (Millicent)
<lb n="171776"/>Bloom, certain pages of which bore diagram drawings, marked <foreign xml:lang="hu">Papli</foreign>,
<lb n="171777"/>which showed a large globular head with 5 hairs erect, 2 eyes in profile, the
<lb n="171778"/>trunk full front with 3 large buttons, 1 triangular foot: 2 fading
<lb n="171779"/>photographs of queen Alexandra of England and of Maud Branscombe,
<lb n="171780"/>actress and professional beauty: a Yuletide card, bearing on it a pictorial
<lb n="171781"/>representation of a parasitic plant, the legend <foreign xml:lang="he">Mizpah</foreign>, the date Xmas 1892,
<lb n="171782"/>the name of the senders: from Mr + Mrs M. Comerford, the versicle: <emph>May
<lb n="171783"/>this Yuletide bring to thee, Joy and peace and welcome glee</emph>: a butt of
<lb n="171784"/>red partly liquefied sealing wax, obtained from the stores department of
<lb n="171785"/>Messrs Hely's, Ltd., <place type="street"><placeName>89, 90, and 91 Dame street</placeName></place>: a box containing the
<lb n="171786"/>remainder of a gross of gilt "J" pennibs, obtained from same department of
<lb n="171787"/>same firm: an old sandglass which rolled containing sand which rolled: a
<lb n="171788"/>sealed prophecy (never unsealed) written by Leopold Bloom in 1886
<lb n="171789"/>concerning the consequences of the passing into law of William Ewart
<lb n="171790"/>Gladstone's Home Rule bill of 1886 (never passed into law): a bazaar
<lb n="171791"/>ticket, no 2004, of S. Kevin's Charity Fair, price 6d, 100 prizes: an infantile
<lb n="171792"/>epistle, dated, small em monday, reading: capital pee Papli comma capital
<lb n="171793"/>aitch How are you note of interrogation capital eye I am very well full stop
<lb n="171794"/>new paragraph signature with flourishes capital em Milly no stop: a cameo
<lb n="171795"/>brooch, property of Ellen Bloom (born Higgins), deceased: a cameo
<lb n="171796"/>scarfpin, property of Rudolph Bloom (born Virag), deceased: 3 typewritten
<lb n="171797"/>letters, addressee, Henry Flower, ℅. P. O. Westland Row, addresser,
<lb n="171798"/>Martha Clifford, ℅. P. O. Dolphin's Barn: the transliterated name and
<lb n="171799"/>address of the addresser of the 3 letters in reversed alphabetic
<lb n="171800"/>boustrophedonic punctated quadrilinear cryptogram (vowels suppressed)
<lb n="171801"/>N. IGS./WI. UU. OX/W. OKS. MH/Y. IM: a press cutting from an
<lb n="171802"/>English weekly periodical <title type="newspaper">Modern Society</title>, subject corporal chastisement in
<lb n="171803"/>girls' schools: a pink ribbon which had festooned an Easter egg in the year
<lb n="171804"/>1899: two partly uncoiled rubber preservatives with reserve pockets,
<lb n="171805"/>purchased by post from <place type="street"><placeName>Box 32, P. O., Charing Cross, London, W. C.</placeName></place>:
<lb n="171806"/>1 pack of 1 dozen creamlaid envelopes and feintruled notepaper,
<lb n="171807"/>watermarked, now reduced by 3: some assorted Austrian-Hungarian coins:
<lb n="171808"/>2 coupons of the Royal and Privileged Hungarian Lottery: a lowpower
<lb n="171809"/>magnifying glass: 2 erotic photocards showing a) buccal coition between
<lb n="171810"/>nude señorita (rere presentation, superior position) and nude torero (fore
<lb n="171811"/>presentation, inferior position) b) anal violation by male religious (fully
<lb n="171812"/>clothed, eyes abject) of female religious (partly clothed, eyes direct),
<lb n="171813"/>purchased by post from <place type="street"><placeName>Box 32, P. O., Charing Cross, London, W. C.</placeName></place>: a
<lb n="171814"/>press cutting of recipe for renovation of old tan boots: a 1d adhesive stamp,
<lb n="171815"/>lavender, of the reign of Queen Victoria: a chart of the measurements of
<lb n="171816"/>Leopold Bloom compiled before, during and after 2 months' consecutive use
<lb n="171817"/>of Sandow-Whiteley's pulley exerciser (men's 15/-, athlete's 20/-) viz. chest
<lb n="171818"/>28 in and 29½ in, biceps 9 in and 10 in, forearm 8½ in and 9 in, thigh 10 in
<lb n="171819"/>and 12 in, calf 11 in and 12 in: 1 prospectus of The Wonderworker, the
<lb n="171820"/>world's greatest remedy for rectal complaints, direct from Wonderworker,
<lb n="171821"/><place><placeName>Coventry House, South Place, London E C</placeName></place>, addressed (erroneously) to
<lb n="171822"/>Mrs L. Bloom with brief accompanying note commencing (erroneously):
<lb n="171823"/>Dear Madam.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171824"/>Quote the textual terms in which the prospectus claimed advantages for this
<lb n="171825"/>thaumaturgic remedy.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171826"/>It heals and soothes while you sleep, in case of trouble in breaking wind,
<lb n="171827"/>assists nature in the most formidable way, insuring instant relief in
<lb n="171828"/>discharge of gases, keeping parts clean and free natural action, an initial
<lb n="171829"/>outlay of 7/6 making a new man of you and life worth living. Ladies find
<lb n="171830"/>Wonderworker especially useful, a pleasant surprise when they note
<lb n="171831"/>delightful result like a cool drink of fresh spring water on a sultry summer's
<lb n="171832"/>day. Recommend it to your lady and gentlemen friends, lasts a lifetime.
<lb n="171833"/>Insert long round end. Wonderworker.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171834"/>Were there testimonials?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171835"/>Numerous. From clergyman, British naval officer, wellknown author, city
<lb n="171836"/>man, hospital nurse, lady, mother of five, absentminded beggar.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171837"/>How did absentminded beggar's concluding testimonial conclude?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171838"/>What a pity the government did not supply our men with wonderworkers
<lb n="171839"/>during the South African campaign! What a relief it would have been!</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171840"/>What object did Bloom add to this collection of objects?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171841"/>A 4th typewritten letter received by Henry Flower (let H. F. be L. B.) from
<lb n="171842"/>Martha Clifford (find M. C.).</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171843"/>What pleasant reflection accompanied this action?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171844"/>The reflection that, apart from the letter in question, his magnetic face, form
<lb n="171845"/>and address had been favourably received during the course of the
<lb n="171846"/>preceding day by a wife (Mrs Josephine Breen, born Josie Powell), a nurse,
<lb n="171847"/>Miss Callan (Christian name unknown), a maid, Gertrude (Gerty, family
<lb n="171848"/>name unknown).</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171849"/>What possibility suggested itself?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171850"/>The possibility of exercising virile power of fascination in the not immediate
<lb n="171851"/>future after an expensive repast in a private apartment in the company of an
<lb n="171852"/>elegant courtesan, of corporal beauty, moderately mercenary, variously
<lb n="171853"/>instructed, a lady by origin.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171854"/>What did the 2nd drawer contain?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171855"/>Documents: the birth certificate of Leopold Paula Bloom: an endowment
<lb n="171856"/>assurance policy of £500 in the Scottish Widows' Assurance Society,
<lb n="171857"/>intestated Millicent (Milly) Bloom, coming into force at 25 years as with
<lb n="171858"/>profit policy of £430, £462-10-0 and £500 at 60 years or death, 65 years or
<lb n="171859"/>death and death, respectively, or with profit policy (paidup) of £299-10-0
<lb n="171860"/>together with cash payment of £133-10-0, at option: a bank passbook
<lb n="171861"/>issued by the Ulster Bank, College Green branch showing statement of
<lb n="171862"/>a/c for halfyear ending 31 December 1903, balance in depositor's favour:
<lb n="171863"/>£18-14-6 (eighteen pounds, fourteen shillings and sixpence, sterling), net
<lb n="171864"/>personalty: certificate of possession of £900, Canadian 4% (inscribed)
<lb n="171865"/>government stock (free of stamp duty): dockets of the Catholic Cemeteries'
<lb n="171866"/>(Glasnevin) Committee, relative to a graveplot purchased: a local press
<lb n="171867"/>cutting concerning change of name by deedpoll.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171868"/>Quote the textual terms of this notice.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171869"/>I, Rudolph Virag, now resident at <place type="street"><placeName><num>no 52</num> Clanbrassil street, Dublin</placeName></place>,
<lb n="171870"/>formerly of <place><placeName>Szombathely in the kingdom of Hungary</placeName></place>, hereby give notice
<lb n="171871"/>that I have assumed and intend henceforth upon all occasions and at all
<lb n="171872"/>times to be known by the name of Rudolph Bloom.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171873"/>What other objects relative to Rudolph Bloom (born Virag) were in the 2nd
<lb n="171874"/>drawer?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171875"/>An indistinct daguerreotype of Rudolf Virag and his father Leopold Virag
<lb n="171876"/>executed in the year 1852 in the portrait atelier of their (respectively) 1st
<lb n="171877"/>and 2nd cousin, Stefan Virag of <place type="city"><placeName>Szesfehervar, Hungary</placeName></place>. An ancient
<lb n="171878"/>haggadah book in which a pair of hornrimmed convex spectacles inserted
<lb n="171879"/>marked the passage of thanksgiving in the ritual prayers for Pessach
<lb n="171880"/>(Passover): a photocard of the Queen's Hotel, Ennis, proprietor, Rudolph
<lb n="171881"/>Bloom: an envelope addressed: <emph>To My Dear Son Leopold</emph>.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171882"/>What fractions of phrases did the lecture of those five whole words evoke?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171883"/>Tomorrow will be a week that I received .... it is no use Leopold to be ....
<lb n="171884"/>with your dear mother ... that is not more to stand ... to her ... all for me is
<lb n="171885"/>out ... be kind to Athos, Leopold .... my dear son ... always ... of me ... <foreign xml:lang="de">das
<lb n="171886"/>Herz ... Gott ... dein</foreign> ...</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171887"/>What reminiscences of a human subject suffering from progressive
<lb n="171888"/>melancholia did these objects evoke in Bloom?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171889"/>An old man, widower, unkempt of hair, in bed, with head covered, sighing:
<lb n="171890"/>an infirm dog, Athos: aconite, resorted to by increasing doses of grains and
<lb n="171891"/>scruples as a palliative of recrudescent neuralgia: the face in death of a
<lb n="171892"/>septuagenarian, suicide by poison.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171893"/>Why did Bloom experience a sentiment of remorse?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171894"/>Because in immature impatience he had treated with disrespect certain
<lb n="171895"/>beliefs and practices.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171896"/>As?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171897"/>The prohibition of the use of fleshmeat and milk at one meal: the
<lb n="171898"/>hebdomadary symposium of incoordinately abstract, perfervidly concrete
<lb n="171899"/>mercantile coexreligionist excompatriots: the circumcision of male infants:
<lb n="171900"/>the supernatural character of Judaic scripture: the ineffability of the
<lb n="171901"/>tetragrammaton: the sanctity of the sabbath.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171902"/>How did these beliefs and practices now appear to him?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171903"/>Not more rational than they had then appeared, not less rational than other
<lb n="171904"/>beliefs and practices now appeared.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171905"/>What first reminiscence had he of Rudolph Bloom (deceased)?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171906"/>Rudolph Bloom (deceased) narrated to his son Leopold Bloom (aged 6) a
<lb n="171907"/>retrospective arrangement of migrations and settlements in and between
<lb n="171908"/><place type="city"><placeName>Dublin</placeName></place>, <place type="city"><placeName>London</placeName></place>, <place type="city"><placeName>Florence</placeName></place>, <place type="city"><placeName>Milan</placeName></place>, <place type="city"><placeName>Vienna</placeName></place>, <place type="city"><placeName>Budapest</placeName></place>, <place type="city"><placeName>Szombathely</placeName></place> with
<lb n="171909"/>statements of satisfaction (his grandfather having seen Maria Theresia,
<lb n="171910"/>empress of <place><placeName>Austria</placeName></place>, queen of <place><placeName>Hungary</placeName></place>), with commercial advice (having
<lb n="171911"/>taken care of pence, the pounds having taken care of themselves). Leopold
<lb n="171912"/>Bloom (aged 6) had accompanied these narrations by constant consultation
<lb n="171913"/>of a geographical map of <place><placeName>Europe</placeName></place> (political) and by suggestions for the
<lb n="171914"/>establishment of affiliated business premises in the various centres
<lb n="171915"/>mentioned.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171916"/>Had time equally but differently obliterated the memory of these migrations
<lb n="171917"/>in narrator and listener?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171918"/>In narrator by the access of years and in consequence of the use of narcotic
<lb n="171919"/>toxin: in listener by the access of years and in consequence of the action of
<lb n="171920"/>distraction upon vicarious experiences.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171921"/>What idiosyncracies of the narrator were concomitant products of
<lb n="171922"/>amnesia?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171923"/>Occasionally he ate without having previously removed his hat.
<lb n="171924"/>Occasionally he drank voraciously the juice of gooseberry fool from an
<lb n="171925"/>inclined plate. Occasionally he removed from his lips the traces of food by
<lb n="171926"/>means of a lacerated envelope or other accessible fragment of paper.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171927"/>What two phenomena of senescence were more frequent?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171928"/>The myopic digital calculation of coins, eructation consequent upon
<lb n="171929"/>repletion.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171930"/>What object offered partial consolation for these reminiscences?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171931"/>The endowment policy, the bank passbook, the certificate of the possession
<lb n="171932"/>of scrip.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171933"/>Reduce Bloom by cross multiplication of reverses of fortune, from which
<lb n="171934"/>these supports protected him, and by elimination of all positive values to a
<lb n="171935"/>negligible negative irrational unreal quantity.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171936"/>Successively, in descending helotic order: Poverty: that of the outdoor
<lb n="171937"/>hawker of imitation jewellery, the dun for the recovery of bad and doubtful
<lb n="171938"/>debts, the poor rate and deputy cess collector. Mendicancy: that of the
<lb n="171939"/>fraudulent bankrupt with negligible assets paying ¼d in the £,
<lb n="171940"/>sandwichman, distributor of throwaways, nocturnal vagrant, insinuating
<lb n="171941"/>sycophant, maimed sailor, blind stripling, superannuated bailiff's man,
<lb n="171942"/>marfeast, lickplate, spoilsport, pickthank, eccentric public laughingstock
<lb n="171943"/>seated on bench of public park under discarded perforated umbrella.
<lb n="171944"/>Destitution: the inmate of Old Man's House (<place><placeName>Royal Hospital</placeName></place>),
<lb n="171945"/>Kilmainham, the inmate of <place><placeName>Simpson's Hospital</placeName></place> for reduced but respectable
<lb n="171946"/>men permanently disabled by gout or want of sight. Nadir of misery: the
<lb n="171947"/>aged impotent disfranchised ratesupported moribund lunatic pauper.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171948"/>With which attendant indignities?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171949"/>The unsympathetic indifference of previously amiable females, the contempt
<lb n="171950"/>of muscular males, the acceptance of fragments of bread, the simulated
<lb n="171951"/>ignorance of casual acquaintances, the latration of illegitimate unlicensed
<lb n="171952"/>vagabond dogs, the infantile discharge of decomposed vegetable missiles,
<lb n="171953"/>worth little or nothing, nothing or less than nothing.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171954"/>By what could such a situation be precluded?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171955"/>By decease (change of state): by departure (change of place).</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171956"/>Which preferably?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171957"/>The latter, by the line of least resistance.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171958"/>What considerations rendered departure not entirely undesirable?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171959"/>Constant cohabitation impeding mutual toleration of personal defects. The
<lb n="171960"/>habit of independent purchase increasingly cultivated. The necessity to
<lb n="171961"/>counteract by impermanent sojourn the permanence of arrest.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171962"/>What considerations rendered departure not irrational?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171963"/>The parties concerned, uniting, had increased and multiplied, which being
<lb n="171964"/>done, offspring produced and educed to maturity, the parties, if not
<lb n="171965"/>disunited were obliged to reunite for increase and multiplication, which was
<lb n="171966"/>absurd, to form by reunion the original couple of uniting parties, which was
<lb n="171967"/>impossible.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171968"/>What considerations rendered departure desirable?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171969"/>The attractive character of certain localities in <place type="country"><placeName>Ireland</placeName></place> and abroad, as
<lb n="171970"/>represented in general geographical maps of polychrome design or in
<lb n="171971"/>special ordnance survey charts by employment of scale numerals and
<lb n="171972"/>hachures.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171973"/>In <place type="country"><placeName>Ireland</placeName></place>?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171974"/>The <place><placeName>cliffs of Moher</placeName></place>, the windy wilds of <place><placeName>Connemara</placeName></place>, lough Neagh with
<lb n="171975"/>submerged petrified city, the Giant's Causeway, <place><placeName>Fort Camden</placeName></place> and <place><placeName>Fort
<lb n="171976"/>Carlisle</placeName></place>, the Golden Vale of Tipperary, the <place><placeName>islands of Aran</placeName></place>, the pastures of
<lb n="171977"/>royal <place><placeName>Meath</placeName></place>, Brigid's elm in <place><placeName>Kildare</placeName></place>, the <place><placeName>Queen's Island shipyard</placeName></place> in
<lb n="171978"/><place type="city"><placeName>Belfast</placeName></place>, the Salmon Leap, the lakes of <place><placeName>Killarney</placeName></place>.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171979"/>Abroad?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171980"/><place type="city"><placeName>Ceylon</placeName></place> (with spicegardens supplying tea to Thomas Kernan, agent for
<lb n="171981"/>Pulbrook, Robertson and Co, <place type="street"><placeName>2 Mincing Lane, London, E. C.</placeName></place>, <place type="street"><placeName>5 Dame
<lb n="171982"/>street, Dublin</placeName></place>), <place type="city"><placeName type="city">Jerusalem</placeName></place>, the holy city (with <place><placeName>mosque of Omar</placeName></place> and <place><placeName>gate of
<lb n="171983"/>Damascus</placeName></place>, goal of aspiration), the <place><placeName>straits of Gibraltar</placeName></place> (the unique
<lb n="171984"/>birthplace of Marion Tweedy), <place><placeName>the Parthenon</placeName></place> (containing statues of nude
<lb n="171985"/>Grecian divinities), the <place><placeName>Wall street money market</placeName></place> (which controlled
<lb n="171986"/>international finance), the <place><placeName>Plaza de Toros at La Linea, Spain</placeName></place> (where
<lb n="171987"/>O'Hara of the Camerons had slain the bull), <place><placeName>Niagara</placeName></place> (over which no
<lb n="171988"/>human being had passed with impunity), <place><placeName>the land of the Eskimos</placeName></place> (eaters of
<lb n="171989"/>soap), the forbidden country of <place type="country"><placeName>Thibet</placeName></place> (from which no traveller returns),
<lb n="171990"/>the bay of Naples (to see which was to die), the <place><placeName>Dead Sea</placeName></place>.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171991"/>Under what guidance, following what signs?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="171992"/>At sea, septentrional, by night the polestar, located at the point of
<lb n="171993"/>intersection of the right line from beta to alpha in Ursa Maior produced
<lb n="171994"/>and divided externally at omega and the hypotenuse of the rightangled
<lb n="171995"/>triangle formed by the line alpha omega so produced and the line alpha
<lb n="171996"/>delta of Ursa Maior. On land, meridional, a bispherical moon, revealed in
<lb n="171997"/>imperfect varying phases of lunation through the posterior interstice of the
<lb n="171998"/>imperfectly occluded skirt of a carnose negligent perambulating female, a
<lb n="171999"/>pillar of the cloud by day.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172000"/>What public advertisement would divulge the occultation of the departed?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172001"/>£5 reward, lost, stolen or strayed from his residence <place type="street"><placeName><num>7</num> Eccles street</placeName></place>, missing
<lb n="172002"/>gent about 40, answering to the name of Bloom, Leopold (Poldy), height
<lb n="172003"/>5 ft 9½ inches, full build, olive complexion, may have since grown a beard,
<lb n="172004"/>when last seen was wearing a black suit. Above sum will be paid for
<lb n="172005"/>information leading to his discovery.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172006"/>What universal binomial denominations would be his as entity and
<lb n="172007"/>nonentity?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172008"/>Assumed by any or known to none. Everyman or Noman.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172009"/>What tributes his?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172010"/>Honour and gifts of strangers, the friends of Everyman. A nymph
<lb n="172011"/>immortal, beauty, the bride of Noman.<note>"Noman" was the name Odysseus gave when the cyclops asked him what his name was in Homer's Odyssey.</note></p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172012"/>Would the departed never nowhere nohow reappear?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172013"/>Ever he would wander, selfcompelled, to the extreme limit of his cometary
<lb n="172014"/>orbit, beyond the fixed stars and variable suns and telescopic planets,
<lb n="172015"/>astronomical waifs and strays, to the extreme boundary of space, passing
<lb n="172016"/>from land to land, among peoples, amid events. Somewhere imperceptibly
<lb n="172017"/>he would hear and somehow reluctantly, suncompelled, obey the summons
<lb n="172018"/>of recall. Whence, disappearing from the constellation of the Northern
<lb n="172019"/>Crown he would somehow reappear reborn above delta in the constellation
<lb n="172020"/>of Cassiopeia and after incalculable eons of peregrination return an
<lb n="172021"/>estranged avenger, a wreaker of justice on malefactors, a dark crusader, a
<lb n="172022"/>sleeper awakened, with financial resources (by supposition) surpassing
<lb n="172023"/>those of Rothschild or the silver king.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172024"/>What would render such return irrational?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172025"/>An unsatisfactory equation between an exodus and return in time through
<lb n="172026"/>reversible space and an exodus and return in space through irreversible
<lb n="172027"/>time.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172028"/>What play of forces, inducing inertia, rendered departure undesirable?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172029"/>The lateness of the hour, rendering procrastinatory: the obscurity of the
<lb n="172030"/>night, rendering invisible: the uncertainty of thoroughfares, rendering
<lb n="172031"/>perilous: the necessity for repose, obviating movement: the proximity of an
<lb n="172032"/>occupied bed, obviating research: the anticipation of warmth (human)
<lb n="172033"/>tempered with coolness (linen), obviating desire and rendering desirable:
<lb n="172034"/>the statue of Narcissus, sound without echo, desired desire.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172035"/>What advantages were possessed by an occupied, as distinct from an
<lb n="172036"/>unoccupied bed?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172037"/>The removal of nocturnal solitude, the superior quality of human (mature
<lb n="172038"/>female) to inhuman (hotwaterjar) calefaction, the stimulation of matutinal
<lb n="172039"/>contact, the economy of mangling done on the premises in the case of
<lb n="172040"/>trousers accurately folded and placed lengthwise between the spring
<lb n="172041"/>mattress (striped) and the woollen mattress (biscuit section).</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172042"/>What past consecutive causes, before rising preapprehended, of
<lb n="172043"/>accumulated fatigue did Bloom, before rising, silently recapitulate?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172044"/>The preparation of breakfast (burnt offering): intestinal congestion and
<lb n="172045"/>premeditative defecation (holy of holies): the bath (rite of John): the
<lb n="172046"/>funeral (rite of Samuel): the advertisement of Alexander Keyes (Urim and
<lb n="172047"/>Thummim): the unsubstantial lunch (rite of Melchisedek): the visit to
<lb n="172048"/>museum and national library (holy place): the bookhunt along <place><placeName>Bedford
<lb n="172049"/>row</placeName></place>, <place><placeName>Merchants' Arch</placeName></place>, <place><placeName>Wellington Quay</placeName></place> (Simchath Torah): the music in
<lb n="172050"/>the <place><placeName>Ormond Hotel</placeName></place> (Shira Shirim): the altercation with a truculent
<lb n="172051"/>troglodyte in <place><placeName>Bernard Kiernan's premises</placeName></place> (holocaust): a blank period of
<lb n="172052"/>time including a cardrive, a visit to a house of mourning, a leavetaking
<lb n="172053"/>(wilderness): the eroticism produced by feminine exhibitionism (rite of
<lb n="172054"/>Onan): the prolonged delivery of Mrs Mina Purefoy (heave offering): the
<lb n="172055"/>visit to the disorderly house of Mrs Bella Cohen, <place type="street"><placeName><num>82</num> Tyrone street, lower</placeName></place>,
<lb n="172056"/>and subsequent brawl and chance medley in <place><placeName>Beaver street</placeName></place> (Armageddon):
<lb n="172057"/>nocturnal perambulation to and from the cabman's shelter, <place><placeName>Butt Bridge</placeName></place>
<lb n="172058"/>(atonement).</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172059"/>What selfimposed enigma did Bloom about to rise in order to go so as to
<lb n="172060"/>conclude lest he should not conclude involuntarily apprehend?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172061"/>The cause of a brief sharp unforeseen heard loud lone crack emitted by the
<lb n="172062"/>insentient material of a strainveined timber table.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172063"/>What selfinvolved enigma did Bloom risen, going, gathering multicoloured
<lb n="172064"/>multiform multitudinous garments, voluntarily apprehending, not
<lb n="172065"/>comprehend?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172066"/>Who was M'Intosh?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172067"/>What selfevident enigma pondered with desultory constancy during 30
<lb n="172068"/>years did Bloom now, having effected natural obscurity by the extinction of
<lb n="172069"/>artificial light, silently suddenly comprehend?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172070"/>Where was Moses when the candle went out?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172071"/>What imperfections in a perfect day did Bloom, walking, charged with
<lb n="172072"/>collected articles of recently disvested male wearing apparel, silently,
<lb n="172073"/>successively, enumerate?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172074"/>A provisional failure to obtain renewal of an advertisement: to obtain a
<lb n="172075"/>certain quantity of tea from Thomas Kernan (agent for Pulbrook,
<lb n="172076"/>Robertson and Co, <place type="street"><placeName>5 Dame Street, Dublin</placeName></place>, and <place><placeName>2 Mincing Lane, London
<lb n="172077"/>E. C.</placeName></place>): to certify the presence or absence of posterior rectal orifice in the
<lb n="172078"/>case of Hellenic female divinities: to obtain admission (gratuitous or paid)
<lb n="172079"/>to the performance of <title type="play">Leah</title> by Mrs Bandmann Palmer at the <place type="street"><placeName>Gaiety
<lb n="172080"/>Theatre, 46, 47, 48, 49 South King street</placeName></place>.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172081"/>What impression of an absent face did Bloom, arrested, silently recall?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172082"/>The face of her father, the late Major Brian Cooper Tweedy, Royal Dublin
<lb n="172083"/>Fusiliers, of Gibraltar and Rehoboth, Dolphin's Barn.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172084"/>What recurrent impressions of the same were possible by hypothesis?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172085"/>Retreating, at the terminus of the Great Northern Railway, <place type="street"><placeName>Amiens street</placeName></place>,
<lb n="172086"/>with constant uniform acceleration, along parallel lines meeting at infinity,
<lb n="172087"/>if produced: along parallel lines, reproduced from infinity, with constant
<lb n="172088"/>uniform retardation, at the terminus of the Great Northern Railway,
<lb n="172089"/>Amiens street, returning.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172090"/>What miscellaneous effects of female personal wearing apparel were
<lb n="172091"/>perceived by him?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172092"/>A pair of new inodorous halfsilk black ladies' hose, a pair of new violet
<lb n="172093"/>garters, a pair of outsize ladies' drawers of India mull, cut on generous
<lb n="172094"/>lines, redolent of opoponax, jessamine and Muratti's Turkish cigarettes and
<lb n="172095"/>containing a long bright steel safety pin, folded curvilinear, a camisole of
<lb n="172096"/>batiste with thin lace border, an accordion underskirt of blue silk moirette,
<lb n="172097"/>all these objects being disposed irregularly on the top of a rectangular
<lb n="172098"/>trunk, quadruple battened, having capped corners, with multicoloured
<lb n="172099"/>labels, initialled on its fore side in white lettering B. C. T. (Brian Cooper
<lb n="172100"/>Tweedy).</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172101"/>What impersonal objects were perceived?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172102"/>A commode, one leg fractured, totally covered by square cretonne cutting,
<lb n="172103"/>apple design, on which rested a lady's black straw hat. Orangekeyed ware,
<lb n="172104"/>bought of Henry Price, basket, fancy goods, chinaware and ironmongery
<lb n="172105"/>manufacturer, <place type="street"><placeName>21, 22, 23 Moore street</placeName></place>, disposed irregularly on the
<lb n="172106"/>washstand and floor and consisting of basin, soapdish and brushtray (on
<lb n="172107"/>the washstand, together), pitcher and night article (on the floor, separate).</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172108"/>Bloom's acts?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172109"/>He deposited the articles of clothing on a chair, removed his remaining
<lb n="172110"/>articles of clothing, took from beneath the bolster at the head of the bed a
<lb n="172111"/>folded long white nightshirt, inserted his head and arms into the proper
<lb n="172112"/>apertures of the nightshirt, removed a pillow from the head to the foot of
<lb n="172113"/>the bed, prepared the bedlinen accordingly and entered the bed.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172114"/>How?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172115"/>With circumspection, as invariably when entering an abode (his own or not
<lb n="172116"/>his own): with solicitude, the snakespiral springs of the mattress being old,
<lb n="172117"/>the brass quoits and pendent viper radii loose and tremulous under stress
<lb n="172118"/>and strain: prudently, as entering a lair or ambush of lust or adders: lightly,
<lb n="172119"/>the less to disturb: reverently, the bed of conception and of birth, of
<lb n="172120"/>consummation of marriage and of breach of marriage, of sleep and of
<lb n="172121"/>death.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172122"/>What did his limbs, when gradually extended, encounter?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172123"/>New clean bedlinen, additional odours, the presence of a human form,
<lb n="172124"/>female, hers, the imprint of a human form, male, not his, some crumbs,
<lb n="172125"/>some flakes of potted meat, recooked, which he removed.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172126"/>If he had smiled why would he have smiled?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172127"/>To reflect that each one who enters imagines himself to be the first to enter
<lb n="172128"/>whereas he is always the last term of a preceding series even if the first term
<lb n="172129"/>of a succeeding one, each imagining himself to be first, last, only and alone
<lb n="172130"/>whereas he is neither first nor last nor only nor alone in a series originating
<lb n="172131"/>in and repeated to infinity.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172132"/>What preceding series?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172133"/>Assuming Mulvey to be the first term of his series, Penrose, Bartell d'Arcy,
<lb n="172134"/>professor Goodwin, Julius Mastiansky, John Henry Menton, Father
<lb n="172135"/>Bernard Corrigan, a farmer at the Royal Dublin Society's Horse Show,
<lb n="172136"/>Maggot O'Reilly, Matthew Dillon, Valentine Blake Dillon (Lord Mayor of
<lb n="172137"/>Dublin), Christopher Callinan, Lenehan, an Italian organgrinder, an
<lb n="172138"/>unknown gentleman in the Gaiety Theatre, Benjamin Dollard, Simon
<lb n="172139"/>Dedalus, Andrew (Pisser) Burke, Joseph Cuffe, Wisdom Hely, Alderman
<lb n="172140"/>John Hooper, Dr Francis Brady, Father Sebastian of Mount Argus, a
<lb n="172141"/>bootblack at the General Post Office, Hugh E. (Blazes) Boylan and so each
<lb n="172142"/>and so on to no last term.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172143"/>What were his reflections concerning the last member of this series and late
<lb n="172144"/>occupant of the bed?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172145"/>Reflections on his vigour (a bounder), corporal proportion (a billsticker),
<lb n="172146"/>commercial ability (a bester), impressionability (a boaster).</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172147"/>Why for the observer impressionability in addition to vigour, corporal
<lb n="172148"/>proportion and commercial ability?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172149"/>Because he had observed with augmenting frequency in the preceding
<lb n="172150"/>members of the same series the same concupiscence, inflammably
<lb n="172151"/>transmitted, first with alarm, then with understanding, then with desire,
<lb n="172152"/>finally with fatigue, with alternating symptoms of epicene comprehension
<lb n="172153"/>and apprehension.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172154"/>With what antagonistic sentiments were his subsequent reflections affected?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172155"/>Envy, jealousy, abnegation, equanimity.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172156"/>Envy?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172157"/>Of a bodily and mental male organism specially adapted for the
<lb n="172158"/>superincumbent posture of energetic human copulation and energetic piston
<lb n="172159"/>and cylinder movement necessary for the complete satisfaction of a constant
<lb n="172160"/>but not acute concupiscence resident in a bodily and mental female
<lb n="172161"/>organism, passive but not obtuse.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172162"/>Jealousy?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172163"/>Because a nature full and volatile in its free state, was alternately the agent
<lb n="172164"/>and reagent of attraction. Because attraction between agent(s) and
<lb n="172165"/>reagent(s) at all instants varied, with inverse proportion of increase and
<lb n="172166"/>decrease, with incessant circular extension and radial reentrance. Because
<lb n="172167"/>the controlled contemplation of the fluctuation of attraction produced, if
<lb n="172168"/>desired, a fluctuation of pleasure.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172169"/>Abnegation?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172170"/>In virtue of a) acquaintance initiated in September 1903 in the establishment
<lb n="172171"/>of George Mesias, merchant tailor and outfitter, <place type="street"><placeName>5 Eden Quay</placeName></place>, b) hospitality
<lb n="172172"/>extended and received in kind, reciprocated and reappropriated in person,
<lb n="172173"/>c) comparative youth subject to impulses of ambition and magnanimity,
<lb n="172174"/>colleagual altruism and amorous egoism, d) extraracial attraction,
<lb n="172175"/>intraracial inhibition, supraracial prerogative, e) an imminent provincial
<lb n="172176"/>musical tour, common current expenses, net proceeds divided.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172177"/>Equanimity?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172178"/>As as natural as any and every natural act of a nature expressed or
<lb n="172179"/>understood executed in natured nature by natural creatures in accordance
<lb n="172180"/>with his, her and their natured natures, of dissimilar similarity. As not so
<lb n="172181"/>calamitous as a cataclysmic annihilation of the planet in consequence of a
<lb n="172182"/>collision with a dark sun. As less reprehensible than theft, highway robbery,
<lb n="172183"/>cruelty to children and animals, obtaining money under false pretences,
<lb n="172184"/>forgery, embezzlement, misappropriation of public money, betrayal of
<lb n="172185"/>public trust, malingering, mayhem, corruption of minors, criminal libel,
<lb n="172186"/>blackmail, contempt of court, arson, treason, felony, mutiny on the high
<lb n="172187"/>seas, trespass, burglary, jailbreaking, practice of unnatural vice, desertion
<lb n="172188"/>from armed forces in the field, perjury, poaching, usury, intelligence with
<lb n="172189"/>the king's enemies, impersonation, criminal assault, manslaughter, wilful
<lb n="172190"/>and premeditated murder. As not more abnormal than all other parallel
<lb n="172191"/>processes of adaptation to altered conditions of existence, resulting in a
<lb n="172192"/>reciprocal equilibrium between the bodily organism and its attendant
<lb n="172193"/>circumstances, foods, beverages, acquired habits, indulged inclinations,
<lb n="172194"/>significant disease. As more than inevitable, irreparable.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172195"/>Why more abnegation than jealousy, less envy than equanimity?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172196"/>From outrage (matrimony) to outrage (adultery) there arose nought but
<lb n="172197"/>outrage (copulation) yet the matrimonial violator of the matrimonially
<lb n="172198"/>violated had not been outraged by the adulterous violator of the
<lb n="172199"/>adulterously violated.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172200"/>What retribution, if any?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172201"/>Assassination, never, as two wrongs did not make one right. Duel by
<lb n="172202"/>combat, no. Divorce, not now. Exposure by mechanical artifice (automatic
<lb n="172203"/>bed) or individual testimony (concealed ocular witnesses), not yet. Suit for
<lb n="172204"/>damages by legal influence or simulation of assault with evidence of injuries
<lb n="172205"/>sustained (selfinflicted), not impossibly. Hushmoney by moral influence,
<lb n="172206"/>possibly. If any, positively, connivance, introduction of emulation (material,
<lb n="172207"/>a prosperous rival agency of publicity: moral, a successful rival agent of
<lb n="172208"/>intimacy), depreciation, alienation, humiliation, separation protecting the
<lb n="172209"/>one separated from the other, protecting the separator from both.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172210"/>By what reflections did he, a conscious reactor against the void of
<lb n="172211"/>incertitude, justify to himself his sentiments?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172212"/>The preordained frangibility of the hymen: the presupposed intangibility of
<lb n="172213"/>the thing in itself: the incongruity and disproportion between the
<lb n="172214"/>selfprolonging tension of the thing proposed to be done and the
<lb n="172215"/>selfabbreviating relaxation of the thing done: the fallaciously inferred
<lb n="172216"/>debility of the female: the muscularity of the male: the variations of ethical
<lb n="172217"/>codes: the natural grammatical transition by inversion involving no
<lb n="172218"/>alteration of sense of an aorist preterite proposition (parsed as masculine
<lb n="172219"/>subject, monosyllabic onomatopoeic transitive verb with direct feminine
<lb n="172220"/>object) from the active voice into its correlative aorist preterite proposition
<lb n="172221"/>(parsed as feminine subject, auxiliary verb and quasimonosyllabic
<lb n="172222"/>onomatopoeic past participle with complementary masculine agent) in the
<lb n="172223"/>passive voice: the continued product of seminators by generation: the
<lb n="172224"/>continual production of semen by distillation: the futility of triumph or
<lb n="172225"/>protest or vindication: the inanity of extolled virtue: the lethargy of nescient
<lb n="172226"/>matter: the apathy of the stars.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172227"/>In what final satisfaction did these antagonistic sentiments and reflections,
<lb n="172228"/>reduced to their simplest forms, converge?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172229"/>Satisfaction at the ubiquity in eastern and western terrestrial hemispheres,
<lb n="172230"/>in all habitable lands and islands explored or unexplored (the land of the
<lb n="172231"/>midnight sun, the islands of the blessed, the isles of <place type="country"><placeName>Greece</placeName></place>, the land of
<lb n="172232"/>promise), of adipose anterior and posterior female hemispheres, redolent of
<lb n="172233"/>milk and honey and of excretory sanguine and seminal warmth, reminiscent
<lb n="172234"/>of secular families of curves of amplitude, insusceptible of moods of
<lb n="172235"/>impression or of contrarieties of expression, expressive of mute immutable
<lb n="172236"/>mature animality.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172237"/>The visible signs of antesatisfaction?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172238"/>An approximate erection: a solicitous adversion: a gradual elevation: a
<lb n="172239"/>tentative revelation: a silent contemplation.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172240"/>Then?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172241"/>He kissed the plump mellow yellow smellow melons of her rump, on each
<lb n="172242"/>plump melonous hemisphere, in their mellow yellow furrow, with obscure
<lb n="172243"/>prolonged provocative melonsmellonous osculation.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172244"/>The visible signs of postsatisfaction?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172245"/>A silent contemplation: a tentative velation: a gradual abasement: a
<lb n="172246"/>solicitous aversion: a proximate erection.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172247"/>What followed this silent action?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172248"/>Somnolent invocation, less somnolent recognition, incipient excitation,
<lb n="172249"/>catechetical interrogation.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172250"/>With what modifications did the narrator reply to this interrogation?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172251"/>Negative: he omitted to mention the clandestine correspondence between
<lb n="172252"/>Martha Clifford and Henry Flower, the public altercation at, in and in the
<lb n="172253"/>vicinity of the licensed premises of Bernard Kiernan and Co, Limited, <place type="street"><placeName>8, 9
<lb n="172254"/>and 10 Little Britain street</placeName></place>, the erotic provocation and response thereto
<lb n="172255"/>caused by the exhibitionism of Gertrude (Gerty), surname unknown.
<lb n="172256"/>Positive: he included mention of a performance by Mrs Bandmann Palmer
<lb n="172257"/>of <title type="play">Leah</title> at the Gaiety Theatre, <place type="street"><placeName>46, 47, 48, 49 South King street</placeName></place>, an
<lb n="172258"/>invitation to supper at Wynn's (Murphy's) Hotel, <place type="street"><placeName>35, 36 and 37 Lower
<lb n="172259"/>Abbey street</placeName></place>, a volume of peccaminous pornographical tendency entituled
<lb n="172260"/><title type="book">Sweets of Sin</title>, anonymous author a gentleman of fashion, a temporary
<lb n="172261"/>concussion caused by a falsely calculated movement in the course of a
<lb n="172262"/>postcenal gymnastic display, the victim (since completely recovered) being
<lb n="172263"/>Stephen Dedalus, professor and author, eldest surviving son of Simon
<lb n="172264"/>Dedalus, of no fixed occupation, an aeronautical feat executed by him
<lb n="172265"/>(narrator) in the presence of a witness, the professor and author aforesaid,
<lb n="172266"/>with promptitude of decision and gymnastic flexibility.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172267"/>Was the narration otherwise unaltered by modifications?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172268"/>Absolutely.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172269"/>Which event or person emerged as the salient point of his narration?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172270"/>Stephen Dedalus, professor and author.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172271"/>What limitations of activity and inhibitions of conjugal rights were
<lb n="172272"/>perceived by listener and narrator concerning themselves during the course
<lb n="172273"/>of this intermittent and increasingly more laconic narration?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172274"/>By the listener a limitation of fertility inasmuch as marriage had been
<lb n="172275"/>celebrated 1 calendar month after the 18th anniversary of her birth (8
<lb n="172276"/>September 1870), viz. 8 October, and consummated on the same date with
<lb n="172277"/>female issue born 15 June 1889, having been anticipatorily consummated on
<lb n="172278"/>the 10 September of the same year and complete carnal intercourse, with
<lb n="172279"/>ejaculation of semen within the natural female organ, having last taken
<lb n="172280"/>place 5 weeks previous, viz. 27 November 1893, to the birth on 29
<lb n="172281"/>December 1893 of second (and only male) issue, deceased 9 January 1894,
<lb n="172282"/>aged 11 days, there remained a period of 10 years, 5 months and 18 days
<lb n="172283"/>during which carnal intercourse had been incomplete, without ejaculation
<lb n="172284"/>of semen within the natural female organ. By the narrator a limitation of
<lb n="172285"/>activity, mental and corporal, inasmuch as complete mental intercourse
<lb n="172286"/>between himself and the listener had not taken place since the
<lb n="172287"/>consummation of puberty, indicated by catamenic hemorrhage, of the
<lb n="172288"/>female issue of narrator and listener, 15 September 1903, there remained a
<lb n="172289"/>period of 9 months and 1 day during which, in consequence of a
<lb n="172290"/>preestablished natural comprehension in incomprehension between the
<lb n="172291"/>consummated females (listener and issue), complete corporal liberty of
<lb n="172292"/>action had been circumscribed.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172293"/>How?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172294"/>By various reiterated feminine interrogation concerning the masculine
<lb n="172295"/>destination whither, the place where, the time at which, the duration for
<lb n="172296"/>which, the object with which in the case of temporary absences, projected
<lb n="172297"/>or effected.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172298"/>What moved visibly above the listener's and the narrator's invisible
<lb n="172299"/>thoughts?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172300"/>The upcast reflection of a lamp and shade, an inconstant series of
<lb n="172301"/>concentric circles of varying gradations of light and shadow.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172302"/>In what directions did listener and narrator lie?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172303"/>Listener, S. E. by E.: Narrator, N. W. by W.: on the <place><placeName>53rd parallel of
<lb n="172304"/>latitude, N., and 6th meridian of longitude, W.</placeName></place>: at an angle of 45° to the
<lb n="172305"/>terrestrial equator.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172306"/>In what state of rest or motion?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172307"/>At rest relatively to themselves and to each other. In motion being each and
<lb n="172308"/>both carried westward, forward and rereward respectively, by the proper
<lb n="172309"/>perpetual motion of the earth through everchanging tracks of
<lb n="172310"/>neverchanging space.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172311"/>In what posture?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172312"/>Listener: reclined semilaterally, left, left hand under head, right leg extended
<lb n="172313"/>in a straight line and resting on left leg, flexed, in the attitude of Gea-Tellus,
<lb n="172314"/>fulfilled, recumbent, big with seed. Narrator: reclined laterally, left, with
<lb n="172315"/>right and left legs flexed, the indexfinger and thumb of the right hand
<lb n="172316"/>resting on the bridge of the nose, in the attitude depicted in a snapshot
<lb n="172317"/>photograph made by Percy Apjohn, the childman weary, the manchild in
<lb n="172318"/>the womb.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172319"/>Womb? Weary?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172320"/>He rests. He has travelled.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172321"/>With?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172322" xml:id="lb_172322"/>Sinbad the Sailor and Tinbad the Tailor and Jinbad the Jailer and Whinbad
<lb n="172323"/>the Whaler and Ninbad the Nailer and Finbad the Failer and Binbad the
<lb n="172324"/>Bailer and Pinbad the Pailer and Minbad the Mailer and Hinbad the Hailer
<lb n="172325"/>and Rinbad the Railer and Dinbad the Kailer and Vinbad the Quailer and
<lb n="172326"/>Linbad the Yailer and Xinbad the Phthailer.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172327"/>When?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172328"/>Going to dark bed there was a square round Sinbad the Sailor roc's auk's
<lb n="172329"/>egg in the night of the bed of all the auks of the rocs of Darkinbad the
<lb n="172330"/>Brightdayler.</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172331"/>Where?</p>
<p rend="non-indent"><lb n="172332"/>●</p>
</div> <!-- End of Episode 17, "Ithaca" -->
